Another data type that we want to look
at is the VAR data type. If you look at
it, the VAR type is the generic property
type that can refer to any data type. So
basically what you can do, you can also
use a var to store this integer, you can
use a var to store a boolean data type,
you can use the VAR to store any value
and it's going to work. It is very useful
when you don't know the data type that
you are dealing with. So to play with it
I am going to copy these examples here
in the documentation and play with them
in our code. Okay so I'm going to copy
this. This is the beauty of working with
QT creator. There are tons and tons of
pieces of code you can copy and use in
your application. And this is not a bad
thing. If you wonder how I align this
thing I just hit ctrl+A, ctrl+I to have
this things aligned. And if you see here
you see that there are warnings telling
us that we should use specific data
types instead of using the VAR data type
here. Okay it says you should use int
or real instead of var, bool instead of var,
string instead of var. But you can see
that var can store integers, boolean,
strings. You can see that we can define
our own string using this JavaScript
constructor. We can define colors we are
going to play with these variables and
try to output some information about
them, we're going to start with this
number here and show you that you can
output it just like you did for these
numbers here. So let's do that, we're
going to console.log let's separate
things a little bit so we're going to
say console.log the value of what is it
called again.
let's look aNumber is aNumber. And if
we run this we should see the value that
is stored here which is 100,
100 here. We can do the same thing
for bool, string and this string here. So
I'm going to do this and come back and
show you these things running. Okay I
went ahead and typed this things to save
you some time.
We're going to output the boolean data
type, string and another string that we
initialized using the constructor here.
Let's run the application, mm-hmm you see
the bool is false, the value of a string
is hello world which is here and the
other string has this thing here and you
see that we output it without a problem.
Var can also be used to store other more
complex data types for example a color
so this is a color for example and we
are storing it as a var. You can see that
they are giving us a warning that we
should use the color datatype instead of
var but var can store this too so it is
possible to use it if you need to use it
this way.
To show you that you can use this color
we're going to use it to set the
background of this rectangle here. So we
can take out this yellow here and say aColor
and it's going to work. Let's run
the application, we are going to see this
color. Mm-hmm this is the color. We
can change it again we can play with
these numbers. What this is really doing
it is changing the components of the
color, this is the red component, this is
the green component, this is the blue
component and this is the opacity. You
can look at the documentation for the
color qml type to have more information
about this. Let's turn the others to zero
make the opacity one to make it
completely opaque and make it completely
red. Run the application, we should have a
red background on our text here which is
what we have. Ok so let's turn it back
because this red is really annoying.
There's another data type that is called
rect that you used to represent
rectangles let's go back to the doc and
show you this thing, rect. The rect
type refers to a value with X, Y, width
and height. It really represents a
rectangle. So to show you the properties
inside this thing I'm going to output
this component. Okay so let's go back
to our oncompleted method here and say
console.log - a rect height - okay you can
access these things I think this is
correct. And let's change the values to
not make it completely square. So let's
change this to 17, change this to 56,
change this to 46, change this to leave
this to a ten, no problem. Let's run the
application, this is X, this is y ,this is
the width, this is the height. Okay and you
can see that X is 17 Y, is 56, width is 46
and height is 10 which is what we
specified. You can access these values.
There's another data type that is called
point. Let's go to the documentation
and see what it is about. Okay it refers
to a value with X&Y attributes you can
use it to store pairs of data with one
being X and the other being Y. I'm not
going to show you how to output this
things because it really is the same. So
size is the another data type that
refers to value with width and height.
And if you look at this you can see that
rectangle really groups point and size
into one thing. These are some other data
types you can use. You can check them out
if you are interested but for now we are
going to play with this array data type
and this function here. If you look at
this array it is storing different data
types these are integers, these are
strings. Okay if you look here this is a
function you can do this thing's in
JavaScript if you have been programming
in languages like C, C++ or Java. You're
going to find this a little bit weird
because usually you don't put different
data types in array but you can do this
in JavaScript. So what we're going to do,
we're going to play with this array. For
example we can output its length if you
look at its contents this is one - two -
three - four - five - six elements in the
array. So if we want to output that we
can do something like console.log ("the
length of the array is, what is it called
again I forgot, anArray. So let's do that
and you can see that you can output its
length. Let's run the application. Hmm the
length is 6, we have 6 elements in the
array. What if you want to output these
elements in the array? What you can do is
loop through all these elements and
output them. The way you do that, this is
really JavaScript knowledge, so if you
find this a little bit confusing you
should consider it looking at some
JavaScript tutorial to get these basics,
but if you have some programming
experience this is really nothing new.
What you can do is say anArray and say
forEach and inside passing a callback
function. So the way you do that you say
function and you say value this is going
to be the value that you are working on.
So we put this on a separate line and
what we can do inside we can output this
value here. So what this is doing is
really looping through the array and at
each iteration it is storing the value
of the element we are at in the array in
this variable here called value so we
can output it. To prove our case let's do
console.log(value).
Just to show you that we are
retrieving the values in the array. If we
run the application we should see them 1
2 3 four five and we have function here, what
the heck is this? We are seeing function
here because the last element in the
array is a function. If we wanted this
function to print the returned value
here which is six we would need to call
this as a function and the way we could
do that is to also pass in the index as
a second parameter in our function. And
say if (index === 5) console.log (value())
and call this as a function, if it's not
equal to 5 we're going to do the usual
thing we've done before console.log(value).
I know this might sound cryptic
for people who are not familiar with
JavaScript but if you take some tutorial
or some course on JavaScript this is
going to make sense. We are actually
checking to see if we are dealing with
this value here if we are dealing with
this value here we call it as a function
notice this set of parentheses we put
here and if it's another element we just
output it. So if we run again we should
see the output as expected one through
six. And you see that six is output here.
This is one way to output the element of
the array that you have if you don't
like this notation we can use a regular
for loop that you also have in other
programming languages. I also take this
chance to show you that you can do
comments in qml. Okay this is
multiple lines comment you can also do
comments like this for example if you
want to comment this line you can use
these two slashes like this to comment
it out. Okay it's not going to be
processed when this application is being
compiled. So we comment this out
and we can say for (var i = 0; I < anArray.length; i++)
less than the length of the array so
we're going to say anArray.length and
increment this thing and if we are at
index 5 we are going to retrieve the
current item. This is how you retrieve it
you put in the name of the array
you got the square brackets and inside
you put the index and you call this as a
function also by putting parentheses
like we did on top here. And if we are
not dealing with the index number 5 we
just do the normal thing and output the
array element at this index. If we run
the application we are going to see the
same thing. Ok 1 through six. You can use
whatever notation you see it fit many
people are going to like this one
because it is familiar but this can come
in handy and be very easy to understand
if you start getting familiar with
JavaScript. I currently like to use this
one. Ok by now we have seen multiple uses
for the VAR data type but there are two
other data types that I want you to see
one is the font data type that you used
to store font information for your text.
So if you want to know more about the
font data type you can come to the
documentation and search for font. It's
this easy. If you go down you're going to
find the font qml data type and you can
see all the information about it and the
properties that you can set to them. And
if you want to set this font as your
font in the text you can do that very
easily. You can comment this out for
example and say font : aFont.
Let's run again and you see that the
font has changed. This is the font that
we have defined here that we are using.
Okay you can specify the font family its
size whether or not it's bold. For
example if we change this to false and
run again.
It's not going to be bold again.Okay you
seen this. Another property that you can
use in qml is the date property.
You use it when you are dealing with
time information and you can specify a
date like this. Okay for example if we go
in the oncompleted method of ours here,
we can say console.log mDate. Let's run
and see what we're going to see. You see
that it shows full information of the
date in my locale here. Okay it's in
Chinese because my local is in Chinese
right now but what I want to show you is
that you can call all kinds of methods
on this date object. For example you can
get date, get day, get full year, these are
methods that are documented in the data
object in the JavaScript documentation. I
am going to talk fully about the way you
use JavaScript in your code when I talk
about JavaScript integration with qml
but right now I just want you to get a
hang of what is available and how you
can use it. And it really is impossible
to talk about qml without using
javascript, it's just going to be dealed
you need to see some JavaScript even if
we haven't got to talk about JavaScript
in qml yet. The last thing we're
going to see is this function here, you
can actually assign a function to a
variable and call it as a function. So
what we can do is go down here and say
console.log
and call it. Okay we'd like to say
aFunction and call it like this. If you
don't put the parentheses you're going
to see the same thing we saw when we
called the last element of the array,
which was a function. You're going to see
that it is a function but it's not going
to show you the value so you need to put
these parentheses to actually get the
function to do what it's meant to do.
Let's run the application again and
you're going to see that the function
value is one which is what is being
returned here. For example if you return
Seven and run again it's going to say the
function value is 7. And take care to see
the syntax here it might be corrected to
some people but it is just a way to put
this things on one line and it makes
things a little bit easier to see. For
now this covers all we set out to do in
this lecture. I hope you now have a
pretty good idea of the data types that
are available for you to work with in
qml and how you can use some of these
data types to affect the code and make
things a little bit neater. In the next
lecture we are going to explore a very
strong concept in qml which is property
binding. I'll see you in the next lecture.