In this lecture we're going to look at
qml basic types. Before we start looking
at the data types in QML I'd like to go
in the documentation in qt creator
and show you somethings. You go to the
documentation by clicking on this help
tab here. And in the search bar here make
sure that you have index selected like
me here if you want to see exactly the
same things I'm saying. And in here type
qml basic types. Okay you are going to see
some choices here.
We're going to choose the second one
here and we're going to look at it. If
you look the title says qml basic types
and down here they show you the basic
types that we're going to look at.
There is boolean data types, there is
double, enumeration, integer and lists
real, string and all these things. Right
now we're going to create a qml project
and play with these things. So we're going to
start a new project, it's going to be a
qt quick application an empty one. We're
going to call it qmlDatatypesDemo.
We're going to save it in a location on
our drive, hit next, choose our build
system as qmake and you choose the
lastest version of Qt have installed. We
choose the desktop kit and finish. After
this we're going to have our starter
project. We're going to change the title
here and make it say QML Datatypes Demo.
Because we don't want an empty project,
we're going to put a rectangle in the
middle. We're going to give it a width of
200 and a height of 100 why not. And
inside the rectangle we're going to put
a text element the id is going to be
mTextId and the text is going to say
hello world. If you look here you see the
text is wrapped into this qsTr function,
it is a function that helps when you
want to translate your application into
multiple languages. We're not going to go
into that right now just take this as if
it was
piece of text that we put here. We want
to Center this rectangle in the parent
so we're going to say anchors.centerIn: parent.
And we want to give it a color of
yellow so that it is visible. We also
want to anchor this text in the center
of the rectangle to have thing lay out
nicely so let's do that we're going to
copy that property and paste it here, we
can do that. Let's run the application
and see what it looks like. Mm-hmm, you
see we have hello world in the middle
this is our design. From the last lecture
you must be starting to be familiar with
this thing. These are the properties for
our window element, inside we have a
rectangle and the rectangle has a child
of its own which is this text element
here. Okay you can put in any properties
that this element supports, and if you
want to look at the documentation for
any element. You can select it hit f1 and
you're going to be taken into the
documentation on the right here. If you
want to show the help mode in full, you
can click on this button here "Open in help mode"
and it's going to show the
documentation for that element. In this
case it is the text element. But we're
going to look at this later in the
course. Let's go back to our project. The
first thing I want to do is to create
this string data type how do I do that,
I say property string I'm going to call
this mString and let it say hello world
why not. One thing I can do with this
string is really assign it to anything.
Okay so the first thing I can do I can
assign it as the text of this text
element. So let's do that, I can do
something like this.
Sorry and if I run it guess what we are
going to see in the middle, Hello World.
A variable here is being assigned to the
text element right here. The other thing
we can do is show this string in a log
statement when this widow component here
has been loaded. So we're going to say
component, we've done this before
oncompleted and we can say console.log
the value of mString is and then
we're going to say to your mString. If
run the application we're going to see
this message here and the value is going
to be hello world and we're also going
to see hello world in this text element
here. Let's run the application hello
world the value of mString is Hello World
in the application output panel
here. Okay so you should really notice
this console.log thing it is a way that
JavaScript gives you to output log
messages. There is another one you can
use which is called print and we can say
print. And if we run we're going to see
the same thing.
Okay the value of mString is Hello World.
Now that you've seen how to work
with the string datatype we can try
other ones. So let's try an integer so
we're going to say property int it's
going to be called
mInt and let's call this 45. Okay you can
also output this console.log the value
of mInt. If we run the application we're going
to see that okay it's 45. And you can
work with this value in your application
whenever you need an integer value. For
example we can add this to the height of
our middle rectangle here. So we can say
mInt and add it like this. And if we run
we're going to see the rectangle become
a little bit bigger in height. Another
data type we want to look at is a
boolean data type. So we
going to say property bool let's call
this isFemale and say false. In the
oncompleted method here we can do some
tests. Let's say if (isFemale) do a console.log
for example and say else if it's not
a female we're going to say console log
you may wear a suit. Okay so let's run the
application you may wear a suit because
you're not a female. Remember isFemale is
false here so let's change this to true
run again and you may wear a dress
because you are a female, isFemale is true
here. So you can also use this property
in your code. Let's change this text here
to bold if we are dealing with a female,
how do we do that.
So we can say font.bold, it's a property
of the text element and we can put a
value here for example true okay to make
it bold.
If you run we're going to see the text
become bold. Okay it's bold but we can
make this depend on this boolean
property that we had here. So we're going
to say isFemale so if it's a female
we're going to make it bold if it's not
we're going to not make it bold. This is
a ternary operator in programming
languages you might have seen it
somewhere else. Okay we are making some
progress. We can also work with double
values you can say property double
mDouble.
Let's say somebody 77.5 for example and
you can output this value. Let's do that
console.log okay is it called mDouble?
Yes it is.
Let's run we should see the value of
mDouble is 77.5. Okay
We have worked with string, integers,
boolean and doubles. Another datatype
that we may use is the URL
datatype here so let's try this. It has
many similarities to the string datatype
but it is specifically used for URLs. So
let's do property url and i call
it mUrl and inside put in our website,
why not. And we can output it as we've
been doing before console.log "the value of mUrl:"+mUrl.
And if we run we see it here. To show
you that this is very different from a
string in terms of data types, let's take
this URL here and paste it in our text
here and down here we are going to do a
test. We're going to say if mString
equals we use a triple equals because
this thing in JavaScript tests for value
and the data type, it checks to see if
the values are equal, it also looks at
the data types to make sure that they
are equal. So we are going to check this
against mURL and if they are equal
value in data type, we're going to say
console.log, let's copy this. And if they
are not equal we're going to say they
are not the same.
Let's run the application. Mmm they are
not the same but if you use a double
equal sign to only test for the value,
you're going to see that they are equal
because we are only checking to see if
the values are equal and you see they
are equal. Now you know a little bit
about the difference between a string
datatype and the URL datatype and we're
going to have a chance to use these
later in the course.
This lecture is getting pretty long so
we're going to stop here and continue
exploring this subject in the next one.