In this lecture we're going to talk
about property binding in qml.
This is actually easier to show than
talk about so I'm going to go to QT
creator, create a project and show you
this concept. Okay so here we are in qt
creator, I'm going to create a new
project, it's going to be a QT quick
application as we've been doing before,
we're going to call it property binding
demo and store it in the usual location
hit next choose the latest version of
qt that we have installed, choose ok.
And we have our project here, we want to
change this title to the property
binding demo. We are going to put in a
rectangle, id is going to be redRectId.
It's going to have a width of 50
and a height that depends on the width
so we're going to say width * 1.5. This
will do we want to give it a color of
red. This is what property binding really
is it is to define one property to
depend on another property. In this case
the height of this rectangle depends on
its width.
I know this looks like a simple
assignment of a property but in qml
this is a contract between the width and
the height of this rectangle.
Whenever the width is going to change the
height is going to change accordingly
according to this expression here. And
this is what we call property binding.
The height is bound to the width with
this expression here. To show this off
I'm going to add a few other components.
I'm going to add another rectangle, you
might have guessed that the color of
this rectangle is going to be blue. It's
going to have a width of 100, a height of
and inside we're going to put a
mouseArea and when this thing is clicked
we're going to do something. We want to
add 10 to the current width of the red
rectangle. The way you do that, you'd say
redRectId.width = redRectId.width + 10.
We also want to make this
mouseArea filled the rectangle here
so we're going to come on top here and
say anchors.fill: parent. And we want this
rectangle here to be to the bottom of
the window the way we do that we going
to anchor it to the bottom. We want the
bottom line of it to be aligned with the
bottom line of the window. We're going to
say anchor.bottom: parent.bottom. Let's run the
application and see what we get. Mm-hmm
we have a red rectangle which is 50 in
width and 75 in height and we have
another rectangle down which is blue. And
when you click on this blue rectangle
the width of the red rectangle increases.
So we should expect to click and see
this thing increasing in width and
height. And this is happening this is
what we want. This is property binding in
action notice that we didn't do anything
to have this updating happening when the
width changes. This is done automatically
by qml and this is what is called
property binding you bind two properties
together and you define an expression
that is going to be used to bind them
together. But there is a problem when you
try to change this binding it is going
to break. Let's add another rectangle
we're going to call it green rectangle
Id, the color is going to be green,
the width and height and anchor
properties are going to be exactly the
same but its left side it's going to be
anchored to the right side of the blue
rectangle. So I'm going to say
blueRectId.right. And inside we're going to
put a mouse area so we're going to just
copy this and modify its on clicked
method to have a different effect. So
we're going to say redRectId.height and
change this to static value, let's
change this to 100, for example. Run the
application and show you what I mean. So
if we click on the blue rectangle things
are normal the width is changing and the
height is changing. If you click on the
green rectangle the height is going to
be reset to 100 notice that the width
doesn't change but what is even worse is
that if you click on the blue rectangle
you see that only the width is changing
and the height is not changing with that.
That is because we broke the contract by
setting the height to a static value.
Okay so we set the height to 100 and
broke the contract that was binding the
height to the width here. That's why when
you click on the blue rectangle only the
width is changing. You might think that
you can fix this by ammm
for example copying this thing here and
changing this to an expression. This
should fix things right. Let's make this
two so that when we click on the green
rectangle the height becomes 2 times the
width. Let's run the application and see
if this works. Actually we click on the
blue rectangle things are normal,
we click on the
green rectangle you see that things
change a little bit but if you click on
the blue rectangle things are not
working as we expect.
We are still seeing that the width is
changing but the height is not changing
with the width which means that the
expression here is really not working. So
what is really happening when you assign
a property like this when it has been
assigned before and bound to another
property the binding still breaks. It is
actually taking the result of this
expression and assigning it as a static
value to the height here. And this is no
different than what we did by assigning
a static value like this. If you want
your expression like this to take effect
when you click on this green button, you
need to do a little bit more work. So
what we are going to do is copy this
thing because we are going to use it and
say Qt.binding(). And inside we need to
pass in a function that is going to
return our expression. So what we're
going to say, we're going to say function,
you give it a parameter list and we give
it a body like this. I like to separate
things on different lines so it is
easier to read. And return
redRectId.width and multiply this by 2. We
are using this ID here because we are
trying to access this rectangle from
another element which is this rectangle
here. Let's run the application see if
our logic works and then I'm going to
try and explain it again. You click on
the blue rectangle, you see the width
changing and the height changing, click
on the green rectangle and click on the
blue rectangle again.
You see that where things are updating
now. So how is this working, this is
working because we are wrapping our
logic into this qt.binding thing. What it's
really doing, it is notifying the qt
system that we want this binding here to
replace the binding that we had here
if you don't wrap your code into this
qt.binding thing it's going to be like
you are assigning aesthetic value and it's
not going to update as you want. I hope
this really makes it clear how you work
with property bindings. And you saw the
need to use this qt.binding when you
need to update your binding that you are
defined before in your QT application.
And the next lecture we are going to
talk about the qt global object which
we have touched on right now by calling
qt.binding. This is the qt global
object and we are going to tackle it in
the next lecture. I'll see you there.