In this lecture we are talking about
properties and signal handlers. When you
define your property in qt quick
something important happens behind the
scenes and that is for every property
that you define. There is a signal that
is automatically generated for you and
you can use it to track changes to your
property. Let's go to QT creator and show
you what I mean. I'm going to create a
new project we are going to work with. I
am going to call it properties and
handlers demo and save it in the usual
location we're going to hit next it's a qmake
project, choose the latters version of
qt I have installed, choose our kit and
we have a project here. We're going to
change the title here. And we are going
to put in our usual rectangle, you must
be familiar with this already.
Let's give it a width of 300, a height of
100, a color of let's try dodger blue
right now. And by the way if you wonder
where I am getting this color names from.
Let's go to the help and type in color
and you're going to find qml basic type
of color, click on that. And they're going
to tell you that: this is a type for
colors and you can specify your color in
a number of ways: by an SVG color name,
which is what we are using; you can also
use a hexadecimal triplet or quad or
using these methods from the qt global
object. Click on this SVG color name link
and you are going to have a list of all
the colors that you can choose. Let's
copy one for example. Let's choose
this green yellow I like it. Come back to
qt creator
and change this to green yellow, why not.
So inside here we're going to code
a mouseArea ,it's going to fill its
parent and when it's clicked we want to
do something. We're going to leave this
empty for now. And we want to Center this
retangle too so you're going to say.
Right now we just using anchors to have
things laid out nicely
but we're going to have a chance to talk
about them. Let's run the application and
we have our yellow green rectangle in
the middle you click on it nothing
happens. Okay so we are talking about
properties and signal handlers, let's
define our first property here make it a
string type. So it's going to say first
name that's what we're going to call
this variable and we are going to put in
a default value of Daniel for example. We
also want to come down here and do
something when the component is loaded.
We are going to console.log, we're going
to output it. Run the application and you
can guess what we are going to see. We
are going to see the first name is
Daniel. So when we define mFirstName
here qt automatically generated the
signal that is going to be fired
whenever this property changes. Okay so
for example we can say on, you can see
that we have a signal called
onMFirstNamechanged. Okay
this is the signal that is generated for
you automatically. You can notice that it
starts with on capitalizes the first
letter of your property name and then
adds it changed suffix to that. Whenever
you want to track your changes you
should look for this signal. So we're
going to click on it.
and we are going to do something when
the first name changes we are going to
console.log you might have guessed that
that's what we are doing for now and say
"The first name changed to" the new value
which is still stored in mFirstName.
Okay so we are going to change the first
name when we click on this mouseArea so
we're going to say mFirstName =
John for example. Let's run the
application, okay the first name is
Daniel when I click here you see that it
says the first name changed to John.
Because we are doing that when we click
on this mouseArea here. So I hope this
drives from the point that whenever you
define a property you also have an
automatically generated signal that is
fired every time something changes about
that property of yours. And this works
for any property that you may define be
a string, a boolean and integer or
whatever really. That's what I wanted to
make clear in this lecture because many
of my students are confused by this
thing so I just want to make sure that
it is very clear to you. Okay this covers
all I had to say in this lecture and the
next chapter we are going to keep
digging on more concepts to work with QT
quick to design fluid user interfaces.
I'll see you in the next chapter.