In this lecture we're going to start to
look at the syntax for the qml language.
Rather than giving you a full lecture on
the semantics of qml, I think it's more
effective to go to QT creator, start
building something fun and then explain
the syntax as we go. What we're going to
build is something like this you can
click on the red window, it's going to
show the color you clicked in the dodger
blue circle here, you click on green you
see it says green here, you click on blue
it says blue. And you see that we have
some logs in the application output panel.
When you click on the dodger blue
rectangle you see that it says loop and when
you click nothing happens anymore even
though we see the log output here. So
we're going to build this thing and
along the way explain the QML syntax
that we will be using. So we are going to
create a new project.
It's a QT quick application that is
empty. We are going to save it in a
location on our drive, we use this as the
default project location for now. We're
going to call it Qml syntax demo, hit
next, choose Q make as your build tool,
choose the latest version of qt you
have installed. And you choose your
desktop kit. The first thing I want you
to notice is this import statements here.
The first one is importing the QT quick
libraries that we are going to use, and
the second one is going to import a part
of QT quick that deals with showing this
window here if you see this window
component is coming from this one. And if
we comment that out you see that the
window here is not recognized. So it is
coming from this import here. They
basically import other libraries and
make them available for you to use in
our file here. The first thing we want to
do is to give this window of ours here
an ID we're going to call it rootId. And
the ID like a flag that uniquely
identifies your qml component.
You're going to be using this a lot so
keep this in mind. The next thing we want
to do is to tell this window
to say that it is a QML Syntax Demo
because that's what it is. And we
want to define one property. It's going
to be a string it's going to say testToShow
and it's going to be initialized
to an empty string like this. This is how
you define variables or properties in
QML and we are going to have a chance to
talk more about this when we talk about
variables and data types. We are going to
create a row component, we are going to
give it an ID of Row 1 and remember an
ID uniquely identifies a qml
element in your qml code. And we can
refer to this row from anywhere in this
file by using this ID here you're going
to see how we use this.
We want this row to be in the center, the
way we say that we say anchors.centerIn: Parent.
We are going to talk about
anchors later in the course but right
now we are using this to tell a program
to show this row in the center of this
window here, the row is going to be in
the center of the window. We want to add
some spacing and let's make it 20 because
we want the content of our row component
here to have some space between them. And
I don't think I said this but the row
component allows you to lay out
components on one row, okay from left to
right if you will. And right now we are
ready to put some things inside we are
going to put in a rectangle element. Okay
so we're going to say rectangle like
this we are going to give it a width of
150 and a height of 150. And if you
haven't noticed this is how you specify
properties for your qml components, this
is not the first time we do it but I
think it is the first time that I
explained it. On top here you see that a
window component also has some
properties, we have a visible property to
make it visible it also has a width and
a height and the title that is shown in
the title bar for our window here. We are
doing the same thing specify the
width and height for this rectangle. We
also have other properties and this
rectangle element we are going to have a
chance to talk about it but for now we
want to specify a color. That is going to
be its background so we're going to make
it red. We want to give it a radius we
want its borders to be round a little
bit we're going to make this 20. And
inside we want to put a component that
we call a MouseArea. A MouseArea is
basically a thing that allows you to
make something clickable okay so we're
going to make it fill our rectangle and
we're going to use anchors again. We're
going to say anchors.fill:parent. And
we want to put an event handler that is
going to be called when you click on it.
The way you do it is like in JavaScript
you say onClicked and you specify the
code that you want to be executed when
you click on it inside here. For now we
want to say console.log and we want to
say "click on the red rectangle". And we
should give an ID to this rectangle too
so we're going to say ID : redRectId.
Okay now that we've done this I want to
copy this rectangle and paste it in
three times. You see that they are giving
us this error saying that red rect has
been used it's a duplicate ID. This
rectangle is going to be green so we
should say greenRectId and this
one is going to be blue we should say
blueRectId here. And we should change
the message that are shown here so we're
going to say green here when a rectangle
and blue here. Now that we have this I
want to run the application and show you
what it looks like. Hit the green button
here to run a
and boom you see that we have our
rectangles and they have round borders
which is specified by this radius
property here on the rectangle. Another
thing I want you to see is that what
text has taken effect, the title that we
specified. And if you increase the size
of the window you see that the
rectangles stay centered in the window
as we specified here. We want everything
in the road to be centered in the parent.
And by now hope you see that the row
component lays out its contents in one
row from left to the right. Okay you see
that the first element we put in was
the red rectangle, the second was the
green rectangle, the third was the blue
rectangle and you see that they are in
this order from left to right. Okay if
you click on the red rectangle you see
that they say you clicked on the red
rectangle, click on green you see the
message, click on blue you see the
message. But this doesn't look like what
we set out to do in this lecture. So the
next thing we want to do is to add that
dodger blue circle how do we do it. We're
going to copy the code here for the
rectangle again because that's what
we're going to adapt to make it look
like a circle. We are going to paste it
down here. We are going to change the ID
to textRectId and inside we want to
show some text. The way we do that we put
the text component inside we have done
this in the previous lecture so we are
to going say text and we want its value to be
textToShow the property that we
defined on top here. We also want this to
show in the center of the parent so
we're going to say anchors.centerIn: parent.
And just to test let's say hello
here to see that we see this text in the
rectangle that we define here. We also
want to make it look like a circle so we
want to increase the radius to
something really big, let's make it 100 and
see what it looks like. And before we run
let's make this color dodger blue. These are
some predefined colors that you can use
in your qml applications, we're going to
talk more about this when we talk about
the color property. Let's run the
application to see what we have. And boom
we see that we have a Dodger blue circle
that says hello. The next thing we want
to do is to change this property when we
click on the rectangles here how do we
do that. If you look the ID for this text
is not there so this is a good time to
define it so we're going to say is textId.
Okay so when somebody click we
want to change this textToShow
property and this is going to change the
text property here for us because we
have bound this property to this
property here. Let me show you what I
mean.
Okay so we're going to say here textToShow
equals red - blue because this is the
blue rectangle. Here we're going to say
textToShow equals green and here we're
going to say textToShow equals red.
Let's run. Uh-huh so you see that it says
red it says screen say it's blue. Okay so
how is this work and why is it changing
the text in the Dodger blue circle. When
we only change the property of testToShow
remember we define this thing on
top here. It is happening because we did
the binding when we assign textToShow
to the text here. So when you do this for
the first time we're doing what we call
property binding in Qml, you are actually
telling your system to keep track of
changes in the textToShow property and
whenever something changes that change
is going to be propagated to any
interested
property and in this case to the text
property of our text component here, I
hope this make sense. Let's run again so
that you see this in action red, green,
blue. Okay I actually want to do
something to break this contruct here. So
when you click on the Dodger blue
rectangle here I want to change the text
in here to some static text. So I'm going
to say textId.text equals something
like loop. Okay this is some dummy text I
put here. So when I run the application
I'm going to still be able to click on
red, green, blue rectangle and change the
text in here but when I click on the
Dodger blue rectangle I'm going to break
this contruct here because I am
assigning something else to the property
here. Let's run the application and show
you what I mean. Okay the application is
here I can click on red, I see red here, I
click on green see green here, I click on
blue I see blue here. Let's click on this
guy we're going to see a loop here. But
when I click on red again notice that I
get the message here but the changes are
not reflected in the Dodger blue
rectangle because I broke that property.
I have broken the binding between the
textToShow property and the text of
the text component here. I hope this
makes sense. Of course this is just an
introduction we're going to have more
chances to talk about this but for now
you should have an idea that qml is a
language that is declarative. It is
declarative because you define your
components as you need them. And another
thing you should notice is that elements
are all hierarchy there is a
parent-child relationship between your
elements in your qml file. For example
the row component is a child of the
window here the rectangle here is a
child of this row component here and
these rectangles are siblings. And you
can see that each rectangle has a child
of its own, a mouse area.
And down here we have a rectangle that
has two children
text component and a mouseArea
component. Another thing you notice is
that we give our components unique IDs.
We didn't use this row ID here but
notice that we changed the text inside
this component here using its ID we use
text ID.text. If we did text only
just like this we should have an error
when we run the application because this
property is not recognized.
Okay so let's click on this and you see
that error invalid write to global
property "text". The mouseArea doesn't
have a text property to work with. That's
why we are seeing this error here and it
gives us the line where we have this
error here. So we should fix this by
hitting ctrl Z to bring what we had
before. Okay IDs are very important when
you plan to work with that component
later in the code like we did here.
Another thing you saw is that in qml you
can respond to events. We had this mouseArea
component and we could click and
respond to the click in this code
snippet here. Okay we show the message by
logging into the console we also change
the value of the textToShow property
here. Okay so you can do this things in
qml you can handle events and we are
going to have more chances to talk about
this later in the course. Okay I hope
this gives you a good introduction to
the general syntax of qml it really is
not that hard if you are familiar with
the things like HTML and CSS, this
shouldn't really scare you because it is
similar even if the syntax is a little
bit different.
Ok this covers what we set out to do in
this lecture. I hope you had a good
introduction to the Qml language. I
would recommend to go through this again
and try to run it or modify a few things
on your own to see the effect of your
changes. In the next lecture we're going
to look at some data types in QML and
how you can use them in your QT quick
applications. I'll see you in the next
lecture.