In this lecture we are talking about the
QT quick global object. Here we are in
the online documentation for this qt
global object. It is called the qt qml
type. If we click on the more link here, it
says that the qt object is a global
object with utility functions, properties
and enums. It basically gives you
some utilities that you can use to make
your job easier. For example, you can use
it here to define a color we have done
this before when we looked at the data
types. So to define a color you call the
qt global object, you put a dot, you
call the RGBA a method and you specify
the red component, the green component,
the blue component and the opacity
component. There are some types that are
defined in this qt global object you
can use it to define a rectangle, a
point, a size, we have done this in a
previous lecture. You can use it to
define a color, there are methods you can
use, the font and all these objects. You
can use it to define these objects. There
are also some other objects that have
information we might be interested in.
For example, you may want to grab the
information for the operating system
that you are working on and the way you
do that you can come to the platform
object and query the OS that you are
using. Okay it can print it out and we
are going to try this thing. So right now
I'd like to go to QT creator and show
you some of this things in action. Okay
so here we are in QT creator, I am going
to create a new project, it's going to be
a QT quick application, I am going to
call it qt global object demo and
store it in the usual location and next,
choose the QT version I want to use, I
choose the latest one I have installed, I
choose my kit as usual and hit finish. I
want to change this title here
and put a rectangle down here. It's going
to have a width of 300 a height of 100
the color red. And inside we're going to
put in a mouseArea which is going to
fill the parent and in its onClicked the
method we are going to quit the
application and guess what we are going
to use, we are going to call the quit
method from the qt global object,
something like this. We also want to
Center this rectangle so we're going to
say anchor.centerIn: parent. Okay so
let's say that we are quiting so that
it is obvious. Let's run the application
okay the app is here you can see our red
rectangle and when I click on it notice
what happens in the app output pane here.
"Quiting the app" and your app dies. Okay
this is what we want. Now you know how to
use the quit method from the qt global
object. Another thing you can do from the
qt global object is list the available
fonts so let's say that. So we are going
to define a property here, it's going to
be a VAR type and it's going to be
called fonts and we are going to assign
the qt.fontFamilies method
which returns a list of available fonts.
So what we can do down here is do a loop
so we're going to say
for (var i = o ; i < fonts.length ; i++).
And you see that this
doesn't have to complete to show us this
property because this is a var there's
no way the system would have known that
it's an array. But when we call this
property, the system is going to check
and see if it's available and if it's
available it's going to call it and we
won't have any problem. So we're going to
go inside the body of the loop and say
console.log ok it's going to show the
index in square brackets and then it's
going to say in the font that we are
dealing with at that particular
iteration. Let's run the application. When
you click this then you see that we have
around 352 fonts installed on this
system and if you scroll up you're going
to see the entire list. Okay and if you
look down you're going to find my
favorite font which is consolas, I love
this so much. This is what I am even
using here in QT creator. So you
can now list your fonts using the qt
global object by calling qt.fontFamilies
method. The other thing you can
do from the qt global object is hash a
string.
So what you can do for example is define
a var call it mName and give it a value
of Daniel Gawaya, my name, so what you can do is
compute the hash for this. So we're going
to say and you can call QT md5 and pass
in mName. Okay so by now we have our
hash stored in this variable so we can
output it and console.log mNameHash.
Run the application, click on the button
and this is our hash here. This is not
all, you can also open URLs externally so
we're going to say open url qxternally.
These are the things
you're going to need some time in your
journey as a UI developer using QT quick.
So you can say QT.openUrlExternally
and pass in the URL that you
want to open. So we're going to say HTTP
for example and put in our website and
if we run this, click on this. You're going
to see that a browser is going to open
but it's not putting in our website,
what is wrong. I put in two colons, let's
run again. Mm-hmm you see that it's now
working, it is loading our website. We can
also open local files using the default
program. For example what happens
when you double click on an image your
default program for opening images is
going to open them. So that's what we're
going to do here when we click on this
mouse area we are going to call this
method but we are going to pass in a
full path to a file. Let me show you what
I mean so we are doing to call QT.openUrlExternally
it's going to be the same
thing
but we are going to say file and passing
the full path to the file. I happen to
have an image down here under this path
this image is a PNG, you can see it here.
So I am going to capture its path copy
and come back to our project and paste
it here. Ok I'm going to change this to a
back slash bring this back and pass in
the name for that file. So to avoid any
errors I am just going to copy the name
here, put it in here and give it a PNG
extension. So if we click we are going to
open this website but we are also going
to open
file locally so let's comment this out
so that it doesn't get in the way of
what we want to see. Run the application
if we click on this you see that this
image opens in my default program which
happens to be the default windows image
viewer. Okay this is cool sometimes you
need to do this and qt makes it very
easy to do even using the Qt Quick API.
The last thing I want to do is to show
you how you can print or get the current
platform that your application is
running on. So the way you do that you
can print it out console.log and say
qt platform OS okay so we can put a
string in front here and make it clear
what we are trying to show "The current
platform". Let's see this, run the
application, click on this guy, it's going
to open in our image viewer but you see
that it says that the current platforms
windows. Okay we have just seen a few
things about the qt global object but
if you are really interested you can
come and look at all the offerings that
are there and I'm sure you're going to
be using this all over your applications
in qt. For example what we just did
to print the platform information, it is
from this platform object and you see
that it prints the OS "This read-only
property contains the name of the
operating system. Possible values are:"
currently the platforms supported by
qt.
You see Android, iOS, TVOS, Linux, Mac OS,
Windows. This is what we just saw. Okay
you can play with other things if you are
in the mood for that. This cover is
all we set up to do in this lecture. In
the next one we're going to talk about
properties and signal handlers. I'll see
you in the next lecture.