Tabs
In this video, we are going to learn about a new Qt class, QTabWidget.
Then we'll see how to switch tabs programmatically in the code.
The learning process will be done through an example of tabbed-window created with QTabWidget.
Now let's take a look at QTabWidget. So if you're ready.
Launch Qt Creator and create a new QWidget application project.
Doubleclick the mainwindow.ui to switch to design mode to design this UI.
In the container section, you can find Tab Widget.
Drag and drop it to centralWidget. Then change the layout of centralWidget to either Box layout
so that the Tab Widget can fill up the centralWidget.
The Tab widget you can see has a tab bar and a page area.
The tab bar is shown above the page area by default and it is used to switch between different pages.
The page area is used to display pages that related to each tab. Like all built-in Qt widgets.
You can design the tab window here in the design mode by dragging widgets into the page area.
and arrange them as you normally do.
As you can see from the object tree panel, each page is actually a QWidget.
To change the title of each tab.
Double click won't work.
What you can do
You have to select a tab in the tab bar and then go to the property panel.
Scroll down and find currentTabText. By changing currentTabText.
You effectively change the title of the tab.
Once you selected the tab two in the tab bar. The widget now you drag and drop will appear
in the tab two.
If you build and run the application now.
You can see how this tab window looks like.
Now we've seen how it works in designing tab widget in the design mode.
We are going to see how we can manipulate it in the code programmatically.
Let's open mainwindow.cpp in the editor. To add a new tab
it requires a QWidget object which represents a page area.
In this example we are going to just use a label as our page for the new tab.
We create a new QLabel with String "Hello New Tab".
Then we call addTab() method to insert this label widget as the new tab to the end
with title "New Tab".
Now if you build and run the application.
In order to use QLabel.
We have to first include QLabel header file.
And now you see our new tab is created using the label we just created inside the code.
Another common usage is to switch tabs programmatically. Qt has provided two methods for this purpose.
We can either call setCurrentWidget() and pass the widget pointer to this function
or we can just call setCurrentindex().
In this case we only need to give the index of the tab instead of the widget pointer.
Since we've changed the current tab in MainWindow's constructor. The application is shown with the new
tab selected by default.
In this case these two statements have the same effect.
By building and running the application.
You can see it works as expected.
Lastly you might want to remove a tab. To do that
you need to give index.
In this case we can remove the second tab.
And run the application again.
Now you see the tab two is removed. In this section we've learnt Display Widgets, Editable widgets, Layouts
and Tabs. They should be able to help you enrich your GUI applications and deliver a better user experience.
In the next section we'll talk about Models and Views.