Hello welcome back to learning Qt5.
This is Symeon Huang. This video will be our last video of the section one, multi-platform and portability.
In this video.
We're going to take a look at how to use compile-time OS macros and how to get System Information at
runtime.
In the end we're going to take a look how to write some platform-specific configurations in qmake based
project file. Now if you're ready let's get back to our HelloWorld project.
Sometimes, especially when you develop some low level applications or libraries, you have to provide
the APIs but with different implementations. Here i make a very naive and simple example printHello()
it's a function that will print "Hello Qt world" with the operating system or the platform you are currently
running. It sounds very simple.
But as a downstream consumer you just want to call printHello().
I know you don't want to care about the details. But as a provider you have to know which operating system
you're currently building or running. Lucky Qt provide a lot of global Qt declarations.
They are actually platform-specific. For example, Q_OS_WIN is only defined when the
Qt libraries were build on Windows. For Q_OS_UNIX
It is only defined when Qt
libraries were built on UNIX systems such as Mac or Linux.
So in the printHello() we say if Q_OS_WIN is defined, we're going to output "Hello Qt World on Windows".
If it's Unix we're going to say "Hello Qt world on Unix". As you can see
Qt creator is very smart. It has already grayed out all the inapplicable section in defined.
Let's build and run this application.
See if we can see "Hello Qt World on Windows". Since I'm running on Windows at this moment.
Yes "Hello Qt on Windows".
Now
Sometimes you may also want some runtime system information. In some cases, like your application crashed
you wish to gather some essentials system information, such as the Windows version or sometimes you simply
want to send a deprecation warning.
For example, if you are running Windows XP, we actually want to say "we're deprecating Windows XP support".
You can get this enum using QSysInfo.
Remember to include this header file. There's a static member function called a windowVersion(). It will return
a win version enum.
So if it's a Windows XP. We're going to say "We're deprecating Windows XP support". But actually I'm
running Windows 10.
Of course we're not going to deprecate Windows 10 at this moment.
Hence we can give some messages, such as.
Welcome to Windows 10.
Let's build and run again.
We should be able to see two outputs. The first one will be "Hello Qt World on Windows".
And the second one should be "Welcome to Windows 10".
Hello Qt world on Windows and welcome to windows 10 as we expected.
Now last but not least, sometimes you may wonder how do we configure this qmake based project file to include new modules.
Because some modules are platform-specific, such as win32 etc.
Or sometimes you just want to give some messages.
You can use some keywords win32, unix to do this job.
Now if I run qmake, i should be able to see "building on Windows" messages.
Project MESSAGE: Building on Windows. Using this technique you should be able to send a warning like "Unknown platform!
Doesn't support it yet" message to the platform you actually haven't supported. So people can know
that platform is not supported when they run qmake.
Instead of
when they compile and get tons of errors, or even worse when they run the application and they just crashes.
So in our first section we've so far have learned the basics about Qt application and the fundamentals
about
Qt object and memory management and how do parse and process command-line options and also
multi-platform and portability knowledge.
And also our techniques about developing multi-platform and also techniques how to develop cross-platform
applications.
In the next section we're going to take a look at multi-threading and multiprocessing
which can enhance your command-line based, which can enhance your application even further.