Window, dialog, Popup. In this video we will talk about some built-in top level widgets in Qt, namely
MainWindow and Dialog. And then we'll see how we can create Popups in Qt.
At fist, let me get your attention that the term window here means a window in terms of graphical user interface
not the QWindow class.
In fact the class that represents the window is QMainWindow. To make them distinct.
I'll use the class name QMainWindow from now on.
Launch Qt Creator and open the GUI project from previous videos or create
new Qt widgets application project with QMainWindows as the base class.
Let's check what QMainWindow is and what features that a QMainWindow has.
If you double click mainwindow.ui.
And switch to design mode.
You can see that a QMainWindow has it's layout to which you can add tool bar, status bar and the menu bar.
Once you added everything it becomes a traditionally classic desktop window. But by default the toolbar
and the menu bar are empty.
So I'll show you how to add actions into tool bar and the menu bar.
If you double click the "type here" placeholder in the menu bar.
Then you can insert a new menu.
Once you've done that you can just click the menu you just inserted and double click "type here" placeholder
in the menu and then you can insert an action.
Once you've got the action you can see the action would appear in the action editor and you can drag and drop
it into the toolbar.
Of course, you don't need a menu action to have a tool bar action.
In the action editor, you can click the new button to create a new action and then
you can make use of it in the tool box directly.
Now let's go back and create a new object.
Now let's get back in and create a new project.
This time let's choose QDialog as the base class.
And let's see what the dialog looks like. Let's go to design mode again editing dialog.ui.
As you can see, dialog is basically a window but without many features that we have in QMainWindow.
For example there is no menu bar or toolbar.
There is no status bar, hence a QDialog normally is used for short term tasks.
Another interested thing worth mentioning is that a QDialog will be placed on the top of the parent
widget's center.
If it has a parent. That is also a property called "modal" that you can set for QDialog.
If you scroll down the property panel, you can see the modal property under QDialog section. A modal dialog
will block input to other visible windows in the same application.
By contrast, a modaless dialog operate independently off other windows in the same application.
After all a QDialog and a QMainWindow are both windows. We can use QDialog as a Popup.
Essentially, a Popup window is just a dialog that requires even less communication.
So you are ready for some hands on exercises.
Let's get started.
Let's close this dialog project for now.
Now let's open the Qt mainwindow project and editing the .ui file.
Firstly, let's make the action show Popup.
You can double click the action, change the text name.
You can double click the action.
Change the text.
Once you've done, save and go back to mainwindow
Here we're going to define a slot
to handle the action.
As you've already known, the signal of the action needs to be connected to this slot.
This signal trigger
is emitted whenever the action is activated by user either by clicking or keyboard shortcuts.
Now let's define the slot.
We can create a new Popup using the built-in QDialog class.
In the slot,
If you call exec()
In the slot, if you call exec() method, then pop up will block user input.
It will not return until the user closes the dialog.
We can use a simple print statement to check these out.
If you build and run the application now.
Click ShowPopup.
Yes, see, the popup is shown and the user input to other windows
are blocked.
You can also see it the application output.
onShowPopup finised is not printed.
It will only be printed when we close the dialog.
However if you call the show() method, then the popup will be shown as a modaless dialog.
The function will return immediately.
Hence we are expected to see the message immediately.
As you can see, "onShowPopup finished" has been printed and the user input to other windows are
not blocked.
Now I just created a QDialog programmatically. As we said before
It's better to get it from .ui file.
So how do we add a new class like that.
Just right click the project, select "Add new", select Qt, Qt Designer Form Class. Here, you can choose
all the templates you like. Template... dialog without the buttons are what we're looking for.
If you add it to this project. You're immediately be able to edit dialog.ui
I'll leave the customization to you.
But for now we are going to focus on how to use this class.
If you go back to mainwindow.cpp just to include the header file
and replace QDialog with your custom dialog class.
Rebuild and run.
And you get the dialog Popup when you activate showPopup action.
As you can see this dialog is different from the QDialog. It's designed in dialog.ui.
In this section.
You've learnt how to design Qt Creator, signals and slots, Window, dialog and Popup.
In the next section, you'll continue your Qt programming learning process
in Widgets and Layouts.