TCP server. In this video we are going to set up a TCP server.
At first we will create a simple TCP client and get familiar with QTcpSocket API.
Then we will make a TCP server to complete the demo.
Now let's launch Qt Creator.
We create a new Qt console application project tcpClient.
Let's introduce a new class QTcpSocket
which is a derived class of QAbstractSocket, as the name suggests, it is a representation of network
socket using TCP protocol.
On the other hand, QAbstractSocket inherits QIODevice which means we have read and write methods
to receive and a send data. To use this class we need to add network module into project configuration
file.
In this case tcpClient.pro. We type QT plus equal network into this file.
Right click the whole project and then run qmake again to regenerate to make files to enable auto
complete and syntax highlighting for network module in the code editor.
Remember to include relevant header files namely QTcpSocket and QHostAddress.
Now let's create a QTcpSocket object, client. For client-side socket
we may wish to use bind() method in the case of multiple network interfaces.
Otherwise it is sufficient to let the platform determine its outgoing interface.
The port will be assigned randomly.
Now let's use the socket to connect to localhost, at port
54321 and the wait for connected.
Once we are sure the client state is in the connected state, we then wait for the message sent from
the server. We print the message and write our own messages back to the socket.
This is how simple the TCP connection works in Qt. Do bare in mind that we use some blocking methods
such as waitForReadyRead() here to make this example synchronized.
It is possible and actually more common to use them asynchronously with signals and the slots.
Since there is no need to enter an event loop, we return a normal exit code 0 in the end.
If we if we build and run this application now, we will receive an error message saying
It's failed to connect to the localhost and the exit code is 1. That's because we haven't written our server.
And there is no server running and listening at 54321. To finish this demo
Let's make a simple TCP server. Same procedure as TCP client, add network module, run
qmake.
But API set is different in the server side. We will facilitate QTcpServer instead.
QTcpServer provide a TCP based server.
Each incoming connection can be obtained as a QTcpSocket.
We can specify the address and the port that the server should listen at.
Similarly, we first make it listen on localhost at port 54321 and use waitForNewConnection()
to block execution until a new connection is established.
By using this blocking method, we don't need an event loop in this application.
The argument minus one passed to this method means this method would never time out. Then we obtain the
connection by calling nextPedingConnection() method.
The QTcpSocket pointer is the socket to communicate with the client.
We use the same read and write methods to receive and send messages. After we've done with this connection.
We close this socket and then we schedule it for deletion.
This is a good practice to avoid the memory wasting.
In the end, we stop accepting new connections by calling server.close() method.
Now let's verify our server and client.
We first built and run TCP server to let it listen at the specified
address and port.
Now the server is running now.
Then we run TCP client to make a connection.
As you can see from the application output, the connection was established successfully and the messages
were received and sent as expected.
Now let's look back at section 3, throughout this section, we've learned the basics about network
programming.
Then we got our hands on sending HTTP request and downloading. We're finished with this section with TCP
client and server demo.
You should now be able to apply this knowledge to make your application networking capable.