HTTP request and downloading. You have learned how to send a HTTP request to a server to retrieve resource
from a remote server.
Let's launch Qt Creator and create a new Qt console applications project
In order to use Qt network module,
we need to add it to project configuration.
Doubleclick the project file and add Qt plus equal network into this file. Now, re-run qmake to
make sure things like auto-complete will work in code editor
Now, let’s switch back to main.cpp.
First we need to include necessary header files.
Then we create a Q Network Access Manager. Qt provides
Q Network Access Manager to provide the applications layer network access.
It takes in a Q network request object and then returns a Q network reply object.
It also provides common methods such as get, post and put. Then we construct a Q network request object
with the URL pointing to a QT blog.
QNetworkRequest is a class holding the information necessary to send a request over the network.
In addition to the URL, we can also set headers and attributes to specialize the request.
Here we set the UserAgentHeader to our customized string.
Then we call get method to obtain the contents of the target.
Since network access API only provides us with asynchronous implementations we need to connect to the
signal of reply and then make sure that the event loop is running. Here we use the lambda function, introduced in
C++11 as a slot to replace the finished signal.
That signal is emitted when the reply has finished processing and there is no more updates to the data
or metadata unless we explicitly call close or abort.
We can still read data from the reply. In this lambda function,
we print out all the data from that reply.
Then we close and schedule it for deletion.
In the end we call quit to stop the main event loop and then quit the application.
Now let’s rebuild and then run this application.
You should see that HTML content of Qt blog is printed out.
Similarly you can also use this method to download a file from remote server.
Similarly you can also use this method to download a file.
In this example we are going to download a license from GNU,
but rather than printing them out in the console, we're going to store the information in the
local file.
To do that,
we should first include QFile.
This gives us Q file class.
Q file provides us a set of API to read from and write to files.
Here we construct a Q file object out with a local file name lgpl-3.0.txt, then we write the data from
Q network reply to this file.
We call close method in the end
to close this file.
Now let’s build and run again.
Once the application exits,
it means the file has already been downloaded.
Let's open file browser
and you should find the file lgpl-3.0.txt
has already been downloaded.
If you open it with Notepad you should find that this text file was correctly downloaded
Into next video,
we will talk about how to write a TCP server with Qt network module.