Widgets and the layouts. In this section we will talk about different widgets and layouts, from display
widgets such as label to editable widgets like a line edit. Then we will talk about layouts and
tabs
In the video 2.1, display widgets, you are going to learn how to display text in a label and text browser
widgets then how to display images in the label widget.
Lastly you're learning how to make use of a progress bar.
Now let's get started.
Create a new Qt widgets
application project.
It should be a Q main window based project
if you remember what we did in previous videos.
Double-click the mainwindow.ui file to the design mode.
Now we're going to design the user interface.
Now we're going to drag a label widget into the view
then we're going to drag  and drop a text browser widget
change the layout of that central widget to lay out horizontally because we're going to send the same
text to source for these two widgets.
We would do it in the source code
with the default properties label widgets doesn’t wrap the text,
that's why you see the widgets gets awkwardly long.
By contrast text browser will make a scroll panel and embed the text displaying widgets, inside the
text get wrapped automatically in text browser and it walks like a read only editor. You can select
and copy the selection. You may wish to take a look at text browsers documentation and check the property
panel in design mode.
You'll see what properties you have to tweak this widget.
Now let's go to the fun part, showing an image in label widget
so I will use a cat picture to demo.
So I will use a cat picture to demo this
Let’s first remove the text browser widgets from the view
back to mainwindow.cpp
we are use Qpixmap
it's so simple that's all you need to do is to load pictures from the file
Then call set Pixmap method of the label widget
This method will display the pixmap on the screen.
Now if you give your application a run,
you will see the image is shown on the screen in the label widget as we expect.
The last debate of this video is about the progress bar.
Go back to the UI design.
Remove all the widgets.
Now we drag a progress bar into the view.
If you check the property panel by default it has a value 24.
Here we're going to set it back to zero.
So the initial states makes more sense.
Also by default the state value range is from 0 to 100 as you can see here.
You might want to change it
if you have special need
we will make use of the progress bar built-in slot function call it setvalue but in this demo,
we will just use it as a regular member function and I'll use a q timer to update the progress bar
every half second.
So firstly let's create a slot
then we are going to create a Q timer that times up every half second
we set interval to half second
then we connect to the time out signal.
After the second non-connected we start the timer
by default the Q timer emits timeout signal repeatly
after the interval time but if you want to only emits the signal once and then a stop afterwards you need to
set the single shot to true.
Now let's get to the slot part
we first get the values from the progress bar
we check the value if it's greater than a hundred
if is greater or equal to 100 than what you can halt it because progress bar has already been full.
Otherwise we increment the value by one and set it back to the UI progress bar.
If you run the application now
you can see the progress bar increment in the value every half seconds. In real life,
This should of course reflect some meaningful process. In the next video,
we will talk about editable widgets.