Multi-processing. In this video we are going to take a look at how to start an external program with Qprocess in Qt.
Then we're also check how we can communicate with this Qprocess using standard input and output.
If you're ready to get your hands on some small exercises. Let's get started. The external program
we will demo today is Gzip. An open source compression utility.
You can get the binaries from Gzip windows web page.
I've downloaded and extracted binaries into my local drive.
Now if you're ready. Let's open Qt creator and create a new Qt console application project. In this
new project we will need to first re-include QProcess header file.
Then we create a QProcess object. Set Gzip as the program. And now  if we call start() method.
The process will start and enter running state.
Let's use some standard output to check these. As you can see we output the current application process ID
and our child process ID as well.
If we build and run the application now.
You can see the two process IDs and if you check systems task manager you'll find Gzip in process list.
This is because our current application is blocked by our standard input. Now if we give a number
and check the task manager again.
Gzip disappeared.
This is it because the close method close all read and write channels and then kill the process.
OK but how do we communicate with Gzip to do some useful things.
Let's first start Gzip with dash h argument to see what choices we have. To do this
you just need to make a QStringList object.
A QStringList is just a shortcut
to QList
And the only argument we need is dash h.
now we can use setArguments() method to set the argument for our program
To read from the process
We can use method readAll(), since QProcess derives from QIODevice.
So it inherits all input and output methods.
We need to use toStdString() method to convert a Qt backed array to standard string so we
can use std::cout to output the result.
To make sure there is something to read.
We can also use waitForReadyRead() method.
Now if you build and run the application again
we basically redirect the output from Gzip to our applications output. And you can see Gzip by default.
It reads from the standard input
if there is no file specified.
Additionally we can give a dash c argument to make Gzip prints result into standard output.
So let's change our application a bit to write something to Gzip standard input. It's fairly simple, just
call write() method with a QByteArray object.
Let's write "Hello World" into Gzip.
And we can use waitForByteWriten() to make sure the write was successful. And then we need to close
the write channel.
This is very necessary to close
write channel to let Gzip know that there is no more data in standard input.
Let's also change the arguments to dash c. Lastly, but not the least, we don't want junky characters
so we can use toBase64() to encode our results.
Build and run now
And you get to see the base64 encoded results of Gzip compressed "Hello world".
Now let's look back after this section.
You should understand the difference between a thread and a process.
More importantly how to use threads and processes in Qt. In the upcoming section.
We'll go through networking programming in Qt.