This is Section 3 Networking. In this section you are going to get an introduction to network programming
then how to make HTTP request and download files. TCP server is covered in the end of this section.
We are going to go through network programming introduction. Topics out POSIX sockets, TCP and UDP
and HTTP. To develop applications with networking capabilities
We need to first to go through some fundamental knowledge related to Internet Protocol suite which
is commonly known as TCP/IP because of the original Protocols in the suite are the Transmission
Control Protocol and the Internet Protocol. Internet Protocol suite is currently the dominant protocol
for applications and devices to communicate with each other.
A socket is an endpoint to receive or send data in the computer network. In the context of TCP/IP, a socket
is assumed to be associated with a specific socket address. What is a socket address then?
It's basically the combination of IP address and port number.
For example a typical HTTP server would be running with port number 80 and a local IP address is 127 point
what
It's 127.0.0.1.
So a local HTTP server would be running at socket address 127.0.0.1:80.
By local, it means no communication with other nodes in the network.
The process of associating a socket address with a socket is called binding.
Now let's go to the programming domain.
Berkeley sockets which is also known as BSD sockets is an application programming interface aka API for network
socket. It evolved and made into POSIX specifications.
And became the standard interface for connecting to the Internet.
All modern operating systems have implemented Berkeley sockets or POSIX sockets including, Microsoft
Windows. And the implementation in Microsoft Windows,
Winsock follows the standard closely. A socket can operate under different protocols.
The common ones are transmission control protocol TCP and user datagram protocol UDP. TCP is widely
used in the Internet world.
Due to it's
notable advantages, reliability and accuracy.
Most internet services such as World Wide Web, file transfer, e-mail are using TCP.
The most prominent feature of TCP is that TCP guarantees the order and the completeness of data packages.
That means all bytes received will be exactly the same with bytes sent and in the same order. Because
the physical networks are not always reliable.
Some data packages may be lost, duplicated or delivered in different order.
In those cases TCP requests the sender to redelivered the lost data and  rearranges the packages
to make sure the data correctness and the completeness. In the case where the data is still not able
to be delivered, the sender will be notified of this failure.
You might think network programming sounds so complicated that there are so many details to take care of.
On the contrary, because of TCP applications don't need to do with this low labor networking details.
TCP has abstracted the low level transmission details away.
Although UDP is not widely used as TCP. It remains a brightstar in some areas, especially where latency
plays a more important role.
By contrast UDP doesn't provide a reliable connection.
In fact it is connectionless which also means UDP doesn't provide protection against data being
lost.
Miss ordered or duplicated.
Therefore UDP is very suitable for applications where those error detection is not required or handled
at the application level.
In some cases where latency is very sensitive, applications also prefer UDP than TCP because dropping
data packages are better than waiting for delayed packages. Due to these features, UDP has much less
overhead than TCP and has been used in the areas from query to video and audio streaming.
Notably, the domain name system DNS and network time protocol NTP both favor UDP.
Other than them some big names including NFS network file system, IPTV and Skype are also using UDP.
So a quick summary of TCP and the UDP would be TCP is a reliable protocol.
Meanwhile UDP is simple and fast. The next protocol we are going to look is hypertext transfer protocol
HTTP.
The backbone of world wide web. They're all called protocols.
But HTTP is a protocol at application layer rather than transport layer.
It's assumed a reliable underlying transport layer protocol where in most cases TCP is used.
HTTP is a protocol for client-server model where the client send HTTP request and the server responses
with the required resources. Take a real life example to wrap up this session.
When you open browser and type www.Google.com. A DNS query is sent by UDP to
resolve the IP address of www.Google.com.
Once the result is received.
The browser will send a HTTP request wire TCP to Google's web server and that server will return the
content.
www.Google.com are the response.
Again I have to emphasize that you could send a DNS query via TCP and use HTTP over UDP. In the next
video we're going to get our hands on HTTP request in Qt.