Hello welcome to section two. Multithreading and multiprocessing. In this section we are first to get
to know threads and processes then some hands on practices to use threads and processes in Qt. In the first
video of this section. An introduction to threads and processes we will be given.
We are also going to take a look at the differences between a thread and a process.
Let's first introduce process. A process
is fairly easy to understand. When you start a program the instance of that program has all the execution
code and states and the resources it currently holds.
We call that instance a process.
For example you can check all running processes in your system
task manager.
Let's take a real life example here.
When you have your browser and audio player running at the same time so you can listen to music while
checking messages and the news.
The audio player and the browser are running at different process.
And if we take a closer look some browsers such as Google Chrome have multiple processes. Meanwhile a
typical audio player has multiple threads
by definition a thread is the smallest sequence of instructions that can be managed independently
by scheduler. By sequence
it means a thread has beginning and end. In addition to sequential instructions that a thread includes. But
and you cannot start a thread without a program.
Threads can only be started within the computer program.
In the example of an audio player it has the GUI thread running to keep user interface responsive and
response to user interactions while another thread working with audio driver to play sound. Threads
can only be started within the computer program.
In the example of an audio player it has a GUI thread running to keep user interface responsive and
response to user interactions while another thread working with audio driver to play sound.
Although in some contexts it's also called like lightweight process and a thread is similar to a process
in some way.
Some significant differences exist between the two.
Typically thread exist inside a process and they share the resources like the memory that is allocated
to the process.
However processes are independent and they don't share those resources.
On the other hand a crash inside of a thread leads to the crash of whole process but a process crashes.
Other processes are normally not affected.
In the meantime it's much easier to communicate among threads since they are sharing resources.
Meanwhile the interprocess communication is often limited and tricky. By harnessing multithreading
or multiprocessing which is called parallelization. Programmers can utilize modern multicore and the modern
CPU devices more effectively.
This can help us reduce processing time and improve responsiveness of the application.
What's more important for graphical user interface application is that by separating the UI thread and
the logic heavy lifting thread the user interface can stay responsive
rather than getting frozen. In Qt, there are a range of classes provided to help developers to use threads
and processes in their applications. From low level Qthread to high level QConcurrent.
It's fair to say that threading is getting easier despite it's a complicated topic.
Now we've learned some theoretical parts. In the next video we are going to play with threads in the
Qt world.