Hi, i am Symeon Huang.
And welcome to learning Qt5 by a Packt publishing.
I have been a full stack developer for a few years and am very passionate about the UI and UX
as well as the latest open source technologies.
this coursework consists of a complete overview of learning Qt5 including what can be accomplished
with it.
Our exploration of learning Qt5 will include enhancing command line applications with Qt, C++
GUI programming with Qt and the declarative Qt quick application development.
This video provides you with a glimpse of the entire course.
This video consists of nine sections. In the first section,
You'll learn how to enrich your command line applications with a Qt framework while learning the architecture
for example CommandLineOption.
Parsing is very common and useful console applications.
We're going to cover this in this section.
Then in the second section we would talk about multi-threading and the multi-processing.
The difference between them and what Qt has offer to make using multiple threads and process easy
writing a worker class and off-loading heavy job into separate threads to improve your application.
in the world of Internet, It's almost inevitable to do some network programming as in the section 3.
You will learn how network programming in Qt works.
For example we are going to build a TCP server and a TCP client.
Now we're going to show you how easy it is to let them work in Qt.
in Section 4.
We will learn important knowledge about Qt GUI programing such as signals and slots.
It is the bedrock of asynchronous and GUI programming in Qt. The we will learn all different kinds of widgets
in the 5th section
move further advanced knowledge GUI programming in the section 6 including the crucial concept models
and the views.
Surely it also means GUI widgets like table and layout which we covered
from the section 7 on.
We will enter the word of Qt quick and QML .The fundamental knowledge where we cover
first.
You also get to learn the declarative way building a GUI application
then in Section 8.
We will talk about the architecture of QML and its relationship with javascript and how easy it is to
import a javascript to resource file in QML and make use of it.
In the last section Qt Quick is covered so that we can make elegant GUI applications in a rapid and
declarative fashion.
This includes different styles and animations.
In this video course any prior knowledge about Qt is not required.
You should be familiar with C++ but you don't have to be a master.
Knowledge about javascript would be prefered but it is not required. Since a Qt is a cross-platform framework.
it means you can learn this course on either Windows, Mac or Linux.
By the end of this course you will have a good understanding of the Qt architecture . Be able to enhance
your console applications and create cross-platform Qt GUI applications and also write modern
dynamic GUI applications.
Declaratively with Qt quick.