We are going to talk about some standard layout managers.
We've actually used the QBoxLayout already and I'll briefly speak about it later. Then we will take a closer
look at the other two layouts.
There are only two different layouts in QBoxLayout manager.
QHBoxLayout for Qt horizontal box layout. And QVBoxLayout V for vertical. They line up widgets horizontally and vertically
respectively. And the yes we've changed the layout of centralWidget in main window to both of them in previous video already.
QGridLayout meanwhile gives you a two dimensional grid to arrange widgets.
It is divided into different same size cells.
While a widget can occupy multiple cells.
It is also the most flexible layout manager a among standard built-in layout managers.
As for QFormLayout, it can be seen as a specialized version of QGridLayout.
It lays out it's children into two column form.
Usually the labels are in the left column and the input widgets are on the right.
The advantages over QGridLayout is that the QFormLayout would  adhere to the different
platforms look and feel guidelines.
It supports row wrapping and has convenient API to add a label fields pairs.
Now let's get Qt Creator started and try these layouts out.
Create a new project or just reuse the project from one of the previous videos.
Now we drag four Push buttons into the view.
Try to switch the layout of centralWidget. Between the horizontal and the vertical.
This is basically the QBoxLayout manager.
Now if you click a centralWidget and click Lay Out in a Grid.
There is no difference.
You can of course think QBoxLayout as a special case of QGridLayout where you can only
have one column or one row.
But if you drag this button around.
So you notice the difference.
By default a button height is fixed so you can't make a button have two cells in a column.
But you can make it to have multiple cells in a row.
At last, if you click the Lay Out in a Form button.
You immediately see that widgets on the left column have been shrunk to the minimal size.
Meanwhile all widgets are also top aligned to give a look and feel that it is a form. So a typical usage
of this layout
is to use labels on the left and input widgets
such as line edit one the right.
The convenient API we have is to add such a pair in C++ code.
Let's close the UI design for now and go back to the code editor.
Here we learn a new template function in Qt.
qobject_cast(). It behaves similarly to the standard C++, dynamic_cast with some other advantages.
The template class argument must be a subclass of the given arguments type.
0 or null pointer is returned
if the cast failed.
So here since we make the layout of centralWidget. A formal layout. We can cast it into a QFormLayout pointer.
instead of the generic QLayout
Then we will have the convenient method addRow().
It has an overloaded function to except a string and a QWidget pointer.
So we can just create a widget here and use this method
to insert this new pair into the layout.
If you build and run an application now.
You'll see that in addition to those widgets we added in the UI design mode.
We now have a row with a label and a line edit
in the end.
In the next video you you will lean how to use Tabs
in Qt.