Hello everyone, welcome back.
Multi-threading. In this video we are
going to get our hands on QThread to
make use of threads in Qt application.
To cover the most of the used cases, we are going
to take a look at how to create a worker
thread and use QThread class to make
an application threaded. So let's do a
small exercise. Say we want to listen to
user input in the console application,
and a generator vector of random numbers.
Of course the size is determined from the
user input. To avoid blocking input
listening, we will have to create a
thread to put the random generation job
in a different thread, and also because
we could not do loop with a block event loop,
we will have to put it in a separate
thread as well. This is to meet the
last requirement that the application needs
to be responsive at all time. That means
the main thread where the main event
loop is cannot be blocked. Now let's open
Qt creator. First, let's create an InputWorker
It is a derived class from the
QObject. Here we define a signal input
available, and a slot function startWork.
We're going to use QTextString to
get input.
Yes, as you noticed, we are making use of
Qt signals and slots here. You can
imagine signals as events that a QObject
can trigger or emit. A slot function is a
handler to handle signals which have the
certain same signatures.
We will elaborate them in a future video,
for now let's focus on QThread in
this video. So in this input worker class,
we use the standard input to construct
that QTextString and then we're
going to use the QtextString object
"is" to read user input. Every time we read
the input from the user we are going to
emit a signal inputAvailable with the
input are the arguments. Another class
we're going to construct is random
vector worker. This class handles user
input and it generates randomized
vectors. In the input handler we will use
the current time at the feed to
initialize the random number generator,
and for each number in the vector we
will assign it with the new random
number. After this operation we are
output Randomized. Now let's go back to
main.cpp. To use two threads we simply
construct thread1 and thread2.
They are objects of QThread, and each of
them represents a separate thread. To
move our workers into their own thread,
we just need to call movetoThread
method with QThread address on the
argument. That's how simple it is to make
use of threads in Qt. So so to make use of
signal and slot here we connect inputAvailable
signal with the slot inputHandler,
so every time inputAvailable
is emitted, inputHandler will be
triggered, which will generate random numbers
for us. Lastly make sure the event loop
is running and stop the work of input
worker before we return a.exec. Now
let's build this application and test it
out!
As you can see we've already seen input
worker thread address and now let's give
it a vector, say ten. The operation is
instantly done but we can already see
the random vector worker exist in a
different thread. Now if we give a very
large number, say 200 million
it will take a while but at the same
time the application is not blocked
because the user input is immediately
entered in the Qt console application.
Note if your application is not started
in the terminal, you may need to
configure your projects, and make sure
Run in terminal is checked. In the next
video we are going to talk about multi-processing
and see how it is different
to use different threads in Qt.