Qt GUI Application Development Basics. In this section, you will learn Design in Qt Creator; Signals
and Slots; Window, Dialog, Pop up- all the basics of Qt GUI development.
The first video is about designing in Qt Creator. In this video,
we're going to take a look at how to create a Qt GUI application project in Qt creator, and to use its
design mode to design the user interfaces.
Now if you're ready, let's launch Qt Creator and get started.
Click new project button to create a new project. Select a Qt widget application project. Qt
Widgets means the traditional desktop widgets in C++. Set the project name.
Click next.
Now we have a chance to choose the Base class. In this example,
We'll use QMainWindow which gives us a full-featured window.
Meanwhile, QWidget will give you the freedom to create a custom widget, QDialog makes things easier
if you want to create a custom dialog that has simple contents with buttons to accept or reject.
So we have the skeleton we can build and the run immediately.
It will give you a blank window.
Since we haven't done any Ui yet. How can we add a text to widget, say, Hello World to the center
of Window?
Double click at mainwindow.ui on  the forms and then you will be redirected into Design mode.
You can only add things to this file in this mode.
On the left hand side, there are all widgets and the layouts that you can use. The bottom panel has the Action
Editor and the Signals and Slots Editor.
An action represents a clickable action, and it usually appears in the main or tool bar. There, on the
right hand side,
you have the top panel showing all widgets that belong to Ui this class.
The bottom panel gives you all property details of selected widgets object.
This is the place where you can further customize the object,
things like title, text,
icon, fontsize.
Now let's add a label widget to the window.
It's so simple that all you need to do is to track a label widget into the view in the middle.
You can then use the mouse to move or resize it.
To change the text in the label just double click the label and edit.
Or you can go to property panel,
scroll down to QLabel section,
here you can change the text.
Now we've changed it to Hello World.
Let's build
and then run it again.
And you get Helllo World placed in the window.
To make it aligned right in the center of the window, we need to make use of the layout.
If you look closely at the object tree you'll see that the MainWindow is treating central
Widget as a single widget that has some children objects and the central widget has its own layout to
arrange its children with its objects.
Since we only have one label widget here, to make the text show in the center we can use either vertical
layout or horizontal layout. Select the central Widget and then click vertical layout button. You'll
see the label which now fills up all space of the center widget. Then click LabelWidget object,
scroll down to the alignment property.
We'll change it to make aligned in the center both horizontally and vertically.
If you build and then launch the application again,
voilà (french word, = here it is) the text is shown right in the center.
It stays in the center
when you resize the window as well.
All widget objects you see from the object tree are also accessible in the code.
That's how you can control the user interfaces programmatically,
switch back to the Edit mode to check the mainwindow Headers file .h. You see that is a private member
called Ui.
This is the excess of the mainwindow.ui.
Now if you want to change the text of the label, you can do it by
adding the line to the constructor like this.
Let's run the application again.
You'll see the text is changed by the code.
In most cases, it's much preferred to have user interfaces design in .ui file whereever possible.
In the design mode,
it is much more intuitive and that you can immediately see what the interface looks like without even
running it. In the next video,
we are going to talk about signals and slots.