Editable widgets in this video we will talk about different editable input widgets, namely combo
box and text edit.
We are going to build an application to preview our text input.
We can use combo box to choose text mode, and the preview will be updated in real time.
So let's get started.
Launch your Qt Creator and create new project. Change the centralWidget to Lay Out Vertically. Drag
a text edit widget.
Drag a text edit widget into the top followed by a combo box widget, and then a text browser widget.
Now we will use to text browser as our previewer and the text edit as the input widget for user to type text,
the combo box to choose the mode.
How can you add items into the combo box?
You can simply double click it.
In the Edit dialog, you can add new items, arrange them, and delete them.
Here we put 2 combo box items, Plain and Html.
So much for the UI design import.
Let's go to the coding part.
Open mainwindow.h, the header file. And the private member variable plainText
Add two private slots functions, updateTextBrowser and onComboBoxChanged.
The onComboBoxChanged to slot function will be used to handle text change to signal when user changes
the combo box widget,
the updateTextBrowser and those text edit widgets updates.
Switch to the .cpp file.
Let's finish these two slot definitions.
We firstly, in the updateTextBrowser, get the text input from the text edit widget. The
document method returns a QTextDocumentPointer.
And we then call it toPlainText method to get the text from the user.
There is another method called toHtml that also returns a QString but that won't mark the text
up the Html,
which doesn't fit the case in this example. Then depending on whether the plainText is true or not,
we update the textBrowser document with a setPlainText or setHtml respectively.
In the onComboBoxChanged slot function,
we set plainText value depending on the combo box which is curretn text which is passed in the document
by the signal.
Then we update the TextBrowser to reflect the change.
Last but never the least,
don't forget to initialize plainText And connect those signals to the relevant slots.
Here you can see
the signal currentTextChanged from QComboBoxber has the same document as
onComboBoxChanged.
The code is now ready to be built. After that, run the application.
Let's find out if it works as we expected.
Try some simple Html mock-ups in the text edit widget.
With the plain text mode,the text browser shows the identical text.
Then if you change the combo box to select Html, you'll see nicely formatted text. And it gets updated
when you change the text in the editor.
Qt has also provided other input widgets.
You can think Line Edit, Plain Text Edit as the simpler version of Text Edit.
The APIs of all these input widgets are very similar and easy to pick up. In the next video,
You'll get to learn more about layout.