Welcome to learning Qt5: command-line. In this video we're going to take a look at how to create a
project with Qt creator and write our first project.
Hello Qt World!
And then I'm going to show you how to debug in Qt creator. Lets open Qt Creator and create
our first project. Click new project, select the Qt console application. A console application means
non GUI which basically means command-line only.
Now let's give it a name
HelloWorld.Here you also choose where you want to put the project and then select the Qt kit.
Lastly you will be able to choose a version control tool.
So just git.
normally you'd prefer a version control tool to manage large scale projects or simply just the one
to keep tracking your history and commit log.
Let's take a look at Qt creator, at the top left.
There's a project view of all the files that belong to this project.
The bottom left is currently open files and on the right is the editor.
Now let's write our first application.
Hello Qt
World.
By default you will be able to use qDebug which behaves very similar to the C programming
Printf function.
If you're not very used to it the first overloaded function is to simply print a string, now lets build.
once it's finished let's click run.
as you see Hello Qt World is printed in the application output.
As I said this is basically printf-like function.
So we can print out a number as the second argument.
Let's try it out. Build and then run it
once it's finished.
as you can see now it's printed 'Hello Qt  Word My 1 application'.
If you include QtDebug header you will be able to use it as an output stream instead of a C like function
simply call to qDebug, parentheses.
This will give you an output stream just it use it like a standard cout.
now build and run it again. the same output is printed using this new syntax. You have also used standard C++ standard template
library, such as std::cout.
You don't have to click build
and then click run. If you just click run button, Qt creator will build and then run the latest
code for you.
Now let's try a variable. Let's type int num equals to 1.
Now this should give us "Hello Qt World
My 1 application" as we expected.
so far the application runs as we expected.
But if you don't get the expected results don't worry we can debug this very easily
in Qt creator. Just click the debug button on the left, switch to debug mode.
Here you can put a break point very easily.
Right clicking on the side.
Now I put a break point in line seven.
Let's run debugger.
On the top right,
we can track all our variables.
Now the application stops at line 7.
As you can see the num is not yet initialized.
Now if we click step over button, you can see the variable now has been initialized to 1.
For more information I suggest you to click help button to read Qt creator manual about debugging.
in the next video.
We are going to go through fundamentals of Qt.