Signals and Slots. In this video, we'll talk about the most prominent trait of Qt: signals and
slots.
It's rare that's a real world Qt application that doesn't use signals and slots at all. It's extremely
hard to imagine a Qt GUI application without the signals and slots. Signals and slots are the bedrock
of the asynchronous Qt world.
So we are going to firstly go through the signals and slots
mechanism and get some kinds of practices.
So what's a signal?
In practice it's a synonym of event.
Whenever there's a need to notify potential receivers, for example a user interaction such as typing, clicking
or program flow control such as an execution finishing. The object that emits the signal is called sender.
The function that can be connected to a signal is called Slot.
You don't have to connect all signals to all slots.
Now let's take a look at slots.
A slot is essentially a function that is called to handle an event by connecting to the signal. The object
that has the slot and then receives the signal is called receiver. To wrap it up,
an event happens, which makes the relevant signals emitted. Then the connected slots will be invoked.
Let's get our hands on some exercises to see how we can define signals and slots and how to connect
a signal to a slot. If you launch
Qt Creator and use the project from last video,
or you can create a new Qt widgets application project. To define a signal, you define it as a regular
member function
after the Signals keyword
like this. We've just defined a signal code init.
It must be defined after Signals keyword. Signals are special that the master return void.
They may have arguments and you only need to declare them in the header file.
There is no definition of signal function. To emit signal,
let's just go to the CPP file and emit the signal in the constructor.
That is the key word "emit"
and the signal function. Meanwhile a slot function is just a regular function that has the same arguments
lazed (từ này nữa) as the signal does.
It is usually a member function that is defined with the slots keyword.
It can return a value and it can be called directly as a member function.
It can either be public protected or private.
And now we are defining a private slots function.
What are we going to do with this function?
Well we're simply print a message.
OK to make the message printed we need to connect the signal to a slot. To do that,
we just need to call the connect method provided by QObject.
Since basically all QClasses derive from QObject.
You just need to type connect.
There has been a new syntax introduced in 2005 to enable compiler to do some compile time safe checks
for us.
So instead of writing it in the old way with signals and slots macros, we use the new signal,
we use the new syntax.
The first argument is the pointer to the sender and at the second the one is the address of the signal.
The third one is the pointer to the receiver followed by a slot address.
In this case, we need to connect the signal and the slot before we emit it, only the slots that are already
connected as the time when signals are emitted will be invoked.
That means if you connect a signal and a slot after the signal emission, that slot may never be
called.
Now if we run the application,
we can see that init message is printed.
A signal has also been connected to C++ 11 lammed pointer.
Let's doubleclick to main.cpp. Here, we can connect the abuse in signal code destroyed to a functor
in the main.cpp.
And then remember the Connect is a member function of queue object but it is also a static one.
Hence we can still use it even when we are not in a queue object.
Close
the beauty and destroy the signal and a C++ 11 operator and a C++ 11 lambda Foxton
let's beaute and then run this project in
meme window.
In it it meant window has initialized we see in it's printed and with this join it's
we see men window destroyed message printed it has provided tons of computing signals as well as slots
to help you to code next for that.
Be sure to always check the documentation of the butte incudes classes that you are working with in
the next video.
We are going to talk about window dialog and the pop up.