Table model and view. In this video we will talk about the
QSqlTableModel which provides a data model for a database table and the QTableView which displays
items of data in the table. Let's launch qt creator and create a new qt widgets application project.
And the project file, in case you forgot, it's the .pro file
And SqlModel into qt configuration field this enables us to use QSqlModel which
is necessary for QSqlTableModelable . UI first, now if you DoubleClick mainwindow.ui
and redirect to design mode. You can find the table widget,
pay attention to the widget.
It is the table view widgets that says model based instead of the table widget which is item based. So if you
drag table view widget into the view and change the layout of a central widget so that the Table
View widgets can make use of all the space.
Then in the mainwindow.h file declared to private member functions init D-B
and initModel. They are going to initialize the sql database connection and the
QSqlTableModel respectively.
Moreover initModel will return a pointer to QSqlTableModel.
In the main windows constructor in the cpp file we first call initDb to initialize a database
connection.
Then we get QSqlTableModel pointer for initModel.
To make the tableview
use this model
you just need to call set model method,
simple as that. People will look at initDb definition.
Make sure you've included QSqlDatabase and QSqlQuery haeder, they are required to
construct a QSqlDatabase object and execute Sql statements. In initDb we first need make a
QSqlDatabase object by calling the static member function addDatabase the argument is a
QSqlDatabase Type.
Here is SQLite since we don't give a second argument which is the database connection
and this database connection will be that the default database connection. Then we call setDatabaseName method
to set SQLite as a in memory database.
We then open this connection and execute some standards Sql statements.
Creating a table called price and insert a few rows into the table.
In another word this function creates a default database connection to add inmemory in SQLite database
and create a database table that we would use later.
Now let's move to initModel function, in this function
we first create a QSqlTableModel instance.
Here we didn't give the second argument to this constructor which is the type of SqlDatabase therefore the model
uses the default database connection which we just made in initDb.
Then we called setTable to set the database table that it will read.
Then we call select to get all the data from the database table and populate
them into this model.
In the end we use setHeaderData method to create table header.
Then we return this pointer.
If you look back at the constructor, it should be much clearer that initDb create the underlying
database, that initModel creat the data model.
And lastly we use a set model to let tableview widgets access data from the model.
Now if you build and run the application
you can see a table shown in the window, it shows all the data from the database.
In the next video
you will learn the list model and view.