A video which covers an event driven GUI list program. We're going to cover types of programming concurrency,
functor base signal/slot connections and finished by doing an event loop driven example.
Now one of the key proponents in Qt is it's event driven framework.
The good news is that even if we're not using graphics, we can still use the event loop.
So let's figure out how.
So if we open up Qt Creator, File, New file or project application, Qt Console Application, Choose
a name and a location.
We'll stick with the qmake build system, select the kit and do some project management.
And what we see here is it's going to create a small application and it's going to create a new QCoreApplication
call exec().
So this is actually the event loop. How to do the event loop in a non-GUI program?
So if we run this, it will go ahead and since there's nothing to tell a differently abled just run the
event loop forever.
What this means for us is that we can take signals and slots and put them into our console application.
So where would this be useful?
Well any application that needs to weigh on IO is always a good target for an event loop.
Any sort of network application or server would benefit from this application.
One of the reasons we talked about doing a graphic list application was for the use case of us being run
on a server.
So let's work to expand that a little bit.
Typically we run on servers either because we they have more processing power than our typical desktop
or we've got a process that needs to run for a long time to provide some kind of service.
Now the microservice architecture has been one design pattern that has gained a huge amount of steam recently.
So let's design a small application that would sit on our server and spin up other services as needed
or on demand using subprocess.
If you're not familiar programming concurrency has typically gained by either using threading an event
loop or multiple processes. Each concurrency has its own strengths and weaknesses.
But the nice part about using multiple processes is that we get to use the operating system to manage
switching rather than manually programming ourselves.
This is why microservices have gotten so popular.
So let's go ahead and design a manager app that would launch our microservices.
Now typically for this, we'd use a networked application.
But in order to keep this example simple, we're going to use a timer to simulate some sort of demand.
We will cover setting up a networked application in the next video.
So we look at our main.cpp, we're going to create a small class called ProcessManager and go
ahead and start that.
And if we look at the header file, this, one important thing that we need know is that we need to subclass
our ProcessManager from Q_OBJECT and include QObject macro.
This is going to allow us to use signals and slots.
So in our case we want to use signals and slots to help us understand how our subprocesses are doing.
There are several signals we want to collect and several slots we want to vote.
So if we go up and look at the constructor. Here's our timer that's going to stimulate our demand and
we connect our 'timer' 'timeout' signal to the start_process command.
That's part of this class.
So the start_process is that's where we're actually going to start.
And you'll note that this start_process command takes in a 'name' so the 'name' should actually be the name
of the process or the file location.
In this case we're just going to leave that blank since we're just an example.
But normally you'd want it to be whatever service that you're trying to start.
So the first thing that we need to do here is actually create our QProcess and then we'll add this
to our list of processes and then we'll go ahead and start this with our name that we want to add.
So this name will be the file path or the name that's linked in your path.
So let's go ahead and pass this to a helper method to help us setup some of the signals.
Now what we'd like to do is connect the signal for finish to our processes_finished method.
We'd also like to pass in the original process name as well which we can't normally do with signals.
So this is where our functor base signals come to the rescue.
Now what we'd like to do is connect the signal_finished to our process_finished method as part of this
class.
The only challenge here is we'd like to pass in the original process name as well which we typically
can't do.
But that's where functor base signals come into the rescue.
So let's go ahead and implement that.
Now so since the actual finished signal is overloaded we use this QOverloaded helper method to
kind of help us connect the signals and slots correctly and then the functor based signal is you never
seen that before.
You have an argument list that will pass in, the method list that contains all of our method arguments
and then the actual code block that we'll use.
So the first thing that we want to pass in is the variables that will need as part of our function.
So in this case we all need the actual process, the process_name.
And then if we want to call a method from the class we'll need a pointer to the instance variable.
So there's the process, process_name and a pointer to the instance.
The next thing we'll need to do is go ahead and grab the two variables that are coming in.
So we've got an integer and the exit status and we'll pass this in to the actual method call here.
And the int is actually known as the exit_code.
And then we've got our ExitStatus.
So now that we've got all of the overhead information, the only thing we need to do is actually call
the method.
So in our case, the method that we want to call is part of this class is the process_finished. This
takes in our exit_code, status, process and process_name
Awesome.
So that's a really challenging example of a functor based signal.
So let's try a a little bit of a simpler one and this one won't be overloaded and the signal that we
want to connect to is the error occurred and the slot that we want to connect it to is is our error handler.
So if you remember using functors, this first block is where we pass in the arguments that we want to
pass and the method.
This is part of the method call.
So we'll need to grab both the just the error of this one and then see where we actually run our code.
So are the methods that we want we want to keep a hold of the process the process name any pointer to
the instance. And then in our method call,
the only thing that we're going to grab is the QProcess, ProcessError and then the method call that we want
to call as part of our class is just the error_handler and we'll go ahead and pass in our error, process
and process_name. Awesome. So that's a two example of using functor base signal/slot connections.
One that was overloaded and one that didn't need to actually be overloaded.
So now that we've got our signals connected up. Let's go ahead and implement our crash process handling.
So let's assume that if the process exits normally, we'll just let it fade into the background.
The one thing that we will want to do is remove it from our vector of processes.
The thing that we do want to do is if our process actually crashes, we want to go ahead and restart it,
which is part of the reason that we actually passed in the process_name and again to do this, we'll do
call the start method here.
Now that we've got our crash process handling set up, let's go ahead and handle a sort of kill signal.
Normally this we passed in remotely as well but in this instance we're actually going to simulate one
and we'll simulate it using this single shot from QTimer.
Now part of the reason we're using this ifdef- else- endif is as mentioned in this comment. Windows
applications, they may or may not handle the WM_CLOSE message.
So we're going to bring out the big guns and instead of trying to terminate them, we're going to go ahead
and call kill() on them. If we're not running in Windows,
the one thing that we do want to do is give our processes a chance to kind of shut down by themselves
and the way we do that is to call the actual terminate() method.
And this way if our processes have any files or anything that they need to clean up first that gives
them a chance.
Now you can still actually call the kill() method here.
But again if you call the kill here, it doesn't give your process the chance to sort of clean up first themselves,
which is why we like to try and call terminate() first and we probably want to give our users
some sort of way to actually go in and specify kill if terminate doesn't work.
Sometimes our processes can hang.
The last thing that we're not going to touch on here is the error handling.
So if you look through the code that's left here we've got quite a few possible errors that can pop
out here.
We've got Crashed, FailedToStart, Timedout, WriteError etc... But this shows you how you would actually
go through and have a code block to go ahead and handle all of that.
But with that, with all the coding that we've done, let's go ahead and run this and make sure it works.
So if you got to pass in the process name here in a semi-colon there so now you can see is we are going
to cycle through the code here.
And as part of the start method will actually reach a maximum process here and actually stop the timer.
So we're simulating some sort of network process that is going to tell us to start. See the process
name here is left blank.
But we could put in any sort of process.
I just didn't have a good cross-platform one to put in.
And we'll go ahead and start all four of our processes before we reach our max processes and go and
stop our timer.
And then here's our killed process where we actually killed our sacrificial process.
Awesome all down so we successfully created a small event loop based non-GUI example where we covered
creating functor signals and slots and touched on how to do programming concurrency.
Please join us next time where we talked about supercomputing with networks.