This is a video, we're gonna covers the treeview and model.
In this video we're going to cover Qmodelindex tree structure,
mapping tree models to real data, and walk through
an example where we implement
our own custom tree model.
Treemodels can be challenging.
So let's get started with Qt indexing paradigm.
It uses model indexes to separate the data representation from the way it is accessed.
In practice this means that you will have to programmatically bridge your data representation to Qt
data representation which is the model index.
It's we're talking about how model index are represented as that can give you some insight into the
bridging process.
Q model indexes are defined by row, a column, an apparent key model index.
The requirement for a parent key model index for every item creates the requirement for a shadowy data
list root item, represented in this diagram by the dash box.
This root item doesn't have any data itself. its only purpose is to be the parent to the first set of
real data items.
In this diagram it's the first column.
Here are the first three columns. in this diagram,
every solid box represents a data item.
So let's look at how to define a q model index for some of our items that are labeled in our diagram,
starting with the root item.
You can create an index to the root item by calling the constructor for the queue model in X class.
I know this is invalid C++ code, but it helps demonstrate how easy it is to create a reference to the
root item, which is good, because if you're looking at the diagram, the parent for both box A and box C
is the root item.
So let's show how to create an index for box a. Qmodelindex is defined by row column and parent.
So for box A, the description would be row 0, column 0 and the root parent.
Pretty easy.
Let's take a look at the difference between box A and box C.
We're no longer in the first row, so the index for box C would be defined as row 2 column 2 and the
root parent.
But now what do we do if the parent isn't the root.
Well let's take a look at the index for Box B. in order to get the Qmodelindex for B.
We first need the Qmodelindex for A because Box A is box B's parent.
Once we have the parent define, box B would be Row 1 column 0 and the parent A.
So now that we understand how Qt represents our data, how are we going to represent our data
for this example. in this example, we're going to use a custom colored tree item class to hold our data.
This box represents an instance of our color tree item. In our implementation,
each item will have a pointer to the parent item.
The pointer is represented by the green arrow and a list of pointers to the child items, represented
by these two green arrows.
Each item will also contain a list of color data represented by these varying blue boxes, the color values
we use to populate the columns.
Now if you squint enough, this should look very similar to the tree model from our previous slides.
If this slide doesn't make sense, don't worry about it too much.
The important piece to remember is that you need to map your data to Qt model index, so it's better
to have an idea of how Qt represents its data, which would be row, column and parent, then worry about
how we represent data
for this example.
So now that we have some idea of how representing our data, and how Qt does. let's look at implementing
the mapping.
When we subclass Qt abstract item model, the two methods that we need to reimplement are the parent
model and the index.
When we subclass queue abstract item model, the two methods that we need to reimplement are the parent
method and the index method.
Those are the two that are going to do the data translation for us.
Let's go ahead and look at what that looks like.
We'll start by looking at our concrete implementation of QAbstractItemModel.
It should look exactly like our QAbstractListModel
reimplementation with the only difference being that we have the two methods mentioned before the index
and parent method.
Now the only weird bit of this is we need to translate between QModelIndex and our internal data
quite frequently.
So we're going to implement a helper method to do that translation for us.
We'll call it get_item_from_index.
It's going to return a color Tree item pointer, which is our internal data representation, and it will
take in a QModelIndex.
Just go ahead and implement that first.
So we switch over to the picture model of C++, CPP will go here.
So the first thing that we want to do in this method is check to see if the index passed in is our root
item or not.
By calling the is valid method on our index, if the index is not valid ,it is a shadowy root item which
holds no data.
So this will represent this code right here which represents the fact if it is not valid, and will go
ahead and return our root item.
If the index is valid, then we can use the internal pointer method on Q model in text to get a pointer
to our internal data.
We use a static_cast to switch the data type from a null pointer to our internal representation. Lastly
will just check to make sure that it's valid, and if it is, we'll go ahead and return the item. sweet.
Now that we've got that implemented. let's put together our parent method.
The first thing that we're gonna do in this method is check if the index passed in is valid.
If it isn't, that means it's our root item ,and we can return an empty QModelIndex as the root item
has no parent. then we use our get_item_from_index command that we just created to get a colortreeitem
pointer as previously mentioned, the color tree item class contains a reference to the parent item,
so we'll call that method to get a colortreeitem pointer to the parent. We'll check again to see if
our parent item is the root item, as we can always return an empty Q model index
in that case. otherwise we'll create an index using the create index method from our class.
We need to pass in the row, column and a pointer to our internal data.
By convention, only the first column of items in a treeview have children.
So our column value will be equal to zero.
Our implementation of colortreeitem also tracks the row it occupies with the child number method.
So we use all three of those.
So there's our row.
Here's our column is equal to zero, and we'll pass in our parent item.
Awesome.
Let's tackle the index method first.
Let's tackle the index method next, remembering that we're always looking out for our data lists
root item, let's check to make sure that we're getting passed in isn't the root item first.
We'll do this using the hasIndex method.
Now we're going to work backwards from our parent method. Instead of getting the parent from the child,
let's get the child from the parent. We'll need to get our internal data representation out, which we'll
do by calling our get_item_from_index method.
Lasly we'll check the child and create the index if it is valid using the createIndex function and
QAbstractItemModel.
If the child is not valid, will return an empty QModelIndex.
The last thing we'll do is implement part_of_the_data method.
Specifically the Q decoration role. we'll get our item from our queue model index first. remembering
that each item contains a list of color data which is used to populate each column in the row, means
that we'll use the column method from the model index to return the proper color data from the item.
Now we've implemented most of a tree model.
So what is our tree model actually displaying.
Well if we take a look at the main window implementation, we can see that we create a QPushButton.
So here is the QPushButton that's clicked method
down here is connected to the get colour's slot.
See here. we look at the get color method where we can see as we create a QColor dialog using that
get color static method to get out a new color which is a Qcolor.
We pass that into this function called generate hues, which gives us a vector of Q colors, and then we
go ahead and add that into our model.
So let's just run this real quick and take a look and see what it does.
So now if we click this button at the bottom and we select a color, we can see that it populates the
view by expanding this selection.
What we find is that we have a very rough color scheme generation app, by selecting a color we automatically
calculate 11 other potential colors to use in a color scheme.
If we hover over the values, what we'll find is we do this by altering the values by 30 each time while
holding the saturation in value constant.
So if you look here you see the hue 60 saturation 254 and value of 255, here is the first one hue of 90 saturation
and values the same.
Next one 120.
Next one 150.
There are of course other ways to generate color schemes and I would encourage you to look at this Wikipedia
entry.
And implement some of your own into this application.
Who knows it might help you create some visually appealing applications.
But for now we've finished our implementation of our custom tree model, walk through how to map Qt
model index to our own internal data representation, and discuss in depth the Qmodelindex.
Join us next time.
In the interacting with the web section.