And this is Section 1- 'Moving beyond GUI Application' which covers using Qt to create console application.
In this video we're going to cover why we want to use Qt for console application, Qt file directory
manipulations and Qt messaging debugging.
So let's answer the obvious question up front.
Why would we use a GUI development platform for console or non-graphical applications?
Well it is much much more than a GUI development platform.
In fact I won't give you one reason to use Qt for console applications.
I'll give you 6. So if your code involves SQL database access, XML parsing, JSON parsing, thread
management, networking, event handling, any combination of the aforementioned tasks and it's better for
you to use C++ you should consider using Qt. There's no need to reinvent the programming wheel.
Another reason to use Qt for non-graphical applications is that your environment might constrain
you from using a GUI for anything.
Common examples of where this would apply would be if you're running on a server, creating a simple utility
or creating a bunch of services for a microservice architecture.
So now that we've explained why, let's tackle how we create a project without a GUI. We're going to tackle
the nonevent loop based example in this lesson.
But we'll do an event loop based example in the next one.
So if we switch to the Qt Creator, go to 'File', 'New File or Project', 'Non-Qt Project', 'Plain C++ Application'.
Select a project location, we will stick with the 'qmake' build system and select the desktop kit and
then select our version control and we go ahead and run this project.
What you'll see is this is a very simple Hello World example but we have this process stuff that pops
up every time we run this.
If we don't want that process of the pop up, we can navigate into the '.pro', under this console,
we will take that out and now if we rerun this, this application output will actually pop up in here.
Awesome. So now, we know how to do that.
Let's go ahead and create a small utility.
Now we need to create some photos for use in the next section.
A bunch of randomly colored photos to be exact.
So let's create an application to generate some photos.
We change the code.
See I've already outlined what we need to do here and the first step is file path manipulation.
Now I don't often memorise things programming but if there's one thing I invariably end up memorising,
it's file path manipulation.
Being able to change directories, create files and create directories while incredibly mundane is in
the lifeblood of programming.
So we're going to cover it now.
Qt provides a cross-platform method for file manipulation in QDir. QDir can be used to manipulate
pathnames, access information regarding path and files and manipulate the underlying file system.
So let's go ahead and get access to our current working directory. Awesome.
So now that we've got access to our current directory, we need to go back to the root of the project
which means we need to backup 2 directories and then change into the folder for Section 2.
We're going to create a directory called 'pics' in the section 2 folder.
So go and change into that section 2 now.
Now I can of course tell our program to do this but whether or not this is a valid operation is another
question entirely.
So let's go ahead and make sure that it was a valid directory change and if it's not that we go ahead
and inform our users. Nice.
So now that we've got this boolean. How do we inform our users?
Well Qt has a built in debugging messaging framework.
The nice thing about using this framework is that we can change a flag and it can be compiled out.
We're going to use QFatal here since this is a pretty much no go for our application.
Our users will need to take some drastic steps in order to make it an actual valid run of the program
but if it isn't quite that drastic there's also QInfo, QWarning, QCritical and QDebug.
So if you actually look at this message, it tells us is that the directory 2_section was not
found and that we need to change our code to 'cd' into the absolute path for our system instead,
or move the build to the expected directory which it then gives us the expected directory.
Now we might want to tell our users what the absolute path is.
So let's go ahead and do that right now before we actually exit this program.
So since we can't go any further from here we'll go ahead and return out of our main file or a main
function here.
So now that we've ensured that we're in the correct directory or it at least exists.
Let's go ahead and create our 'pics' directory.
Well actually let's only create it if it doesn't exist in the first place.
Now this is a little bit of trivial code because if we look at this make mkdir function it'll actually
returns out of boolean.
But I wanted to find excuse to use this exist function.
So you know that it 'exists' function exists right.
So we also need a change into this directory, so go into that now.
Perfect.
Now we need to remove any old photos.
We use a Qt specific keyword to make this a little easier,
the 'foreach' command which makes it much simpler to iterate over containers.
So the entryList will go ahead and give us a bunch of filepaths and then if we find any filepath
in this pics directory, we're going to go ahead and remove them. Awesome.
So now when you just need to generate our 100 photos we'll go ahead and do this using a big for loop.
The first thing that we need to do in our for loop is go ahead and create our QImage.
And this is going to be a 100 by 100 pixel photos.
So we'll go and specify that here and then pass in a valid format.
Now we need to fill the image with a color.
So we actually need to pick a color first.
So there's a couple of thing to note here.
First of all we create the 'colors' at the top of our actual function. It is just a QVector of QColor which
we get from this method get_virdis_values(), which comes from this header file, which just defines a bunch
of colors.
Also the other thing to note is we're using the modulus operator.
You'll see this quite a bit using qrand or the RAND function and the modulus operator to kind of get
some sort of bounded random number.
So this isn't actually been correctly because you don't know what the maximum number is but it's not
been in 256 increments basically.
So what I want to demonstrate right now is basically a good way to actually create a true random distribution.
So we go out and use the class QRandomGenerator and we'll create that.
And so instead of using this, we can actually call the 'bounded' function on 'random' and pass in the maximum
which is going to be 255.
So this will actually return us a better more random than using qrand with modulus operator.
This is probably still valid code if you don't really care about how it's bent.
But it's important to know.
Awesome.
So now that we've got our color, let's go ahead and fill in our image.
And once we've got it filled, the last thing we need to do is go ahead and save it. Before we save it,
we actually need a file path to save it and so let's create that and then just to make sure that we
got everything right,
let's go ahead and pass this in to the de-bug before actually saving our file. And that's it. Let's go
and run this to
make sure it works.
Looks like everything worked out OK.
Now this might not seem like a big deal.
Let's think about this for a second.
Without the help of Qt, we would have had to dive into the portable network graphics or PNG format
and figure out ourselves how to manually save a PNG file.
Additionally if we wanted this code to be cross-platform we'd have to individually implement the file
manipulations ourself, which would be a huge drag, which is why we're using Qt in this case for
console applications and why can be so useful.
And with that we successfully created our pictures for our future graphics library while demonstrating
Qt debugging messaging and the QDir class for file manipulations.
Join us next time where we go over event loop applications and beyond GUI programming section.