I'm Ben Hoff and welcome to 'Mastering Qt 5 GUI Programming' by Packt publishing.
As a brief introduction to myself, I actually have a lot of experience with Qt, having started programming with both C++ and
Qt, developing realtime graphical simulations.
I also have extensive experience with PyQt, creating Chat GUIs and have had success integrating
OpenCV and Qt to provide facial recognition applications.
If you'd like to start me on the web feel free to visit my blog, YouTube channel or follow me on
Github.
This course will provide you an in-depth view of the Qt framework, covering both the traditional C++
aspects as well as exploring the newer QML options. To provide a little more depth,
we'll look into moving beyond GUI applications which covers both how the make command line programs
as well as exploring and utilizing some of the network capability to create a simple supercomputing framework.
Once you're done with that, we move on to the model view where we'll explore in depth Qt model view
framework and tease out some of its inner workings.
We'll also look into interacting with the web, showing how to embed web pages in our application as well
as reaching out and interacting with JavaScript on the pages.
Once we're done with Web, we'll move onto the world of multimedia covering recording video, audio and
photos in our applications.
Additionally adding in open computer vision and the Qt 3D module, we will then move on to our first
Qt section covering communicating between QML and C++ as well as creating our own modules and types.
Once we're done introducing QML, we will go more in depth coverage charts, animation, particles and 3D in
visual representations.
We'll start to round out the last of that course covering compiling and distributing for both desktop
and mobile. We will cover Windows, Linux and stack distributions on the desktop and cover how to set up and
distribute apps for Google on mobile.
I expect users to have a basic understanding of Qt and C++ but I'm confident that if you're willing to
learn, you can understand all of the material from this course.
By the end of this course you should have an in-depth knowledge and experience to distribute your
applications on any platform.
So let's go ahead and get started.