This video which covers custom models we're going to cover why create custom models how to choose our
models subclass based on the data structure and then walk through an example where we implement our
own custom list model.
So let's go ahead and get started.
So first off why would we create our own custom model especially if we've been getting by so well with
the built in Qt standard item model.
Well sometimes our data is complex.
It comes from different sources.
It's dynamic or it's so expensive to query that we need to create our own model just to get around these
limitations.
You will occasionally also run into corners of the Qt framework where the commune's classes are not
powerful enough to implement what you need requiring you to strike off on your own as well.
So if you know you need a custom model what class should you based your implementation on.
Well it depends on your data structure.
If your data is represented by a list consider using Qt abstract list model.
If it's a table.
Qt abstract table model and a tree structure require you to subclass queue abstract item model completely.
I would also encourage you to try and simplify your models if possible.
So why you didn't.
Maybe a tree structure.
It may be possible to display as a table if you get creative tricks like this will help lower the complexity
of your code.
But for now let's go ahead and implement the simplest example.
A Qt abstract list model.
Now the nice thing about this model is that the data isn't hierarchical.
We don't have to worry about a couple of functions which we'll talk about in the second.
So here's our simple photo item model for this model.
We need to reimplement the row count data set data and flags method.
Now as I previously mentioned the two functions that we don't have to worry about are the index and
parent functions because our data is hierarchical.
So let's start implementing it.
If we go down to our row count the row count method is going to be very simple.
Only the root node should return the list size for all other valid parents.
Row count should return a zero.
So let's go ahead and check that.
I will say if the index is valid we will go ahead and return a 0.
The reason that we do this is so that our model never looks like a tree model in another view for
any of the non-valid i.e. the root node will go ahead and return our internal data type which in this
example is colors and since it's a vector we can just return the size function in order to implement
our data method.
The only role that we're concerned with is the cute decoration role.
So we're going to check and return data based on that.
And again we've got a couple of catch alls So if the index isn't valid we're just going to return a
q variance and at the end of this method if we end up at the end we're going to return a blank queue
as well for all our other display's role.
The only rule that we're worried about is we're going to say if the rule is equal to the Qt declaration
rule that means that we want to return our color information so we'll go ahead and do that.
We say return again.
Just the colors.
And since that's the vector we'll just access the row method in the index and go ahead and return that
directly.
The next thing that we need to do is implement the set data function.
Now the first thing that we need to do is to make sure that we're actually changing the data.
So let's go ahead and check that first.
The easiest way to do this is access the data using the data method which has two variables the index
which we already have and the role which we have as well and what we want to make sure that we're not
passing in something that's already there.
So we want to make sure that this value variant that we're passing is new data so we want to make sure
that the data that's in there currently is not the data that we're setting it to.
Once we've got that we'll go ahead and make the changes in our underlying data which is again our colors
and will access this using the list in accessor and we'll go ahead and grab the row and what we'll
do is we'll set this equal to our value.
But we do want to change the type so we'll use the value method on our value to get the Q color out.
Now one thing that's important to note is when we actually set data we need to let the viewers know
that they need to update the data and to do that we need actually emit a signal and the signal that
we need to emit is actually the data change signal which takes in several things.
The top left index the bottom right index which for our purposes they are the same right.
We're only changing one.
And then the actual rolls that we're changing which since again we're only changing a single roll.
We're not super concerned with anything else.
So go ahead and pass in the two indexes left most and bottoms and then we'll create a quick q vector
integer type and we'll go ahead and pass our roll directly in.
The last thing we want to do is go ahead and return.
You know if this worked or not in more complex models or what we want would probably be some type of
data validation.
Now since this is a very very simple model we're not going to do that.
But if for example our data validation failed then we want to be sure to let our user know that whatever
they tried didn't work.
And so we do that by what we return on the boolean here.
Awesome.
So the last thing that we need to re-implement is the flags method call.
So the default flags include a item is selectable type which obscures the color whenever we select an
item in the view.
So you can already see this default code if the index isn't valid which means it's the root index we
return no item flags because the root doesn't need to be decorated with any type of flags.
And the only other thing that we want to do is go ahead and return for all our other items.
We want to let the viewers know that the item is actually enabled so the item flags can be pretty tricky.
If you don't return this item as a table are pictures that will get returned will actually be in grayscale
which is a goofy thing to try to track down if you don't know where to look.
So one thing to note is we're slightly gaming the system here because we don't return a item is editable
command but if you run this code you can actually see you can edit stuff.
So normally what you'd see here is a no other item rule that says that the item is editable which we're
actually not going to do but that is exactly how you would implement or stack those type of item roles
together.
And the reason that we're not doing that is because a typical item delegates that actually do the editing
they don't play well with cue dialogues.
So if we go ahead and look at this main window implementation and then look at the change color slot
which is how we're actually changing the colors.
We first get the actual current color out but then we actually call this dialog.
And in order to make that dialog work we need to do that outside of the normal editing process which
is why we're not returning that edible flag because we're actually doing it outside.
Let's go ahead and run this and make sure it works.
Yes we messed up there a little bit with our verbiage be parent instead of index there we go.
So here we've got our random assortment of pictures.
And as promised if you click one of these our dialog pops open and we can actually go ahead and significantly
alter any of the items that we want which gets set.
If you look back at the slot so we'll close this out and we'll look at the implementation of the main
window.
So he uses dialogue to go ahead and get the color and then we get our model and actually call the set
a command on it manually and pass in the index color and the cute decoration roll.
So with that we've successfully implemented everything that we need.
So we successfully implemented a custom model.
We talked on the model data relationship as well as talked about the need for why would we need to
create our own custom model Please join us next time where we implement a treeview as part of the series.