List Model and View. In this video,
you will learn how to create a simple ListModel
with QstringListModel, then
we will access data from this model in
QListView. Lastly, as we mentioned
before, the Model-View architecture
operates the data model and the
presentation. We will validate this
principle by showing you how easy it is
to show that from QSqlTableModel in
QListView. If you are ready,
let's get started!
Launch Qt creator and open the project
from TableModelView, drag a
ListView widget and drop it into the
central widget, side-by-side with
previously added TableView widget. Now
let's go to mainwindow.h and let's
declare yet another private member
function to initialize a QStringModel.
Here, instead of returning a QstringListModel
pointer, we choose to return
the base class point. It's a common way
when dealing with polymorphism. Let's
take a closer look at this function
definition in the CPP file. We first
create a QStringList which is
basically a list of strings using C++ 11
initializer list. Then we construct our
QStringListModel with this list.
To show you how data accessing in this
model works,
I call setData method which modifies
data in this model with model index. We
can get
the model index by calling method index
and gives the row and column number.
Because this is a ListModel the second
argument which is the column number can be
ignored. So this statement changes the
third row of model from Thyme to Cinnamon.
Let's go to the constructor and the let
ListView use the StringModel. If you
build and run this application, you'll
see that the ListModel is shown in
the ListView widget, with its third
item changes to Cinnamon. Now remember we
said we are going to use the QSqlTableModel
with the ListView. How to
do that? You might wonder. It's just a
one-line string calling setModel from
ListView with the argument QSqlTableModel
pointer instead of initSttringModel.
And if you now run the application,
Yes, see the ListView shows the first
column of the table, the reason behind
this is that a StringModel is a special
case of the table which has only one
column, and because the view uses the
model index to access data. It doesn't
really care about the underlying data
structure or the data model type as long
as it can get data via standard
interfaces. The different representation
only exists inside the View. And how
about editing? Try to change one element
in the list, and you'll see the change
immediately reflects on the table view as
well, and vice versa.
So when you double-click the view, the
default delegate which is the QStyleItemDelegate
handles the input and
changes the data in the data model.
Because both views access the same data
model, the relevant signals emitted and
the slot invoked, which in turn
triggers a Pear event that changes the
values in the View. In this section we've
learned what the Model-View architecture
is in Qt, and how to use Table Model
and the View, how to use the List Model
and the View. In the next section you'll
start the journey of learning Qt quick
with introduction to Qt quick and the
QML.