This is video of diving into Model/View section which covers filtering. In this video, we're going to cover
a quick review of Qt's Model/View, establishing a need for filtering with a real life problem before
covering how to filter using a QSortFilterProxyModel.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Now this is going to be a relatively easy section, since we already laid most of the groundwork last
time.
But as a reminder, we've got our model/view framework that Qt relies on.
Now our model is responsible for controlling how the view sees the data.
Now often it's more useful for our users to see part of the data rather than all of it.
So we're going to look at how to cut down some of the data our users are seeing using filtering.
Since the model is responsible for controlling what data the view sees, that's where we're going to
focus on implementing our filter. For our problem,
we're going to continue to work with pictures. So maybe we've got to design app, and working through a
bunch of differently colored random photos, like let's say, 6000 different photos.
Now that's a lot of photos, and we want to give our users a way to narrow down some of them.
So let's go ahead and implement some filtering to do this,
and in this case, we'll filter our photos by their luminosity value.
So let's go ahead and take a look at the code that we've got so far.
It's going to be slightly more advanced than last time.
But if we open up the filtering.pro and look at the main.cpp, we can see that we are again creating
a custom MainWindow, showing it before executing it.
And if we open up the MainWindow, we can start to see some of the implementation.
So scrolling down, we're going to be using a QListView as our central widget and main view for this
example.
We will again have a PhotoModel, which is a simple subclass of QStandardItemModel, and we're going to have
two buttons, one for setting the minimum value for our filter and one for setting the maximum value for
our filter.
If we look at the implementation of our MainWindow, we can see that we create a QToolbar to put both
of our buttons in.
We then create the buttons and add them to our toolbar before adding the toolbar to our main window
using the addToolbar method. Next using the connect function,
we wire up the buttons, specifically the clicked signal, with the set_maximum and set_minimum slots that
are part of this MainWindow class. We're going to take a look at that implementation in a second.
But before we do that, let's look at the rest of the code where we create our main view, the QListView,
our PhotoModel and go ahead and set the model on the view.
We also set up some of the UI before setting the CentralWidget as the list_view.
Now if we run this code, we can see what we're working with. You can see we've got our randomly sorted
photos here, and we've got our toolbar that we just created.
Now if you haven't worked with toolbars before,
the nice thing about them is you can click and drag them around the main window wherever you would like
them. Clicking the buttons pops up a dialog where we can actually set,
in this case, our minimum value. By going and clicking the thing and just dragging it wherever we want
it and click the OK button, we'll see this is actually reflected in the new minimum on the main window.
This happens thanks to the set_maximum and set_minimum slots,
we just talked about.
Let's go ahead and take a look at those implementations now.
So if we're back to our code and we look at the set_minimum and set_maximum,
the slots are basically the same.
We create a dialogue,
in this case VirdisDialogue, and call the static method on it, get_color.
This method opens a new color selector dialog, and returns the minimum color or maximum color at the
end of the method.
If we look at the implementation of the VirdisDialog, it's very simple.
We create two widgets, a ColorPicker and a PushButton, add then to a layout right here and then go ahead
and connect the PushButton's clicked signal with the Dialog's accept slot.
Now the color picker code, that we use to actually select the color, is a little bit more complex and
out of scope for this tutorial. But it basically creates a QImage from the VirdisColorScheme, and
then handles the MouseEvents.
It's a small reimplementation of QColoredDialogue which we'll use later on in this series.
Feel free to poke around the code however you like. But like I said before, the main section of the code
is actually creating this QImage and going ahead and wrangling that. Back to our slot implementation,
once we've gotten the new color, we go ahead and use it to update the button icon before we calculate
the luminosity. The luminosity calculations are in luminosity_calc.h
again which you can take a look as part of this example.
So now that we've looked at all the code, where does this leave a set for our problem?
Well as you might have noticed with the notes I've left, the only thing that we need to do is actually
implement some sort of way to filter the model using the luminosity values from both set_maximum and
luminosity values from set_minimum.
So how do we go about doing that?
Well if you remember back to our last section, the class that we were using was called
QSortFilterProxyModel.
So we're going to be using the same class that we use to implement sorting to do the filtering as well.
Now do you remember how to set QSortFilterProxyModel on the source model?
If you don't it's no worries.
We'll go ahead and do that right now.
So we'll scroll back up to where we create our model, and we'll go ahead and create.
I've got a picture filter which is close enough.
It's our final implementation that we'll be using. But for now go ahead and create a QSortFilterProxyModel.
And then what we want to do on our picture_filter is go ahead and call the setSourceModel function,
and we'll go ahead and pass in our original model, which in this case will be the photo_model.
And once we've done that, we're going to want to go to our view, and instead of passing in our original
photo_model, we want to pass in our proxy model. So we'll go ahead and pass in the picture_filter into
that method call. Awesome.
So we've now implemented the filter proxy at a high level.
Now let's actually implement the low level filtering code.
So if we change back to our picturefilter.h, you can see that I have a basic subclass of
QSortFilterProxyModel that I've created. The method that we need to implement is the filterAcceptsRow method,
which as you can see here, takes in two variables, a source_row and a source_parent which is a
QModelIndex.
The method then returns either a true or false for whether or not this row that gets passed with these
two variables is accepted.
So we need to get our hands on the data.
The best way to do that is to grab the QModelIndex that represents the individual picture that we're
checking, not the parent index, that gets passed into the method.
So how do we do that?
Well if we look at our original model, and more specifically the set item command in the constructor,
what we'll find is the row is set by this for loop which goes from 0 to 100. But the column which is
actually the second is always set to be zero because we don't have multiple columns in our list view.
Now the method that we'll be using to grab the specific index from our Source model out is the index
command.
So if we switch back, the index command takes in three variables, the row, the column, and the parent
QModelIndex.
So in our case, we've already got the row passed in by the function, the parent QModelIndex.
And so the only thing we need that we don't have is the column. But remembering back to our original model,
all pictures are in the zero column.
So we do have everything that we need.
So let's go ahead and grab out our index now.
The first thing that we're going to do is go ahead and create a column variable out of an integer.
We'll set that equal to zero because all of our pictures are in the zero column. And then we want to get
the QModelIndex that represents our picture_index.
So we're going to create that method. And what we need to do is go ahead and get access to our source model,
which there is a method call that does that.
And what we need to call on that is the actual index command.
Now as I just said, the index command takes in three variables, the row which we have access to as the
source row, the column which is the zero column for all of these,
and then the source_parent which gets passed in per the method call as well.
So now that we've got the correct index, do you remember how to grab the data out of it?
Well if you don't, remember you need to use the data method on the index and pass in the specific item
role that you would like from the model.
So in our case, since we want graphic information, it'll be the Qt DecorationRole.
So go ahead and create a QVariant and call it data. And we'll set this equal to our picture index, and
we're going to call the data method on it. And we're going to pass in the decoration roll into this method
call.
Awesome.
So the last thing that we need to do is get the QIcon out from the QVariant, which we can do using
the value method.
So go ahead and create a variable called icon. We'll set this equal to the data, and we can always use
the value method on QVariant to pass in the specific type of data that we need out of it, which in this
case is the QIcon.
Now I've already provided a method to wrangle the color information out of a QIcon, which will call
using the icon_to_luminosity function. So go ahead and create a qreal, and we'll create a lum variable.
And then we'll call the icon_to_luminosity function and pass in our icon.
Now please note that this method is provided by luminosity_calc.h. And you can go ahead and pull
that open and look at the implementation for exactly how that does that
if you like. Cool. So we've successfully converted a source_row and a source_parent QModelIndex
to a luminosity value.
Let's go ahead and see if it meets the constraints on our proxy filter. And we'll do this by checking
the set_min_filter_value and the set_max_filter_value. And we're just going to do a real simple boolean
and compound statement because we need a boolean.
And what we're going to check we're going to see if luminosity is greater than the min_filter_value,
and we need it to be, the luminosity to be less than the max_filter_value.
And we'll just go ahead and return the results of that to see if our filter accepts the row or not.
And that's it.
We've successfully implemented a filter for our model which filters by luminosity.
Now there is only one problem, and that is "how does our proxy model know when the filter values change"?
Well currently they don't.
So let's go ahead and fix that by providing a couple of setter methods. We'll create two, a set_min_filter_value and
a set_max_filter_value.
Now in these method calls, there is a specific method that we need to call to let our proxy model know
that the filter has been change and needs to be recalculated.
This method is called invalidateFilter.
So let's go ahead and create these two methods.
Void set_min_filter_value. It's going to take in a qreal of luminosity. And for the implementation of that,
all you need to do is reset this with whatever that would get passed in. And the last thing that we need
to do is call that function, which is the invalidateFilter function.
We need to implement to these, and we need to implement one for our max as well.
We'll do this by copying and pasting it real quick. And that's it.
So let's switch back to our MainWindow implementation. Now instead of creating this
QSortFilterProxyModel,
We want to use our concrete implementation of that, which is PictureFilter.
Lastly we need to call the methods that we just created, the set of methods that we just created, from
the two slots set_minimum and set_maximum.
So go down here.
Go ahead and delete. And we'll go ahead and on our picture_ilter, we'll call these set_min_filter_value.
And we'll go ahead and pass in our luminosity. And then we'll do the same thing for our set_maximum.
Changing this to the max_filter_value instead.
So let's go ahead and run this and see how it works.
If we click the set minimum value and drag it up to be light instead of super dark and hit OK, we can
see is now our model is actually filtering out all the values that are between the set maximum and set
minimum. So we can go ahead and play with that and include or exclude as many variables as we would like.
Now I took out the sorting code from our last section, but I want to mention that you don't need to do
that.
And I would encourage you right now to go ahead and try to implement and combine both filtering and
sorting in a QSortFilterProxyModel using this picture_filter as a stepping point to kind of do both
of those.
But for now, and with that, we have successfully learned how to filter a model using a
QSortFilterProxyModel.
We also reviewed Qt's model/view and establish a simple use case for filtering.
Please join us in the next video where we continue our dive into the model/view by creating our first
custom model.