This is section 2, Diving into Model View section, which covers sorting. In this  video, we're going to cover
Qt's Model/View paradigm, including both the origins and responsibilities, establishing a need for sorting
with a real life problem before diving into Qt's two methods of sorting, sorting by a proxy model and
programmatically sorting our original model.
So let's go ahead and get started with the model-view-controller or Qt's rebrand of that model view. The
model view controller architecture is a design paradigm used for building user interfaces.
It helps separate the way data is stored
from the way it is presented to the user. You can see it's a typical diagram with the separation of concerns
on the screen.
Qt uses a special construct of the model-view-controller framework called the Model/View. The Model/
vView framework is the same as the model-view-controller framework. You just combine the view with the
ccontroller.
SSo the view in Qt is responsible for both showing the data and responding to user input.
YYou can see a diagram of the model view framework here.
SSo why is this important? Separation of concerns helps promote code reuse.
IIt makes it possible to display the same data in both different views and implement new types of views
wwhile leaving the data untouched.
UUnderstanding them all of view paradigm also helps when designing our gooeys so that we can leverage the
cQt framework instead of fighting against it. With such a mature framework
Tthere's often a prescribed way to do something.
FFor example there are two prescribed ways to do sorting in cute.
SSo what do we want to sort?
WWell let's say that we have an application that shows pictures.
WWe want the pictures to be arranged in the most aesthetically pleasing manner possible, which in this
eexample, we'll be doing by color sorting.
WWe're going to leverage our perceptually uniform color map pictures to help highlight just how effective
tthis can be.
NNow please note that for other non-trivial examples, color sorting is a much more difficult task.
LLet's take a look at the code that we already have at this point.
IIf we open the project by selecting the correct .pro file and configure it using the default desktop configuration,
wwe can take a look.
OOpening the main.cpp, we can see that we create a custom MainWindow and show it before running the exec
eevent loop. Pulling open the header file and the mainwindow,
Wwe can start seeing some of the meat and potatoes of this code.
WWe're going to have 2 views, a QListView and a QTableView.
WWe use each view to demonstrate a different way of sorting
Ain Qt.
II've also got a custom model to help drive our views,
Iin this case the PhotoItemModel.
AAdditionally, we're creating a tab widget, which will allow the user to flip between the two views.
NNow if we pull open our PhotoItemModel, what we'll find is a large for loop that go ahead and creates
oour icons, creates an item, and sets the item with the icon that we just created before finally setting
the item in the model.
TThe only weird bit about this code is that I'm actually creating a second column here using the last
iicon, and then setting it in the column of one.
TThis is to help show exactly how effective sorting is on our QTableView.
SSo let's go ahead and run and see what we're working with right now.
TThe first tab is our QListView and the second is the QTableView.
AAs I mentioned before, there are two prescribed methods of sorting in Qt and you can see I've already
llabeled which method we are going to use on which view.
SSo in the QListView, which is this one, we'll be using a proxy model. In the QTableView, which
iis this one, we'll actually be sorting this programmatically.
NNow you might be surprised, but the proxy method using a QSortFilter proxy model is actually the easier
oof the two methods to implement.
SSo let's go ahead and start with that.
WWe'll need to look at our mainwindow.cpp file. In the constructor of our MainWindow,
Yyou can see that we create an instance of our model, an instance of our QListView before setting
oour model that we created on our list_view.
NNow this is going to be really dumb, but let's go ahead and put a QSortFilterProxyModel in.
SSo you can get a view of how the class is used at high level.
SSo what we'll go ahead and do is in between the creation of our list_view, we'll create an instance and
II've already got a sort proxy model.
WWe'll just go ahead and create a new QSortFilterProxyModel. As part of this, we'll be going to
ggo ahead and set the source model on our proxy model.
SSo we'll go ahead and call that function and pass in our original model, which we've created up here,
iinto our sort proxy filter.
AAnd the last thing that we need to do is instead of passing in our original model, we're going to go
aahead and pass in our sort_proxy_model to our list_view instead. Semi-colons.
SSo high level this is how you use a QSortFilterProxyModel, create an instance, set the source model,
aand then pass the proxy model into our view instead of the original.
BBut this currently won't color sort our pictures like we want because we haven't coded it yet.
SSo let's go ahead and do that now.
NNow I've already created the base framework as part of this example, so we'll just move to that, which
iis labeled the sortproxymodel header file.
SSo in order to enable basic sorting, all we need to do is implement a lessThan function which, as you
can see from the method call, takes in 2 QModelIndexes,
Oone is the left and one is the right, and returns back a boolean.
NNow you might be thinking "then how are we going to go from a QModelIndex to finding a luminosity value
oof a picture"?
II've got to be honest.
GGetting luminosity value of a picture out of the Qt framework is a difficult task.
WWe're not going to go into it too much.
WWhat we're going to talk about instead is how to get data values out of a queue model index, because
oonce you know how to get your hands on the data, you can figure everything else out relatively simply
ddepending on your specific use case.
SSo for the QSortFilterProxyModel, I happen to know that the function is going to return a QVariant.
LLet's go ahead and declare a QVariant and we'll go ahead and call this left_data.
AAnd what we want to do is get a pointer to our sourceModel so that we can call the data function on that.
aAnd the data function takes in two variables, one of which is our QModelIndex which we've got.
SSo we're going pass in the source_left. And the second is the role.
NNow the role is a little special.
WWe should take a second to talk about that.
SSo roles in Qt are used by the view to indicate to the model which type of data it needs.
SSo in this case, we want to get some sort of color or decoration information. So if we take a look at
tthis table, we can see that's most best represented by the DecorationRole. And this table will go
oahead and tell us what types it's going to return.
SSo the data'll be rendered as a decoration in the form of an icon,
QQColor, QIcon or QPixmap.
TThe other important role that you'll often see is the Qt DisplayRole, which I can see from this table,
wwill go ahead and return a QString.
SSo now that we've figured out what role that we need, we'll go ahead and go back to our code and plug that
rrole in.
SSo QtDecoration.
SSo now that we've got the left, the only thing that we need is the right. So we'll do some modifications
Rhere real quick to get our right.
AAnd now that we've got our 2 QVariants, next question we need to answer is how do we wrangle pixel,
ppicture, or color information out of a QVariant?
WWell if we look at the QVariant documentation, what we're going to see is the QVariant contains a lot
oof to functions which helps it convert to specific types of data. So we can see like a toBitArray,
ttoBool, toByteArray.
BBut what we won't find is any type of color information or anything like that.
BBut there is, in the documentation, a note here which says QVariant can't get these things but you can
uuse the value function to actually wrangle out some of this information, which is exactly what we're
ggoing to do.
SSo if we go back to our code, we want to grab our QIcon information, so just go ahead and call the left_icon. And
wwhat we're going to do is on the left data, we're going to call the value function. And we're going to pass in the type we
wwant, which in this case is a QIcon and that is all we need to do.
SSo let's make sure that we do the same thing for the right. Call this on the right data,
Tthe value function, and we'll pass in the QIcon type and that is it. From here
Wwe'll just call a helper function I included, which is luminosity_less_than.
NNow under the hood of this function, it gets a QPixmap from the QIcon, changes the QPixmap
minto a QImage, grabs a pixel from the QImage before finally converting it from the
cRGBColorSpace to the LABColorSpace, which contains the luminosity.
SSo the calculations are all in the luminousty_calc.h.
YYou'll want to see the implementation.
BBut for our case and purposes, all we need to do is return the luminosity_less_than function passing in both
tthe left icon and the right icon.
SSo now we've finished the implementation,
Aall we need to do is actually include it. So if you remember,
Rright now we've got a QSortFilterProxyModel.
SSo let's go ahead and remove that and we'll go ahead and pass in our instance, which is a
mSortProxyModel.
AAnd now if we run this, we're actually not going to see what you're thinking.
SSo instead of having all the information sorted correctly, we're still going to see it unsorted.
SSo there's one more thing that we have to do here.
AAnd that is we need to actually call the sort
Oon model.
SSo we're going to sort_proxy_model and call the sort function and we pass in the first column here. It will
aactually sort the information for us.
AAnd normally what we do is we have a button or something and you click the button and it would sort
sstuff. All it does is an implementation up to the viewer.
TThis is a quick and easy way to demonstrate this functionality.
SSo with that sort function and if we rerun this code, what we can see now is we have all our data sorted,
iin terms of luminosity from darkest to lightest. Cool.
SSo let's get to the second way to do a sort where we sort the data programmatically.
NNow please note that this means that we're going to be changing our original model, where with these
ssort_proxy_model we didn't actually have to do that with the second way of programmatically sorting
ithat we will.
SSo we'll go ahead and change this back to our model. So we can kind of demonstrate the effects of that.
NNow if you look at the model, we're using a QStandardItemModel. And the easiest way to do this is to
go ahead and implement our own custom item type based on QStandardItem and re-implement the lessThan
ooperator.
II'm going to go ahead and paste the framework for this in, and we'll call our custom item type, the photo
iitem.
aAgain this code is going to be very similar to what we've done before.
SSo the first thing that we need to do is go ahead and get our data out in the terms of QVariant. So
wwe'll create a QVariant, and we'll call this the left_data.
WWe're just going to be able to call that data method directly.
TThen we're going to go ahead and pass in our DecorationRole as the role that we want. And we'll do
tthe same thing for our right_data.
AAnd this time we're going to call this on the other, which is described in our actual method Decoration
aand do the same thing.
PPerfect.
OOnce we've got that, we need to grab the QIcon out.
SSo we'll call this the left_icon, and we're going to use the same thing. We'll use the value function and pass
tin the type that we want.
PPerfect. The same thing for the right using the right_data.
AAnd then we've got our helper function, the luminosity_less_than, which will pass in our left_icon and
oour right_icon.
NNow with this one, we'll actually need to change the constructor a little bit and include a semicolon
hhere.
SSo with this one we'll actually need to change the constructor a little bit.
SSo instead of calling or creating a QStandardItem right here, instead we're going to like change
tthis for our PhotoItem.
AAnd again for the second item as well.
BBoth the types and the instances. The last thing that we need to do is if we switch back to our
wMainWWindow, we need to make sure that we've actually enabled sorting. So if we go here, I've actually commented
iit out, it's in the setup_table_view_ui.
TThere's a method that says setSortingEnabled.
SSo I want to make sure that that is set to true.
NNow if we run this, we can see that by clicking the columns, we can actually change how our data is sorted.
aAnd you can see the effect this has on the second column.
NNow what I want you to also notice is that this changes our other view that we have.
RRight?
SSo our other view is now sorted by luminosity as well. And we can a second column to kind of see what
iit looks like without the luminosity sorted.
SSo as we make changes here in our table view, we're actually making changes in our secondary view, which
iis the downside of programmatically sorting our model instead of using a QProxyModel.
SSo with that we've successfully learned how to programmatically sort. We've learned how to use a proxy model.
WWe've touched on Qt's model/view paradigm, and why it's important as well as establishing a real use case
ffor some advance sorting.
PPlease join us for the next video where we continue our dive into the
Amodel/view paradigm by discussing filtering.