This is video which covers building a supercomputing application. In this video we're going to cover a simple
supercomputing architecture, network coding in Qt, and a full implementation of a supercomputing application.
Let's talk briefly about the architecture of our supercomputing application.
We want to create a couple of simple interfaces to help us scale our workload by parallelizing it. To
do this, we're going to create two TCP servers and a bunch of workers that sit between them as seen
in the diagram. One server is going to be the push server which is going to distribute the workload out
to our workers.
The other server is going to be the pull server which is going to get the results of our computations. Now
in between these servers will be the workers.
Workers will connect to the pull server, grab work, run some calculations, and then dumped the results
into the pull server.
This setup is nice because it's simple, and we can always add workers to get our work finished faster.
Just make sure that the calculations take longer than the delays associated with the networking.
Now our example code is actually going to simplify the architecture a little bit, so that we don't have
to start four different processes at once.
We'll do this by combining the push and pull servers in a single process and simulating the workers
with a single process that leverages the event loop and QTimers to simulate multiple workers.
Once we've implemented the example, we'll review a full of architecture that I'd recommend for this type
of application.
So let's start implementing. You're going to have to open up both the server project file and the client project
file.
And if you go in the server file to the push server and scroll all the way down, you can see that we've got two
member variables, a QTcpServer and a QStringList.
So we're going to use our QTcpServer to go ahead and push out our operations one string at a time.
And in this example we're going actually to do 101 operations.
So if we move over to the implementation of this file and look at the constructor of this class, you'll
see that we actually have our server, listen, on the LocalHost, port 5000.
And then we go ahead and initialize our operations, using the number_operations which basically just
adding in a string to every number.
And then lastly and most importantly, we take our QTcpServer, specifically the signal newConnection,
and connect it to our send_work slot.
So if we scroll down into our send_work slot, we can see how we're going to implement this.
The first thing that we need to do is go ahead and grab the socket out.
And the way we'll do that is using the nextPendingConnection method on our server.
Awesome.
Now we want to actually check to make sure that we've still got work to do. And the way we're going to
do that is calling the isEmpty method on our operations.
Now if the operations are empty, then let's go ahead and we'll emit the finished signal and return from
this method.
If the operations are not empty, that means we've still got work to do.
So let's go ahead and grab our first operation out. When we grab the socket out, we want to make sure
that it doesn't that it gets cleaned up in a timely manner.
So what we're going to go ahead and do is connect the disconnected signal to the deleteLater slot,
all on the QTcpSocket.
So one thing I forgot to do is we need to actually make sure that this QTcpSocket that we pulled
up gets cleaned out. And the way that we're going to do that is make sure that we call the disconnected
signal to the deleteLater slot on the actual QTcpSocket.
Next thing you need to remember is data over the network is actually pretty expensive.
So we want to make sure that's compressed as possible.
Luckily Qt provides a helper method to do that in
QDataStreams.
Let's go ahead and use that. So the QDataStream input operation,
the QDataStream input operator, which you can see right here on this line, is actually going to
compress our operation data, which is this QString, into our block
QByteArray, which is called block here, that we pass into the constructor for our QDataStream.
Now the QByteArray block is what we actually want to send over the wire.
So let's go ahead and send it using the write function.
We'll then disconnect our QTcpSocket using that disconnectFromHost method.
So now we've gone ahead and grabbed our client_connection.
We've made sure that it'll go ahead and get cleaned up.
We grabbed our first operation and we've compressed it and gone ahead and written that compressed
QByteArray over the wire so that we send it to one of our workers.
So what is the worker going to do with it?
Well let's go ahead and take a look.
So we'll have to get into our client project and what we're going to head to is our socket_manager implementation
file.
Now the constructor for this class is very simple.
We just called the setup_sockets method.
Now for our workers,
each worker needs two sockets, one for connecting to the push server and one for connecting to the pull
server. Socket pair, which you can see here, creates two sockets just for this purpose, an input and an
output.
We'll go ahead and connect the output right away to the pull server.
So in this case, it'll be the LocalHost on port 5001.
Now since we compressed the data before we sent it, we'll have to decompress it here.
So we go ahead and create a QDataStream and associate it with the input socket pair, or the input
QTcpSocket using the setDevice method on our QDataStream.
Now the signal that our QTcpSocket is going to admit that we're most interested in is the
readyRead signal, which lets us know that we have data to read.
We'll use a functor-based slot to streamline the code a little.
Now since the signal is just readyRead and not something like "Hey all the data is here now and you
can start working on it"
we have to implement a check to make sure that all the data has arrived.
We do this using two methods on the data_stream object, startTransaction and commitTransaction. We'll
call start transaction first.
So in this code, if commitTransaction here returns false, that means that we still have data left to
receive.
Now the commit transaction method is smart enough to roll the internal state of data_stream back to
where we called Start transaction.
If this doesn't make sense, I wouldn't worry about it.
This is basically all implementation details of QDataStream.
The important thing to understand is that this work right here is actually decompressing the data.
So especially right here where we create our QString instance called work, and go ahead and use the
output operators,
that's going to go ahead and put all the data over the wire into this variable called work.
So if we make it pas this method call right here, and the data_stream
commitTransaction returns true,
that means our QString variable called work will actually have the decompressed data that we sent
over the push server.
So let's go ahead and call a method to simulate the work.
Now if we look at our function doing the work, you're going to see that we're not actually going to do
work at all.
So you can see this note here "in real code, work calculations would happen before we compress the data
again".
But since we're just going to simulate doing work, we're going to be compressing the data away, because
we're just going to simulate work where we're just going to go ahead and compress the data again.
Now it might seem silly to decompress the data just to compress again, but remember, missing packets is
expensive.
Now if we look at the function doing the work, you're going to see that we're not actually going to
do anything.
So in this note here "in real code, work calculations would happen before we compress the data back again".
Since we're just simulating this,
we're going to just go ahead and compress the data back again.
And the code is very similar. So we create a QByteArray,
we create a QDataStream and pass our QByteArray in, and then go ahead and using the input operator.
So our QString's actually our work variable.
We're going to write that into our data_stream, which means that this block is ready for us to send over
the wire.
So let's go ahead and do that. And we want to make sure that our output socket is actually connected,
so we're going to check that first.
But if that is actually successful, then we'll go ahead and send our work back, using the write method.
Now we need to simulate some calculation time here.
Otherwise we're just looking to see how fast the LocalHost loopback is. And the way that we're going
to do this is using the random method, bounded.
So we'll get a number between 0 and 500, and we'll go ahead and plug our simulated_work_time into a
QTimer. And this QTimer is hooked up to another functor. And it's actually going to call the get_more_work
method, which actually goes ahead and reconnects our input socket back up to our push socket to
go ahead and get more work.
So the last thing to do, now that we've sent our work, which we did right here.
So we've sent our work from our workers back to our pull server,
so let's go ahead and take a look at our pull server.
And if you look at the constructor of our pull server, you'll see that we go ahead and listen on the
LocalHost port 5001.
And then just like we did for our push server, we connect our server, which is the QTcpServer, specifically
the newConnection method, to our receive_work slot. So our receive_work slot looks identical to our
send_work slot.
Right?
We use the nextPendingConnection on our server to go ahead and get a client_connection out.
We create a QDataStream. And we go ahead and associate our client connection with our data_stream.
And then we want to make sure that we get all the works,
we'll use the startTransaction and commitTransaction to make sure that we get all the information.
But in the end of the day, all the data is going into our variable
QString, which we called result here. And we actually use the output operator in this line here to pass
our QDataStream information into our result.
And then what we're going to do is we're going to check to make sure that we actually get some informations, we check
to see if the result. which is the QString, is empty.
And then we go ahead and print it out into the terminal.
So let's go ahead and run these two projects. We'll start the server first, and then the clients.
So go ahead and change the server and then go ahead and run the client.
Looks like it took us 4.9 to 8 seconds to run.
Now note that we could go into our clients and actually change the number of workers here, and go ahead
and simulate the fact that we have more run workers and run that again.
And that is exactly what we do in real life.
If we needed to get something faster just increase the number of workers.
So it's a very simple process to do this.
Now this is nice in theory but if I were implementing this in practice this is what I would actually
do.
So the first thing I would want is to remove the event loop out of our worker.
Workers would be very simple,
much like the pseudo code displayed here.
The worker would basically run an infinite loop.
It would get the work from the push server, run the calculations, and then send the result back to the
pull server.
And the reason workers would be so simple is because we would leverage the process manager, much like
we created in the last video.
And basically I would create as many workers as I had cores on my server. By making these workers so
simple,
we go ahead and let the operating system manage task switching rather than manually programming the
task switching ourselves, however we want to do that.
Operating systems by design are pretty awesome at switching tasks.
So it only makes sense to leverage that strength rather than try to manually program it ourselves.
And with that we've effectively covered a full implementation of a supercomputing app, worked on network
coding in Qt, and walked through a simple architecture of a supercomputing application.
Join us next time where we go over an introduction to the diving into model/views.