I'd like to give you a few guidelines
that are going to help you write qml
code that is readable. On this
documentation length you're going to
find some qml coding conventions and
they say that they are giving the coding
conventions they follow in the
documentation, and they do recommend us
to follow that. because the code is going
to be much more readable by others. Okay
so in your qml file, you're going to
start by the ID. You learn to follow that
with the property declarations. And down
here they have an example, so you see an
ID. Here we have a qml component. It has
an ID that is shown here.
You follow that with the properties. If
you have any properties, you have to put
them here.
You follow that will signal declarations.
After that you're going to put in your
JavaScript functions, any JavaScript
function that is embedded in your
qml file should come here. And then
you have the properties for the object.
Okay, things like X line width and height
should come here. If you have a lot of
JavaScript that you want to assign to a
property, you should wrap that in a block
like this, and then after all this, you're
going to put your child objects. You see
this rectangle here is a child rectangle
of the parent rectangle here . Down below
you put your states. This is basically
what we did when we looked at states and
transitions. And you end with the
transitions that your element might have.
This is the recommended way: you start
with IDs, property declarations, signal
declarations, JavaScript functions,
object properties, child objects, states
and transitions. This is really how your
qml code should be organized. Down below
to show you how you should use your
group properties. You really shouldn't do
something like this, anchors left, anchors
top, anchors bottom and things
like that. You should group them like
this and say anchors and specify the
properties inside the brackets here. We
looked at this syntax before.
This is the recommended way to make you
qml more readable. If a list only
contains one element you can omit this
square bracket, something like this. Okay.
Instead of doing something like this you
see we have states, we have one state, and
we put that inside these brackets. You
can do something like this, and put your
state inside directly, if it happens to be
only one state. Down here they talk about
things you should be careful about when
writing some JavaScript in your QML code.
If the script is a single expression
they recommend writing that in line,
something like this. You see here, there
is a binding to the width property of
this rectangle here. If the script is a
couple of lines, wrap that in a block. And
if it is much longer you need to wrap
that in a function and call that when
you want to assign something to a QML
property like this. And if javascript is
really too long, you need to put that in
an external Javascript file and import
that in your QML file and we look at
this before. Okay these are the
guidelines to help you write Qml code,
that other people are going to be able
to read very easily, and that adds value
to the code that you write. If you write
code that only you can read or that
other people really find difficult to
read, it is not a good thing for your
piece of code. Okay so keep this in mind.
This being the last lecture of the
course, there are two things I would like
to recommend. If you want to push your
QT Quick knowledge further. One is
ready to consult the documentation and
QT itself the documentation includes. It's
very good and you saw that in the course.
Every time we needed something, we just
looked at the documentation and we had
turned to tons of information just by
looking at the documentation in QT
create tour or or online. So every time you
need to learn about something, going to
documentation
and see what you can find in there. This
is the documentation for Qt Quick itself.
You see here they talk about some of the
things we even talked about in the
course, user input, positioning, states, and
transitions, data models, views and data
storage. We have looked at these things,
but if you want to read about the
canvas, you can read about this.
They have particles and graphical effects.
If you want to do some advanced
animations you can look at this. If you
want to extend your qml with C++, these
are good things to look at. One is
QT, the other is the book that we
had a chance to look at in the course.
And this is a very good book and
knowledge is presented in a very good
structure. And in fact if you have
finished this course, you really have
good grounds to start looking at some of
these things.
This book has one downside is that it
tries and combines C++ and QT quick in
one go. If you don't have a C++
background, you're not going to find this
very understandable. But if you want to
get started with the C++ side of QT,
happen to have a course on that. So if
you are interested be sure to check it
out. And this is really all I have to
offer in terms of tips and tricks on how
to push your knowledge in QT quick
further. Consult the Qt Quick
documentation, look at this book and try
to look if you can learn something from
this balance. Okay this brings us to the
end of this course. I'd like to thank you
for enrolling. If you like the course
please consider leaving your honest
review. It helps a lot. And on top of all
I'm wishing you well on your journey as
the QTquick user interface developer.
Till next time. Bye