In this lecture, we're going to see how we
can work with custom settings in qml. We
have looked at the documentation for
settings, and we just saw a way to let
the system save everything for you
without you doing much more, but when you
do things this way you pay a performance
cost of saving the data whenever any of
this property changes, and sometimes you
don't want this. A solution for that is
to save the data yourself, and they give
an example of how you can do that. You
basically have a settings component, it
has an ID and it has a set of properties
that you want to save. In this case we
want to save this state. And you see that
this item here is reading state
information from our Settings component
here. This is one thing you need to do,
you need to read whatever property you
want to save from these Settings
component, and you have to choose a time
when you want to save your data. In this
case, we are saving the data when this
component is destroyed. We are saying
settings.state = page.state. We are taking
this state from this component and
saving it in the Settings component here
when this component dies. And notice that
as you use your application, you may get
a chance to change the states, and this
changes are going to be saved in here.
Notice that you pass the default value
here, so if you don't have the state set,
it is going to be "active" by default. To
play with this, we are going to go to
Qt creator, find a project we have done
before, so I'm going to go into recent
projects, and I'm going to find the
project we did, that project is
StatesWithGradiant. I want you to go and find
it, and open it in Qt creator like
this. If we run it, you see that it had a
scene like this, and we were able to
change between summer and spring, okay, by
changing states like this. So what we
want is to save the state
that we are in, and when we close the
application, we want to save the state,
and when we run it, we want to pick up
the state we saved last time. To be able
to play with this, we're going to create a
new project and copy over all the files
so that things are nice and clean, I
don't like to do things over other
projects, because it confuses students. So
what we're going to do is create a new
project. I want to do all this live so
that you see everything. Qt Quick application.
We're going to call it SettingsDemo2
because this is the second one. Save it
in the usual location, hit next, choose
your QT version, choose your kit, and
finish. We want to change this to "Custom
settings", because you are saving things
yourself. We want to go to the states
with gradient demo project, go in
QML, and find our QML file. We don't have
any special import, but we want to copy
everything in here. So we're going to
grab everything in the window here, as
you see, except for the properties of the
window, because we have our own
properties in this new project of ours
here. We're going to paste the data in
here, and if you look, you see that we
have images in here, so we need to also
import those images. What I want to do, I
want to go where this project is saved,
and go Show in Explorer... I have a folder
of images here, I want to copy it, go
where my project is saved here, right
click, Show in Explorer, and I am going to
paste in this folder of images. Now I
have it in SettingsDemo2. I can
close this, add a new resource file, add a
new, choose Qt, resource file,
it's going to be resources, next, next,
until the finish, add the prefix, take
this out, hit enter, because we don't want
to have a prefix, add files, images, and
we put in our spring and summer images.
We save this. And if we run this project
of ours, SettingsDemo2, we should
have everything we had in this
StatesWithGradientsDemo project. Let's wait
and see, and we can change between states.
We can close this application and close
these StatesWithGradientsDemo project
because we don't need it anymore,
close everything in here because we
don't want things confusing us, and open
our QML file because this is where we
want to work. First thing we want to do
is to import the settings, because that's
what we are going to be using in this
lecture, and we want to go back to the
documentation and adapt this example to
save our state. Notice that they have a
settings block here, we can copy it,
come back to our project, we want to go
at the end of the rectangle component,
this rectangle here, and it is ending
here, and we want to put in the settings
that we copied from the documentation.
The id is settings... we can keep that,
there's no problem... Ctrl+A Ctrl+I to align...
Down here you see that we are saving the property
of State. We want to make this state
spring by default, and we want to make
the application read the state data from
our settings component, so we should take
this out, and say state : settings.state.
This is the second thing you have
to do. The first one is put in your
settings component like this, give it an
ID, make your application read whatever
that are you saved from the settings. And
the last thing you need to do to make
this work is to provide a component
on destroyed.. onDestruction, that's what
we want, okay. We choose to do it here, but
you can really save it whenever you want.
You can even do this when a user presses
some button or whatever. We are doing it
right now
when this rectangle is destroyed. And in
here we should say settings.state
equals whatever state is saved in the
rectangle here. And notice that this
state is part of the rectangle component
that contains everything, okay. This is
where this state is defined, so we should
save it by saying RectId, I think
that's our ID here for this rectangle...
containerRectId... that's what we have, so
we should say containerRectId.state
like this. And before we run the
application, we need to remember to go
back to the main cpp file, and put in our
application information ctrl A ctrl I to
align, and I want to change this because
it might conflict with the settings we
did in the last lecture. You don't want
to have two applications with the same
set of information, you're just going to
mess up things.
Let's run. If everything works, we should
be able to save our state, whether spring
or summer. So we are in spring right now.
We can change to be in summer, close the
application, run it, we start in summer, we
change to spring, close the application,
run it,
you see that we are in spring. Let's
change to summer again we should see
summer when we run, ok, summer. Let's
change to spring,
close the application, we should see
spring when we run, and it is spring here.
Now you know how to save your data
customally when you close the application,
or whenever you want to save the data. We
are saving when the rectangle component
is destroyed, but you can really save it
anywhere. The bulk of this is defining
the settings component, make your
application read its properties from the
Settings component, and choose a time
when you want to save the data, in this
case we saved the data when the
rectangle component is destroyed. And
ladies and gentlemen, this is how you
work with settings to save your data, you
can completely let the settings
component handle the data for you, pay
the price in performance of saving the
data whenever a property changes, or you
can choose when you want to save the
data yourself and do it like we did in
this lecture here.
In the next lecture, we're going to see
how you can save your data using SQLite,
an internal database that is built in
your system. I'll see you in the next lecture.