In this lecture, we're going to see how
you work with the rest api in your
qml applications. We are going to work
with the api service that is provided by
this website here. It is called ICNDb.com,
and it gives a funny api that
fetches Chuck Norris jokes. So you want
to come to database restful api and
click on this link here, and they show
you the documentation on their api. If
you go down, they give you a list of
links you can use to get the api. We
want to use this one. You want to copy it
and open it in a new tab. We're going to
open it like this.
And if I call it like this, it is going
to give me three jokess. You see that I am
opening this in a browser. I am using
Firefox right now, you can use whatever
you want, but Firefox by default gives me
this good display that helps me see my
data very well. I'm going to increase the
size so that you see what we get. Okay, we
get a JSON object, really, and inside we
have a type attribute, which is whether
we were successful or not, and inside we
have a value array, and it contains JSON
objects as well. On the zero index we
have this object. Inside we have an id,
the joke, attribute here, and the categories
array, but this array is empty for now.
Let's try to parse in 10 to see if this
changes anything... Nothing, which means the
categories array is empty, but we are
interested in the joke here. So what
we're going to do we're going to get
this data, parse it in our QML code
and fetch the data that we have in here,
and we're going to display this in
ListView. And when we get the data from
the internet we're going to find a way
to put that in our model so that it is
displayed by the View. We're going to go
to Qt creator and do that. Here we are
in QT creator. We're going to
create our project: so QT quick
application,
we call it RESTApisDemo, store it in
the usual location, hit next, choose your
QT version, choose your kit, and finish. We
want to change the title here to... say...
Rest APIs Demo, and we want to import QT
QtQuick.Controls, bởi vì ta sẽ
need the button and the SpinBox. We also
want QtQuick.Layouts, We're going to
use 1.4. Down here we want to put in
a column layout, it is going to fill the
the parent. We want a spacing of zero. Inside
we're going to have a ListView,
this SpinBox component that is going to
allow us to specify the number of jokes
that we want, and the button that is
going to kick off the download of the
api. The ListView is going to have
an id: mListViewId as usual. SpinBox
is going to be spinBoxId, and button
is going to be buttonId. I don't know if
you're going to need the ID for the
button, but we put it in anyway. We also
want a list model for the list of views, so
we're going to say listModel, id: mListModel
and it's going to be just like
this: we are going to put in the data
dynamically as we get the data from the
REST API. so we can specify a model for
our list view here mListModelId, I like
to put Id at the end so we know it's an
Id. This list view is going to need to
delegate... we're going to go down below
everything and define a component that
is going to be our delegate. I don't want
to type all this, so I prepared it before,
and I'm going to put
and try to explain it. If you have
watched the chapter on model view
architecture, this is not going to be new
to you. So it is a delegate, we have the
Id, inside we have a rectangle with a
bunch of properties width height color, and
inside we have a text component that is
going to display jokes in our case here,
and we applied some decoration on text
component to make it look better. We set
the font size. We centered it in the
parent, and you see that we applied some
margin on the rectangle to make the text
have some breathing room. We also want to
align the text in the rectangle, and we
are wrapping to not have our text
chopped off. This is really all we have.
We can go back to our list view and
specify a delegate. It's going to be
delegateId, yes, it is, okay. Now
that we have our delegate, we want to
make the ListView fill the available
space. We're going to say
Layout.fillWidth... set this to true... Layout.fillHeight...
and set this to true. Let's take one
colon away. And we want the others to fill
the available width, okay, so we say
SpinBox and Button fill the width. For these
Spinbox, we want to specify the value
that is going to be in by default. We
want to have a 10 inside... Ctrl+A,
Ctr+I to align the things... and for the
button we want to have the text that is
going to be shown.... let's say "Fetch", and
when it is clicked we want to know, and
this is where we are going to kick off
the download of our data. So we want to
put in the function that is going to
fetch the jokes. We go to the top here and
say function fetchJokes.
It's going to take a URL
just like we did in the last lecture,
really. We're going to just download HTTP
data, we just happen to get JSON data
from this request. Inside we're going to
parse in a call back... same thing, really, as
the last lecture. So inside, we are going
to do the same thing we did in the last
lecture: you see we are creating our
XMLHttpRequest object, we are calling open
and send here, and when the ready state
changes we get that here, if we are done
we check to see if the status is okay
and we console.log the "resource found"... We
don't want to say in textID, we don't
have that here. Let's take this out, and
we call back a method with the response
text that we got from the internet, okay.
This is really the same thing. This part
is completely the same as the last
lecture, we just changed the name of the
function here to reflect what we are
doing here. So when you click the button,
we want to call the fetchJokes method.
Let's do that. Okay we want to parse in
the URL. Let's go back to our REST API
service here, copy the URL that we are
parsing in here. We are going to put the
same URL inside here, but this number is
going to be dynamic. It's not going to be
static like this. So we're going to put a
quote here, and add that number
dynamically. So we're going to say
+ spinBoxId.value... you get the value that
is in the spinBox. We can change this
at runtime by clicking the plus or minus
button, but when we click the button here
we're going to get whatever value is in
the spinBox. I hope this makes sense. And
after this, we want to parse in our
callback function. function(response)... we
want to parse in the parameter list and
provide the body for our function
here. Ah, we don't want this parameter list,
we put that in the response. Sorry for
that. We're going to shrink this so that
we have more area to see what is going
on okay. Now we have a response here, so
what we're going to do is console again
to see what we are getting, actually, and
know that our logic here is working. We're
going to console.log(response), like this.
Let's run the application and see that
our logic is working. We have our user
interface here, there is nothing in here
because the model is empty.
If we hit fetch, notice what we get. okay
we say type success value id joke Chuck
Norris, and things like that,
okay. We have our data. We want to parse
it, actually, and put the data in our
model. We want to check if we got a
correct response, so we say if(response),
we do parse the data, and if we have no
response, let's say console.log("something
went wrong"), this will do. Now what we want
to do is turn the data into a json
object that we can parse. We say var
object = JSON.parse, and we parse in
the string that we want to parse, so we
say response, this is what we want. Now
what we want to do is loop,
okay, we want to loop over this to
capture our jokes. I want to go back to
our browser and look at the structure of
the response we get, because we obviously
want to know that. Notice that our object
is going to contain the attribute of
type, and an array of value, okay. We want
to actually loop over this array and
capture these objects. So if you don't
know how to loop over an array, you can
actually open your favorite search
engine and type in... I think it's going to
give us the documentation for JavaScript,
you come here, and what you want to look
at is Built-in objects, look at array, and
there are methods that we can call on
this array. One of those methods is foreach,
and you can use this to loop over
an array. You can look at this to see how
you can loop over your array. This is
what we are going to use. So we are going
to go to our code and say object.values,
because if you go back to our response
we got, we have a "value" array... it's not
"values", its "value", so you need to check
your thing, and say forEach(). Inside we
parse in a callback function, just like
what we did with our requests, it is
going to parse a parameter of joke, and
what we have in here is going to be our
joke object. We want to go in the body of
the function and do something with the
joke data that we have. We actually want
to capture this data and put that in the
Model. Okay, we want to get the joke out
of the joke object. What we are going to
take here is going to be one of these
elements... you see we have many elements,
we're going to
take one element and this is going to be
one joke, and we want to capture the joke
out of that. I hope this makes sense. So
what we're going to do is we're going to
capture the ID of our model, it's called
model Id, let's say mListModelId.append(),
we want to append data and we
want to append this as a JSON object. So
we're going to say "joke", okay. We want to
put the colon on here and say joke.joke.
Joke is our object that we parse in here
and we want to take the joke out of it.
Notice that we did everything we have to
do but we did it in the wrong place. So
we should copy this and put that when we
get the data. Sorry for that, guys. Now we
can run the application and see that we
are getting the data and showing that in
our model. Let's run. Okay, we have our
application here. Let's change to make it
fetch five jokes. Fetch, and you see that we
have our jokes here. Let's fetch again
you see that our list keeps growing. You
can increase the count, fetch again, and
you see that we are fetching the jokes
and showing them in our application here.
The bulk of this application is really
how you parse the data that you get.
Getting the data is part of the last
lecture that we focused on
getting HTML data from the internet. Now
we want to parse the data as a JSON
object and get whatever parts of that
json object that we want. In this case
we want to get joke data and put that in
our model using the append method
dynamically. This is all I had to say in
this lecture. I hope you know how to work
with XMLHttpRequests to both download
HTTP data and parse that data as a json
object as necessary. In the next
chapter we're going to see how you work
with storage mechanisms that are
provided to you by QT quick I see you there