In this lecture, we're going to see what
is available to you in terms of networking
in QT Quick.
First off, I want to mention that in your
Qt development, the resource heavy
operations should be done on the C++
side. We have mentioned before that there
are two major sides to working with Qt:
you can develop your application in C++
purely, or you can do your user interface
in QT Quick, which is what the company
behind Qt is pushing for now. They are
pushing to do user interfaces in Qt Quick,
and do resource heavy operations in C++
because that's much more scalable. Right
here you can see C++ classes that give
you magic powers in terms of networking.
You can do very low level things in
networking using TCP and UDP classes. You
can really do anything. You can do DNS
using the QHostInfo and
QDNSLookup classes. You can do SSL/TLS.
You can use these two classes. And
they provide high level classes to work
with HTTP. You can use
QNetworkAccessManager and QNetworkReply.
We have looked at this in one of my
previous courses on Q. So if you are
working on the C++ side of Qt, these
classes are going to come in handy but
we are not talking about those in this
course, because this course is purely
about QM.Oon the Qt Quick side,
there really isn't much you can do in
terms of networking. There are a few
things they allow you to do through
JavaScript. Here I have listed two use
cases I find important. One is being able
to load QML components remotely. In
this case, you serve your QML files
through the internet, and your
application is really like a web
application, you are serving your user
interface through the internet and it is
really like loading a web page, but you
are loading QML. This is what they
are trying to emulate. I just want you to
know in this use case we are not going to
go into too much detail about it, because
personally I haven't used it that much,
and you can consult the documentation if
you need more information about this.
What we are going to look at in this
chapter is XmlHTTPRequest, which is a
JavaScript object that you can use in
QML. And you can use it to fetch
HTTP data. Now we want to look at what
you can do with XmlHTTPRequest. We are
going to come to the documentation, the
JavaScript documentation available at
developer.mozilla.org. They have much
more details about JavaScript. And this
is the place to go if you need to read
more on things using JavaScript in your
QML. We have mentioned this in
the JavaScript section of this course. So
you use XmlHTTPRequest objects to
interact with servers. You can retrieve
data from a URL without having to do a
full page refresh. They talked about these
things. Despite its name XmlHTTPRequest
can be used to retrieve any page of data,
not just XML. down here they show you the
constructor. we are going to use this to
create our object. And if you look at
properties, there are a few things we are
going to use in a moment. One is
onreadystatechange. We are going to use this
event handler to know if we had the data
or if we got some kind of error while
fetching our data from the internet. Okay,
down here you see the readyState values.
You can click on this to see the
possible values it can be: unsent
opened, headers_received, loading, or done,
which is when the operation is complete.
Another thing you might be interested in
is the responseText, which is the
response from the server that you get:
returns the text received from a server
following a request being sent. Another
thing I want you to look at is the
status: returns an unsigned short with
the status of the response of the
request. There are standard HTTP status
codes that are going to be returned in
here. I think they even have a link on
that. The status codes returned are the
standard HTTP status codes.
If you click on this, open this in
another tab, you're going to see those. You
have 200 when everything is okay. You got
what you wanted. You have 404 when the
page is not found and things like that.
Let's look at 404 page not found. You can
look at all these statuses. They are
available to you. Okay, now that we have a
little bit understanding about the
XmlHTTPRequest object and what it does,
let's look at how we're going to use it.
First we are going to use it to fetch
some HTTP data. We are going to download
the web page, and we are going to write a
function like this to download the data.
It's going to take a URL that we want to
fetch. We're going to create a new
XmlHTTPRequest object. You create it like
this. We just looked at the constructor
in the documentation, and we listen in on
this handler onreadystatechange, okay.
We put in a function that is going to
help us capture the data. And if
readystate is headers_received, we just say
that we receive the headers. The
most important thing we want is to know
when the request is done, and we capture
that when the ready state is
XmlHTTPRequest.done. After that we capture the
data that is stored in response text and
we turn that into a string. After you
get the text, you can really do anything
with it.
In this case we are just stuffinG this
text in a text area UI component, the
text property of it. And if this status
is not 200, meaning that we didn't get
what we wanted, we say that something
went wrong. After we define our XmlHTTPRequest,
we open it by parsing in the URL
that we got from the caller of this
function, and then we send our request.
This is really how you use this object
of XmlHTTPRequest. And when you have
this, you call your method like this by
parsing again a URL. We're going to do a
demo about this. Don't worry if this is
not clear yet. It is going to be clear
and you're going to see it work in
action. One thing I want to mention is
that what
did here is synchronous, meaning that it
can block your user interface if this
download here happens to take longer.
Imagine if it takes something like 5
seconds or 10 seconds to get the data if
your network is slow, that can happen, it
is going to block your user interface
and users are not going to be able to
interact with your application. So this
should be used on really fast operations
that don't take that long. I even
recommend not using this unless you
really have a good reason to do so,
because you can do this call
asynchronously. to call it synchronously
you pass a callback method that is going
to be called when the operation is done.
And when this method is called, you can
do your normal things like grabbing the
text and using it in your user interface.
So the difference with the asynchronous
call is that when you get the data, ok,
you see that it looks mostly like what
we had before, but after we have the data,
we call the callback method with
whatever data we got from the server. You
see we are calling callback and we are
passing in the response text and we call
toString on that to turn that into a
string that we can work with in QML.
If we don't get the response, we
call the callback method with null to
mean that we had an error, and then we
kick off the download the same way we
did with the synchronous call. It really is
the same thing. The difference is that when
you get the data, you call the callback
method. Now how do you call this method
in your application? The downloadData
method. This is how you do it.
You call download data, and you pass in
the URL, and you pass in an inline
function that is going to act as your
callback. So when we get the data, this
function here is going to be called. You
see that it takes a parameter which is
the response here. We check to see if the
response is not null, and then we work
with the data that we got from the
server. In this case we are taking the
data, and also stuffing it in a textarea
UI component. If the response is null we say
that there was some kind of error. This
is really how you work with that.
The first thing we're going to do is to
download HTTP data. The second thing is
going to be to fetch restful api and
work with the json data that we get in
our Qt application. Again, this is going
to work on the foundation that we built
when we downloaded HTTP data using
XmlHTTPRequest. The function to fetch data
is going to look like this. You see that
we are passing in the URL. This is the
URL. And we are passing in a callback
method. We get the response. This response
is going to be JSON data. So we want to
parse the JSON data into an object. This
is what we do here. After we get the
object, we loop over it capturing the
data that we want. This is also going to
be some kind of object. We are basically
capturing the data that we want, and
stuffing the data in a list model like
this. The thing I want you to notice is
that we are passing the image as an
object here, and this thing that is in
quotes is going to be our  and we
are going to use this in our delegate to
capture the data that we show in a
ListView, which is what we're doing next
really. This is our delegate
components. It's nothing special. We've
done most of these things before. We have
a rectangle inside, with a bunch of
properties inside, we have a text
component that is going to display our
data. But the text property can use a
of joke, which is what we had before
here when we appended the data in the
model. This is what I want you to see. You
can use joke here, or you can even use
modelData that we have used before when
we have a direct model. You can look at
the Model View architecture chapter if you
haven't looked at that yet, this is going
to make sense. Ok. This is what we're
going to cover in this chapter. The next
lecture we're going to start by
downloading some data from the internet
using XmlHTTPRequest. I'll see you there