In this chapter we're going to look at
different ways you can store your data
in your QT quick application. We are
going to look at two ways: settings and
SQL mainly, but I want to bring it to our
attention that you can do all kinds of
crazy things from the C++ side and send
the data to Qt quick or QML using the
available channels of communication
between c++ and QML. We are not going to
talk about how you communicate between
C++ & QML because that's not the
subject of this course, but I am planning
to do a course about that so stay tuned
if you need to know more about this
subject. So a takeaway is that we are
going to look at settings and SQL. There
is a QML type that is called settings
that you used to save your data. We're
going to look at that. But the first
thing you have to do when using it: you
have to set the information for your
application, and you usually do that in
your main.cpp file, and you do it
like this: you have a
QGuiApplication class that you instantiate,
and inside you put your organization
name, organization domain, and application
name. So for different applications, this
information should be different. This is
the first thing you want to do when you
are working with settings. Don't forget
this. After that you have to import
Qt.labs.settings. So to use this thing, you
define a Settings component in your qml
file like this, and then you parse in the
data that you want to save using
property alias like this, ok. In this
case we are saving location data for a
window, we want to save the x coordinate,
the y coordinate, the width and height
information, and we save that like this.
And when you do this you don't need to
do anything else, your data is
automatically saved and loaded. And all
this might not make sense yet, but we are
going to do a full demo about this, and
you are going to see this in action. You
can also split your settings in
categories like this: you see we have a
category to save window data, and we have
a category to save color data like this.
You can split your settings into
categories. This is how you do it if you
want to save your settings automatically.
There is another way if you don't want
to save the data automatically. Saving
the data automatically imposes a cost on
you of saving the data whenever
something changes, so whenever I move the
window or whenever these color changes
we are going to save it, and sometimes
this can be heavy in terms of
performance. If you don't want this, you
can use custom settings. And what this
allows you to do is to save the data
whenever you want. The way you do that is
you define the settings component like
this, you put in the property that you
want to save, then you give it a default
value like this.. you see "spring" here is a
default value... In this case we are trying
to save state data, we looked at states
and transitions in the last chapter, if
you remember... we are trying to save the
spring state in one of the demos that we
did. After you define your settings
component, you have to fit the property
in your application. Your application has
to read the property from the Settings
component here, and this is what we are
doing: the state of our rectangle is
coming from the Settings component, and
whenever the state changes in your
application, you update the state here.
And after you do that, you have to decide
on when to save your data. In this case
we are saving the data when the
component dies, but you can do it
whenever you want. For example, you can do
it when a user presses a button or
whenever, really, in your QML application.
Okay, settings is one way to save your
data, but we can also use an embedded
SQLite database that is going to be on
your computer. To use that, you have to
import QT quick local storage 2.0. This
is what we have at the time of recording
this video. Database is already available
on your system so you don't need to set
it up or connect to it, you just need to
create and manage your databases and
tables and we're going to do that in a
moment. You're going to see exactly how
this works. Okay here we see the table
that we are going to design for in our
demo. We want to save location data and
color data, the same thing we did with
settings, but we are saving that
as a json object in a table that we
are going to define. The table is going
to have two fields: the name of the
setting that we want to save, and the
value of that setting. We try to make
things very simple for you to understand,
but if you know SQLite, you can quickly
see that you can use this to do all
kinds of crazy things. We're not going to
cover SQLite in this lecture, you have to
consult other pieces of documentation
for that, but it is not very difficult to
understand. Here you see that you can
also show the location of the database
on your system, it really is a file that
you're going to find, and you're going to
see this in a demo that we're going to
do, okay. This is how you connect to the
database and create your tables. You see
localStorage,openDatabaseSync, you parse
in the identifier for the database, you
parse in the version, you parse in the
description, and you parse in the
estimated size of the database. After
that you can do transactions on your
database. For example, here we are
executing the query to create a table.
The table name is this, and these are the
fields that we have. When you have your
database and your tables, the next thing
you usually want to do is to stuff in
some data. Here I have shown a simple
function that we created in our demo to
store some data. We are checking to see
if the database exists. If it doesn't
exist, we'll return. And we do a
transaction to store the data. We want to
see that we have our value in the table,
so we are selecting everything from
SQLitedemotable where the name equals
SQLite demo, remember that our table has
a field called sqlitedemo, this is what
we are checking for. Here we are
preparing the data that we want to save
in our database,
okay, we are stuffing the data from our
UI components... you see... we are capturing X
Y, width and height information, and we
capture the components of the color
that we want to save, and we save that
in our JSON object here. Next we
look at the result. If we got one result
it means that we had some thing
in our table, and we update, we don't want to
put in something new... that's why our
transaction here is update, we update the
table and we want to set the value where
the name equals sqlitedemo and we want
to put in our JSON objects that we
created. We are just stringifying it. If
we don't have the element already, we
insert in the database and we put it in
like this. This is really plain SQLite
knowledge, so if you are rusty on that
you should read on that, you're going to
understand these queries that we are
parsing in here. This thing you have in
brackets like this replaces what you
have with this question mark. This is
the only thing that is special here, okay,
this is how you store data, we're
going to do that in a demo, if you don't
understand this yet,
please don't worry. And this is how you
read the data. You also check to see if
the database is there, you have a
transaction here, inside you want to
execute this SQL query, we want to select
everything, we really are doing the same
thing. If we have a result, we want to
capture the value in that result, okay,
this is how you capture it. We parse the
JSON in the value that we got, and then
we read the data, okay. This is a JSON
object that we have in obj. So we
captured the data that we want and we
put that in our UI components: X, Y, width,
height, and we construct our color for
the components like this. This method
rgba is available in our Qt global
object as we have seen before. And
everything we've talked about here is
documented in the local storage
documentation either online or in
Qt Creator. We'd like to go to QT creator
and look at that, okay. Here we are in QT
creator. If you go to the documentation
and type in local storage like this,
you're going to find QT quick local
storage, click on that and you are going
to fall here. And they say that this is a
singleton for reading and writing
SQLite databases. If you click on this,
they tell you what the sqlite environment
they have is made of, they show you the
methods that you can call, open database,
they really tell you everything we just
talked about, and even more. So if you are
in doubt about something, this is what
you should read. Down here they also have
an example that you can look at. I do
recommend to look at this later when you
are finished with this course, because it
is a good way to practice your knowledge.
Okay this is all we're going to look at
in this chapter. We're going to look at
settings, and we are going to look at how
you work with SQLite in your QML
application. The last lecture, we're
going to look at settings I'll see you there.