In this lecture we're going to see how
you store your data in QML using
the Settings QML type.
Here we are on the online documentation
for the settings qml type, and they say
that it provides persistent
platform-independent application
settings. If you are on a Windows machine
it, is stored in a given location, if you
are on a Mac, it is stored in a given
location, but this location is not for
you to mess with, ok. This is handled by
the system, all you have to do is know
how to use this and your data is going
to be saved, you're going to be able to
save you data and you're going to be
able to load your data. First thing you
should notice is that they have a note
here, you should read this very carefully.
this type is made available by importing
the Qt.labs.settings module. Types in QT
labs modules are not guaranteed to
remain compatible in future versions. If
you are using thi, you should be careful
and come back in the future to see if
there are any changes to this and change
your application accordingly.
There are two ways we are going to use
this thing, really. One is to let the
settings completely handle the saving
and loading of data for us and this is
what they do in this example here.
Another way is to do part of the work of
saving the data yourself, and save the
data when your component is dying, ok. You
do that like this, and we're going to do
an example in a moment. Right now we want
to go to QT creator, and start a project,
and see how we can let the system handle
everything for us. Here we are in QT
creator, we're going to create a new
project, it's Qt Quick application as
usual, we call it SettingsDemo1,
because we are going to do another
settings demo. We hit next, choose our QT
version, and finish. We want to say
SettingsDemo1. We want to do what we
are supposed to do: import Qt.labs.settings 1.0.
Come back to our
application and do that.
In this application we want to store the
location and the size of the window, so
we are going to store X, Y, width, and
height, and we want to store the color of
the rectangle that we are going to put
inside here. We want to put in a
rectangle component pretty quick.
Rectangle... id... recId. It's going to fill
the parent, and this color is going to be
red by default. Inside we want to put a
mouse area, it's going to fill the
rectangle. When it is clicked, we want to
pop up a dialog that is going to allow
the user to select a color. Because we
want to use dialogues, we want to import
the module like this, you probably
remember this, we have seen this before.
Inside our mouse area, we are going to
define a color dialogue component.
Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to  align. And it is
nothing fancy, we have an ID, it has a
title that tells us to choose a color,
and we want to know when the color is
selected, we know that in the onAccepted
method here, and the new color is going
to be stored in the color property of
the color dialogue. When it is rejected,
we say "Cancelled". Notice that we are
using the wrong ID here, so we should say
rectId, and set the color of this
rectangle here. So what we want to do
when we click, we're going to say
color.dialogId.open(). We're going to open the
dialog. If you run the application, mm-hmm,
we see our window here, but we have the
possibility to click inside the
rectangle and choose a different color
if we wish so, ok. The color becomes blue.
But if we close the application and open
it again, you see that the color that we
set is lost. And if we move it for
example to the top here change the color
to black,
hit okay, close up, and again, you see that
location data and color data is lost. We
want to change that, we want to save all
this information using settings. So we're
going to go below the rectangle here and
say Settings... We want to set the category
for this set of settings. Let's call this
"window" because it is window related data.
And the way you store data automatically:
you define a set of property aliases
that link to the data that you want to
save. So for example for the X location
for this window, we're going to say
property alias, and say window... we need to
give the window an ID... let's say rootId
and we're going to say here rootId.x.
And we're going to do the same for Y,
width, and height, so we can copy this and
paste it a couple of times. This is going
to be y, width, and height. And
you may not believe it, but just by doing
this you are instructing your system to
keep track of these values for you, okay.
When the X property changes for this
window, we're going to store that, and
next time when we run the application, it
is going to get the data from these
settings here. Notice that the default
value for this thing is set here, so the
x position is going to be the default
one, the Y position is going to be the
default one, width and height are going
to be these things here. Let's see what
happens on the location data of our
window if we run.
Let's move it in the top-left corner of
our screen here, and reduce the size of
it, make it really small.
Let's close the application, run it again,
and you see that our settings are not
saved. We expected the settings to be
saved, what is wrong? Well, if we go back
to the documentation, if you scroll down
a little bit, you're going to see
application identifiers here. So these
are the settings that are specific to
your application, and you have to parse in
things like this, okay: organization
name, organization domain, application
name, if you don't parse in these settings,
your settings are not going to be saved,
because obviously your application does
not have an identity, and if the system
saves your data, it's not going to know
who the data belongs to. So short story
is you have to set this. And if you
notice that we set this in
the main.cpp file, the C++ file of your
qml project, so we can go back to our
project here, go in sources, open main.cpp,
go below where we define app here,
go below it, and put in things like this...
Ctrl+A Ctrl+I to align, okay. We are
setting the organization name, we are
setting the domain, and we are setting
the application name, okay. Do this
you can parse in whatever data
you want, you can parse in whatever
organization name, parse in a domain, you
can even parse this if you want, I don't
mind, and you can parse in "SettingsDemo".
Now, if we run the application, you see
that location data is saved. I can change
this, I can make it... I can make this
really really big, and move it to the
right, for example, close the application,
open it again, and you see that location
and size information is stored for us.
This is how you store data automatically,
you put whatever data that you want to
save in their settings like this, and the
data is going to be saved. Another thing
worth seeing is that you can break your
settings into categories, and we are
going to do that. We're going to create
another settings component, category is
going to be colors, you can do whatever
you want in here, and we are going to
say property
alias rectColor... it's going to be
rectId.color. And just like this, it is
going to keep track of the color that we
have in the rectangle here. In other
words, if we change it like we do here,
the new change is going to be saved.
Let's run, choose the color, let's make it
green like this, hit OK, make this thing
really small like this, put it in the
bottom left corner of the window, close
the application, open it again,
you see that even the color is saved.
Let's make it yellow, hit ok, put it in the
top like this, close the application, open
it again, you see that everything is
saved. This is really convenient, and it
works really well
if you want to save data, you don't have
to do a lot of things, and it is very
clean looking at this, you don't have a
lot of garbage that saves and loads your
data. But the cost is that every time the
property changes, you are going to save
it in your application, and this can be a
huge drown on your performance, so you
want to be careful when you use this. And
a better way if you don't want to pay
this performance cost is to save the
data yourself, and choose when you save
the data. And in the next lecture we're
going to show you how you can exactly do
that. I'll see you there