In this lecture we're going to look at
how you can work with SQLite in your qml
application. SQLite allws you to save
your data in a database that is embedded
in your system, and you don't need to
create a database or do some kind of
connection to the database. You use the
database that is available to you, and
all you have to do is to create
databases and tables, and do all kinds of
crazy things. We're going to go to QT
creator and play with this in QT quick.
Okay so here we are in Qt creator. We
are going to create our project Qt
quick, so Qt application, we call
it SQLiteDemo, save it in the usual
location, hit next, choose our QT version,
choose your kit, and finish. We want to
change the text here to say SQLite Demo.
We want to do our imports here, if you
remember, we have to import QT quick
local storage if we want to work with
SQLite databases, so we say import
QtQuick.LocalStorage 2.0. We also want to
import QtQuick.Dialogs because we
are going to do a dialog to choose a
color, let's do too here. So what we want
to do is pretty much what we did in the
settings, we want to save the location of
the window and the color of the window,
but this time we are going to use an
SQLite database. We're going to put in a
Rectangle component. Id is going to be
contained... It is going to fill the
parent, and it is going to be red by
default. So we say red. Inside we want to
have a mouse area because we want it to
be clickable for the user to select the
color of the window here using the
dialog. The mouse area should fill the
parent, and when it is clicked we do
something. In the mouse area, we want to
put in our dialog... ctrl A ctrl I
to align... it is nothing fancy, it's
everything we've done before. We have a
dialogue, it has an ID,
and we can accept the value, or we can
reject it. When we click on the mouse
area we want to open the dialog. We're
going to say color... open... like this.
And we want to give an ID to this Window,
so we're going to say rootId,
this will do. And I think by now we can
run the application and be able to
change the color of the rectangle that
fills the window here. Let's check on IDs...
this is right. Let's run. Okay, here is our
application. The rectangle is red by
default, if you click inside, you see a
dialog like this, it says choose color. We
can click inside to choose a color or
we can move this slider here to choose
between these colors. Let's choose this
greenish color, hit OK, you see that our
color is in. If we close and run again, our
color and position are lost. We close, we
open again, you see that it comes in the
middle, it takes default values. We want
to change this, we want to save the X&Y
location of the window, we also want to
save the width and height, and we want to
save the color that is inside... all using
SQLite. Now we are going to do quite a
lot in JavaScript, so it is a good idea
to create an external javascript file, do
all things in there, and import it and
just call the functions to do our dirty
work in here. We want to come to qrc
here, we add new Qt JS file, which is
really JavaScript file, we choose this,
we call it Database, and we next, and
finish, and we take this out. We want to
come to main.qml first, and put in a
property for our database, we're going to
say property... var... it's going to be a var,
and it's called db, and it doesn't take
any value by
default. We are going to come back to
JavaScript and create a function, we call
it dbInit to initialize our database.
First we are going to console.log
Initialize... And next we want to open our
database... I am going to put in the
statement... we define db in the main QML
file, and we are going to be able to call
the JavaScript file here, and make it
look as if this was defined here, so we
are going to be able to access things in
here, that's why this db variable is
available to us in this function here. Now
we have our database opened, this is the
database name, this is the version, this
is the description of the database, and
this is the estimated size of the
database in bytes, we looked at this in
the introductory video on the chapter
here. After you have your database opened...
and by the way, this is going to create
the database if it is not available, if
it is already available it is going to
open it. After you do this, you want to do
a transaction, so the transaction we're
going to do is to create a table if it
doesn't exist.
This is a normal SQL query, nothing
special here, we are creating the table
called sqlitedemotable and it has two
fields a name field and the value field,
and they are a data type of text. By now
we should have a database and the table
ready to be consumed by our application.
We can save data or read data from it.
So what we want to do is to store the x
and y location of this window here, rootId
is the ID that we are going to use, we
also want to capture the width and
height of the window, we also want to
save the color that the user chooses
here, so that next time the user runs the
application, the rectangle here displays
the background of it in that color. So we
are going to define our function to
store data... function...
It's not going to take any parameter
because it is going to work on the data
that we have in our QML file here. We
want to console.log that we are storing
data... copy that put that here and say
"Storing data"... And we want to check to see
if this db is available and initialized.
The way we do that we say... if not db...
return... okay, if the database is not
available, we get out of this function, we
don't do anything, because we are just
going to get errors if we try to work on
a database that is not available, that is
not properly initialized. We want to put
a semicolon here. Next we want to do a
transaction that is going to store our
data in the database. So we're going to
say transaction(function(TX)), inside we
are going to parse in the body of the
function, and we should put a semicolon
at the end, and we put this on different
lines so that we have something good to
look at. Inside here, we are going to
try and update the data that is in this
table here, if it is already available, or
we are going to insert a new data set if
the data is not already available. The
first thing we want to do is to check
and see if an SQLite demo entry is
available in our table. The way we do
that we say var result = tx... our
transaction here, which is the parameter
that we had... we say executeSql(), inside we
parse in our SQL query. We are going to
select everything from the table where
name equals sqlitedemo, so I am going to
put in the query because I don't want to
type it it is very long... select
everything from the table here where the
name equals sqlitedemo.
If you look at the table that we are
designing for, you see that our data
entry, the name for that equals
sqlitedemo. This is what we are checking, I just
want you to have some context on what we
are doing. This reminds me that we also
have to show you how to look at the
location of your database, we're going to
do that, but first let's finish this, okay.
Now that we have a result here, we're
going to check and see if we actually
had anything in this entry here, and if
we had the entry, we're going to update
that with a new data set, if the entry is
not available, we're going to write a
completely new data set in this entry
here. But before we do that, we want to
prepare our JSON data that we're going
to write in the database. So let's say
that. This is actually very easy, you just
capture data from your qml component, the
X location, the Y location, the width and
height, you capture that, and you put
that in a JSON object that we define
here, okay. You see we have X is the
X location of the root window, Y is the
Y location, we have width and height,
we also have the colors that we have in
that rectangle of ours. We are capturing
the Red Green and Blue component, and we
are putting this in a JSON object that
we call obj. This is what we are going to
save in the database. Now we want to see
the number of rows that we got from this
SQL query here. This is going to return
the number of rows that have been
affected by this, so we can say
if(result.rows.length===1)... If we fall
here, we already have the data entry and
we just need to update it, so here we are
going to do an update. If the length is
not 1, it is probably 0, we didn't find
anything
the database, and we are going to create
a new entry, that's what we're going to
do here. So here we should say
console.log("Updating database table..."), and here
console.log("Creating new database table...").
And here we are doing to do the same
thing we did here, so we are going to
capture this, ok, copy this because I
don't want to type it,
I am lazy at typing, and we are going to
put in a query to update the data. Here
we are going to do the same thing and we
are going to put in a query to create a
new database entry. Our query to update
is going to look like this, it's nothing
fancy, really, if you know some SQL,
update the table, set the value, it is
one... value that we want to set, the
dqlitedemo value, and we want to set it to the
value that we parse in here, and we take
this object we have here and turn that
into a string so that we can save it in
the database. You use JSON.stringify, this
is a method that comes from javascript,
you can check it in the documentation
and see what it does, but it turns your
JSON into a string. Okay, just like this,
we have updated our database with new
data. We want to create a new data set if
it is not available, and we are going to
do an insert, and we are going to insert
it into the table the values are going
to be replaceable in this question marks,
and what we are going to replace them is
the name of the data entry and the value,
and the value is really a json.stringify
the object that we have defined here.
And just like this, we are able to store
data in our database, okay. If this is not
clear to you, take some time to look at
it again, it's really easy to understand.
The only point where you might think
that this is really hard is if you are
rusty on sqlite, and it is not very
difficult to search for an SQLite
tutorial on the Internet
to have an idea about what we are doing
here. Now we have been able to store data,
we want to read data. We are going to
define a new method that is called
readData... function readDate(), it is not going
to take any parameter, it is going to
work directly on the data that we have
in our qml file. The start is really
going to be the same, we can copy this
and put that in our new function, it's
going to save us from typing a few
things. We should say "Reading data...". And we
are checking to see if the database is
available, and if it's not available,
we're going to return out of this
function immediately. Next we want to do
a db transaction, and it is going to be
the same thing we did here, so we can
actually copy this and paste this here,
and take out everything inside, because
we are going to do something completely
different. We are going to read data from
the database. We should say that here...
"Reading data". We want to select
everything in the database table where
the name field equals sqlitedemo, this
is what we are doing here, and we want to
know if we actually got something from
the database, this is where we know that
we have data that we can work with. Now
we need a way to take the data that we
get from the database and turn that into
a JSON object that we can then retrieve
data from and use in our qml code. The
way you do that you get the first row
from the values that you get from the
database, and you call value on it, and
you have a value which is a string,
really, you need to convert that to a
JSON object, and you do that by calling
JSON.parse and parsing in your string
value. And by now we have
an object that we can retrieve data from.
Okay now that we have the JSON object, we
can read the data into our qml
properties. We say rootId.x =
obj.x. Remember when we stored the
data, we put that into a JSON object and
we had these attributes: we have X, Y,
width, height, color red, color green, color
blue, and you see that we are reading
everything by using the same attributes
we use to store it data. This is very
important, because if you get this wrong,
the system is not going to know what you
are trying to get from the database. Be
careful about this. And by now, when you
call the readData method, you are going
to read the data from the database and
stuff that into your qml components. We
are storing location and size
information on the window, and we are
storing the background color of the
rectangle inside. What remains now is
coming to the qml file and import
our JavaScript file, you already know how
to do that. We want to come here and say
import "Database.js", and we import
that as... something... you specify a
namespace here that you want to use to
call your functions. Now we want to come
to the end of the window here and say
Component.onCompleted... we want to do
something, and say Component.onDestruction...
we want to do something.
onCompleted, this is where this window
here is loaded in memory, and we want to
do something, we want to read the data
and stuff that into our qml
properties here, we are going to set
location and size information, we also
are going to set the color here, okay.
This is how we read the data, and we can
say JS.readData(), just like this. But
before we read the data, we need to
initialize our data base, so we should
say JS.dbinit()...
I just forgot that in a moment, I'm
sorry about that.
And when our component is about to die,
we are going to save the data, so you're
going to say
JS.storeData, this is what we call
that. I clear the space here, do the same
here,
and this is neat. And by now, we can run
the application and see if our thing is
working here. Let's run. You see that it
reads data, and it is reading the data
from one of my previous test
applications, but you get the idea. So
we're going to bring it back in the
middle here, and we're going to try and
change the color, let's change it to blue
like this, okay let's change it to pink
like this, move the window to the left
here, close the application, and you see
that we get an error here... we didn't call
the method right, we called it "exetcute", we
did it all over the place. So we should
say executeSql, we're going to be very
careful about this now... executeSql, is it
right? Where else do we have this?
executeSql... executeSql here. I think we
should be okay by now. I'm sorry for this.
Let's bring the application somewhere,
change the color to yellow this time, we
change the size of the window, we close
the application... what the heck is wrong
with you?
Let's save this. Come to qml, change a few
things put in some spaces to have QT
creator pick our changes, okay. We
change the location of the window, we
change the size, and we change the color
in the middle to green, hit okay, close
the application, now it is updating data.
If we run again, our application should
be in a new location, and it should have
the color that we have specified. This is
what I am talking about when I tell you
that you can save data. This is really
all we had to do in this lecture, and it
isn't really rocket science, you have to
use the function as we used here, and
you can adapt these examples to save
whatever you want in your database. The
key here is to know your SQLite and know
how to handle these queries, create, read
update, and delete, and if you can do that,
you're not going to have any problem
storing your data in QT quick
applications. The last thing I want to
show you before we wrap up this lecture
is how you can show the location of your
database file. And the way you do that
you come here in the main.cpp file,
import QDebug... include . It is
a class that allows you to do things
like console log, showing log messages
and we want to come down here and put
our statement to debug output the
location of the SQLite database. This is
how you put it out. If we run the
application now, we are going to see that
in the application output, we are going
to see a path on our drive, and you see
that this is the location where my
things are stored. We can go there, I
think, we are going to need to take out
these double backslashes, because
sometimes they miss things up... I
don't think windows is going to
recognize this, but we can take that out
manually... let's take this out, copy this,
come to My Computer, paste that in here,
and you see that we have qml in here,
we have offline storage, we have
databases, and these are our database
files, okay. You cannot read this because
it is binary file, but if you delete this,
for example, let's delete that... okay we
can't delete this because it is being
used by some application, but I think we
just lost our data. Let's run the
application again, and you see that it
becomes red, okay, you get the idea. That's
the location of your database, it is
trying to open this version and I think
it is not existent... we should delete that
file... how do we delete that if it is
being used by an external application
that we don't know? Now it's gone. Let's
come to Qt creator, clean everything,
clean, clean project, build, clean all, let's
close this, run the application, and this
time, we are not having this error, and
you can store the data again. Let's make
it green, reduce the size, close the
application, start it again, and you see
that it is working correctly. This is
really all I had to say in this lecture.
I hope you know how you can use SQLite
to save and load your data in your Qt Quick
with applications. And I hate to say it,
but this is the last lecture in the
course, and you have learned quite a lot
if you have watched all the lectures in
the course. In the next lecture, I am
going to give you a few tips on how you
can improve the knowledge that you
have in this course, and move further
in your Qt Creator UI development.
I'll see you in the next lecture.