[Music]
In this video we will create a simple
To-do list application. At the end of the
tutorial you will have learned how to
display and modify C++ models in QtQuick.
If you're not familiar with QtQuick
or Qt Creator, we'd recommend
watching the 'Getting started with Qt:
Hello Quick World' video first. As this
video, you will see some familiarity
with these topics. The first step is to
launch a Qt creator, we will be using version
4.4.1 along with Qt 5.9.2.
Let's create a new project. Click the 'New
Project' button.
Select the 'Qt Quick Controls 2 Application'.
And then click on the 'Choose'
button.
Give the project a name, we'll call ours
'todo-list'
separated by hyphens.
Select the suitable location for the
project, we will use the default location.
Click 'Next' when you're done.
Next choose a build system, we'll stick
with the default which is qmake.
We're now given the option of
Qt Quick Controls 2 style, choose
'Material' from the combo box and then
click 'Next'.
Select the kit that you'd like to use
and then click 'Next'.
Click 'Finish' to create the project.
Our project has been created, and now
we're looking at main.qml in the editor.
Qt Creator generated some code for us
that we don't need, so let's remove it.
First remove the code in main.qml,
leaving only application window and its
properties.
Then remove Page1Form.ui.qml
by right-clicking on it in the
product tree and selecting 'Remove File'.
Check the 'Delete File Permanently' on the
check box and then click 'OK'. We'll be
doing most of our work in the editor, so
we won't use UI QML files. Next rename
Page1.qml to ToDoList.qml
by right-clicking on it in the project
tree and selecting 'Rename'.
You
add the following code to application
window.
You
copy the imports at the top of main.qml
and replace the imports in
ToDoList.qml with them.
You
then replace the top level 'item' with a
'frame'.
The 'frame' type comes from Qt Quick
Controls 2 and provides a convenient way
to illustrate the boundary about a
to-do-list. Let's run the application, click
the 'Run' button or press Ctrl+R.
We see a small empty frame in the middle
of the window.
Close the application and return to
Qt Creator.
Within the frame, add a ListView.
ListView is the most common view type
in Qt Quick. There are three important
things that ListView needs in order to
display data: a size, a model and a
delegate. The size determines the area
within which the user can interact with
the list items. Add the following code.
You
notice that we're using implicitWidth
and implicitHeight instead of width and
height. Implicit sizes are a natural or
default size for an item. For example the
text type has an implicit size which is
the width and height of the text it
contains. In our case, frame will
automatically resize itself to the
implicit size of its child item so long
as there is only one item. We take
advantage of that here so that we don't
have to explicitly specify a size for
the frame.
The ListView model is the source of the
data that it uses to create list items.
Type of the following code.
This tells the ListView that the model
is composed of 100 numbers. We use an
integer based model for now because it
will allow us to see how the ListView
behaves.
The model could also be a QML
List Model and javascript array or a C++
model amongst other things.
The delegate is a component, a type of
visual template that describes how list
items will look. For our to do list, we
want a check box to mark items as done
and a text field to enter description. We
also want these items to be laid out
side by side, so add a RowLayout.
RowLayout comes from the QtQuick
Layouts import and behaves similarly to
the row from QtQuick. Within the row
layout, add a CheckBox and a TextField.
These two types are controls from the
QtQuick.Controls 2 import. Run the
application to see how it behaves so far.
You might notice that the contents for
this view are visible outside of the
frame which is not what we want. We'll
fix that shortly. The CheckBox and TextField
can be interacted with, but as they
are not hooked up to the model, any
changes will be lost when they go far
enough outside the ListView. This is
because this view destroys delegates
that are not visible in order to save
memory, allowing it to display large
amounts of data in an efficient manner.
To try this out,
check the checkbox that is a few
delegates down in the ListView.
Scroll down to this view by flicking or
scrolling with the mouse wheel,
then scroll back up to the top.
The checkbox is no longer checked as it
was destroyed and recreated.
Close the application and go back to
Qt Creator. Set 'clip' to true on the ListView.
This will ensure that any list items
outside of the view will not be visible. In
the delegate, set 'width' to 'parent.width'.
Now the row layout will be as wide as
ListView whereas before it was only as
wide as combined widths of its children,
the CheckBox and the TextField. We want the
TextField to be as wide as possible so
that the user has plenty of space to
write in. Add the following attached
property binding to text field.
and attached property provides a way to
annotate an object with extra properties
or signal handles that are otherwise
unavailable to it. In this case, we use
the layout attached type to make sure the
text field takes up as much horizontal
space as possible.
Run the application to see the changes.
Notice that the ListView items are no
longer visible outside of the view and
the TextField is wider.
Now we'll take a look at the model. Close
the application and return to Qt Creator.
Replace the integer model with a list
model.
Within it, add a list element object with
the following code.
Each property in a list element is
called a 'role'. If you're familiar with
C++ models and queued, it's the same
concept.
The 'done' role solves boolean values and
the 'description' role stall strings. Copy
and paste the list element and set as
properties to the following values.
If we were to run the application now,
we'd have 2 list items but they won't
display the data from our model because
they're not connected to it yet. In the
checkbox control, set the 'checked'
property to model.done.
Roles in model are available to
delegates through the model object. We
could also refer to the role directly
without going through the model object.
However doing it this way will result in
the code being easier for others to read
and understand as they can instantly see
where the properties come from. In text
field, set the text property to
model.description.
Now I'm going to run the application.
The checkbox and text field are displaying
the data from the model.
However, any changes to the controls
values are not stored in the model. For
that to happen, we need to respond to
user interaction and set the values of
the model rules accordingly. Close the
application and return to Qt Creator.
In the CheckBox, add the following code.
Now whenever the checkbox is clicked for
your mouse, touch or keyboard, the new
value will be stored in the model. In
text fields, add this code.
This does something similar with the
only different thing that the editing
finished signal ((onEditingFinished) is emitted
whenever the Enter key is pressed or
the text field loses focus. Our to-do
list can now be edited but are still
using the qml based list model. For some
use cases, simple models like this are
sufficient, especially if the data cannot
be editted or does not need to be saved
to disk in order to be persistent. In
most cases however the logic of the
application is in C++ and hence the C++
model is needed to provide a startup to
QML. Let's add a C++ model. Open the 'File'
Menu and select 'New File or Project'.
Under the 'Files and Classes' section,
select Qt
then select 'Qt item model' from the
list.
Click the 'Choose' button,
now we're looking at a wizard that will
create the skeleton of our model. For the
'Class Name', type ToDoModel.
In the Base Class select
'QtAbtractListModel'.
This is a convenience class
implementing list models and it's derived from
QtAbstractItemModel which is the base
class of all other models in Qt.
Uncheck 'Customize header row' and check
'Items are editable'.
The header and source file names are
automatically suggested for us based on
the class name we entered. Click Next,
and then finish.
We're now looking at to todomodel.cpp.
To start off we're going to implement
just enough functionality so that we can
see our C++ model in our Qt ListView.
The first thing that we need to do
is define the role names that we use in
QML, 'done' and 'description'. Switch to the
header file by pressing F4 or
right-clicking anywhere in the file and
selecting 'Switch Header/Source' from the
context menu.
Add the following enum after the
constructor.
Add the following code after
the last function.
Right-click on the function signature
and select 'Refactor', 'Add definition in
todomodel.cpp'.
We've now been taken to the definition
of the function in the source file.
Add the following code.
In the 'rowCount' function add a
'return' statement that simply returns 100.
This will give us 100 rows in the model.
In the 'data' function, add this code after
the FIXME comment.
Now the model will return placeholder
data but we still need to make QML
aware of it and use it. Open main.cpp.
Add an 'include' for 'todomodel.h' after
the Qt includes.
Then after the line where QGuiApplication
is constructed, add this code
This function registers as C++ model
with a QML type system.
Come to ToDoList.qml,
add an import for us ToDo library after
the Qt imports.
Replace the ListModel with ToDoModel
Open the 'Build' menu and select 'Run qmake'.
This ensures that MOC, the meta object
compiler, is run. Any class with the Qt
object macro that is added to a project
requires qmake to be run. Now run
the application which will also call it
to be built.
A model data from C++ is displayed.
Notice it's not possible to
change the values of the controls.
To make the controls editable, we have to
implement the set data function which
also requires us to store the Todo-list
start of somewhere. We could store the
data in the model but in a real-world
scenario, the data is stored in the
backend separate from the model. Open the
'File' menu and select a 'New file or
project'.
Under the 'Files and Classes' the section,
select 'C++' then 'C++ Class'.
We're now looking at the C++ class
wizard, type ToDoList into the 'Class
name' field.
In the Base Class combo box
select QObject,
click Next,
and then click Finish. We're now looking
at todolist.cpp, switch to the
header file.
There are three actions todolist class
should support in terms of todo items:
adding new items, modifying existing
items and removing items. Each to-do item
has two properties that we defined as
roles earlier, 'done' and 'description'. Let's
make it, ToDoItem struct, to make it
easier to manage multiple items. Add the
following code above ToDoList class
public section.
Include QVector after the QObject
include.
Add a private QVector ToDoItem as a
member variable of ToDoList.
Next we're going to add three functions
to support the actions we mentioned
earlier. After the constructor and before
the signal's keyword, add the following
code.
This will allow the model to modify the
to-do lists data, next add two functions
below the 'public slots' section.
This will be called by the Qml code
Under the 'signals' section, add the
following code.
Using pre and post signals matches up
with what the model expects. Need to
be notified before something is about to
happen to the data that it is exposing
and also afterwards. Now we need to
provide a way for the model to access
the data in the list. Add this function
after the constructor.
Let's implement these functions. For each
function, except the signals which don't
need definitions, we're going to be using
Qt Creator's refactoring option to add a
definition in the source file.
Right-click on the signature of the
items function and select a 'Refactor',
'Add definition in todolist.cpp'.
In the body of the function, add the
following code.
Do the same for setItmAt.
In its body add this code.
First we check if the index is valid,
returning false if it's not.
The set data function ToDoModel
returns a bool to indicate whether or
not the data was successfully modified.
So that's why we also return a bool. Next
add the following.
This stores the current or old item in a
local const variable then checks if the
new item has identical values to the old
one, if so it returns false to indicate
that nothing has changed. Finally add
this code.
If the execution of the code has gotten
this far it means that the item has
changed so we store it in our lists and
return true.
Now let's implement the two slots,
Add a definition for append item via the
refactor menu.
Add the following code to its body.
We omit the pre and post signals before
and after
the appendItem.
Eventually we will connect the model up
to their signals.
Go back to the header file
and add a definition for remove
completed items.
Add the following "for" loop to its body.
Then within the "for" loop, add this code.
We loop over each item in the list and
check if it's 'done'. If so we omit the pre
signal, remove the item and then omit the
post signal. If the item is not 'done' we
move on to the next one.
Finally we're going to pretend that our
list already had some data in it by
appending a few items in the constructor.
After do this, class is now done.
Typically C++ classes like this created
as part of the larger application
back-end in C++, so that's what we're
going to do. We'll create an instance of
the past in main.cpp .
After the last Qt include add this
line.
This is necessary in order to be able to
expose the object to Qml,
then include todolist.h
After the qmlRegisterType code, add this
line.
And before the engine.load code, add this
This is where the to-do list is actually
exposed to QML. We set it as a context
property which means that it is
available to any Qml files loaded by
the application. There are other ways to
expose other Qml as properties but
this is the most convenient one.
Run qmake
and then build a project to check
that there are no errors.
Now we're going to make ToDoModel
aware of to-do lists. Open todomodel.h
and add a forward declaration for to-do
list.
We'll only be referring to to-do list
through pointers in the header, so it's
not necessary to include it yet. After
the Q_OBJECT macro, begin typing
Q_PROPERTY and then hit Enter,
once the suggestion with the red icon on
the left is visible. This is a convenient
snippet that saves us from typing.
Without changing the position of the
cursor, type 'ToDoList'
then press Tab and type 'list'.
The key object attributes are
automatically updated. Press ENTER to
confirm its changes
and then add an asterisk to the left of
the first instance of list to mark it as
a pointer, remove and notify list change
part as it's optional and not required
in our case.
Under the private section of ToDoModel,
add this line
Right click on that member variable and
select 'Refactor',
'Create Getter and Setter Member Functions'.
Switch to the source file and add an
include todolist.h
In the constructors initializer list
initialize 'nList' with a null pointer (nullptr).
At the top of setList, add the
following code.
Before the source of model started
changes, we must call beginResetModel.
As I'll be connecting to the signals
other to-do lists it's also a good idea
to disconnect from the oldest when
setting a new one. In our case this isn't
necessary, as a property will only be set
once. However it's a good habit to get
into it. After the list has been assigned
add the following if statement.
If a valid to-do-list was set on the
model, we will connect to its various
signals in order to call the beginning
and end functions. Add the following code
within the if statement.
This connects a lambda to the preItemAppended
signal of to-do lists. The lambda
calls beginInsertRows with an invalid
model index which is fine, as we want to
add the items to the foot note of the
model. The next two arguments are the
first and last indices within which the
new items will be inserted. Since we want
to append items to the end of the model,
we use an index as one passed the last
valid index in the list.
Next connect postItemAppended to a
lambda that calls endInsertRows.
Connect preItemRemoved to a lambda that
calls beginRemoveRows.
Finally connect postedItemRemove to a
lambda the calls endRemoveRows.
To match the beginResetModel, we also
call endResetModel.
Now is a good time to build a project to
check that our compiles.
I'm almost ready to use on model and QML.
Let's implement the remaining functions.
In rowCount, add null point to check to
the if statement.
We're going to do the same for other
functions that use the nList member
variable as is a good practice to
safeguard against null point to
access it, remove the FIXME comment and
change your return statement to return
the amount of items in the todo-list
and data at the same null point to check.
Remove the FIXME comment and store
the current item in the local const variable.
In the 'switch' cases, return the relevant
data phase row.
And setData, add an if statement that
returns false if the null pointer check
fails.
Then store the current item at the index
in a local variable.
We're going to check which role 's set
and updated.
Copy the 'switch' code from the 'data'
function,
and paste it after the last line we
added.
Modify the 'done' role case so that it
looks like this.
Then modify the 'description' role case
Remove the FIXME comment
and change this statement.
We take advantage of setItemAt
return value to determine whether or not
the data has actually changed, and
therefore only emit the dataChanged
signal if we need to. Finally if the data
has changed, we return 'true', otherwise
'false'. In the ItemFlags function, remove the
FIXME comment.
The item is editable file or not file
use case. Open main.cpp,
and add the following
after the code to ....
This forces ToDoList is a QML type, so
that can be used as a property of
ToDoModel. As it is a back-end type, we don't
intend for it to be created in QML, so we
use the qmlRegisterUncreatableType
function. This function prints the error
message that we passed as the last
argument if we attempt to instantiate
the type in QML. In ToDoList.qml,
assign ToDoList context property
to the 'list' property of ToDoModel.
Run the application.
We can now edit the model data
that comes from C++ in a QtQuick
ListView.
Before we can consider our application
complete. We need to make it possible for
users to add and remove items from a
list. We're going to add two buttons
below the to-do list to achieve this.
Close the application
and add a column layout as a parent of
the frame.
To quickly indent a QML file, select the
code and press Ctrl+I.
After the frame, add a RowLayout.
Within the RowLayout, add two buttons.
Run the application to see how it looks
so far.
Notice how the buttons happen to align
nicely with the width of the ListView. By
convenient, this is just a coincidence, we
need to take a few steps to ensure the
combined widths of the buttons match the
width of the ListView and vice versa. To
simulate how wide the buttons might be
on a system with a larger default font
size, let's temporarily add some text to
the labels.
Add three spaces at the end of each
button stack string.
Next we want to make sure that each
button fills the width of the row layout.
Then add the same bounding to the frame.
Finally make ListView fill the frame.
Run the application again.
Now if the button text is too wide, this
view will stretch accordingly.
Remove the extra spaces from the text.
To complete our application, we need to
make the buttons do something. Add the
following to the Add button.
Add the following to the Remove button.
Run the application again.
We can now add, edit and remove items
from our C++ model.
[Music]