This is the video 5.3 of communicating with Qt Which covers Qml Types and Modules. In this video, we're
going to cover: creating Qml types, creating Qml modules and finishing up with the finding Qml modules
and types from C++.
So if we change into our project and look at our "main.qml" right now we've got 130 lines of code
with no real logical breakdown of what's going on here.
So someone else who is trying to make changes has to currently read all 130 lines in order to understand
what's going on.
That's a little rude to whoever comes in behind us.
So let's go ahead and break this code up into chunks.
Let's start by breaking our dialogue into its own object type using a new file.
So we go to File, New File or Project, Qt and then we'll go to QML File. Click Choose. We're going
to go ahead name this the "ColorChangeDialog" and then hit Next and then hit Finish.
Now we need to delete and move all of our dialog code over.
So let's go and do that.
And then we need an indented one.
And then lastly we need to get our imports. So go to the top.
All three of these will be snagged. Perfect.
So the last thing, go ahead and remove this "id" property while we're at it so that we can define it
when we're using our new type. we'll change back to our main document, scroll down to the bottom here
and just recreate our "ColorChangeDialog" using its type name which is "ColorChangeDialog" and go and
set the "id" here and that's it.
Types define this manner are automatically available to all other Qml files within the same directory
which is super easy.
Now eventually you're going to have some Qml code that you want to share between two projects.
Right now we only know how to define a type from within the same directory.
So in order to share code between the two projects we'd have to copy the file over in both projects.
And as we made changes in one of those projects it wouldn't automatically get changed into the other
which is bad.
So this is where modules come into play when we're sharing Qml types between different projects.
Now to create a new module we need three things.
First a new directory which is a folder for your windows types.
Second a new Qml type located in the directory we just mentioned.
It's probably easier to think of a new Qml type as a new Qml file because that's typically how
they're defined.
So to reiterate the second thing that we need is a new Qml file.
Lastly slash Thirdly we need a qmldir there which is a special text file located in our new directory.
So let's go out and create a new module and to do this we will go ahead and create a new directory.
First, let's go to File, New file or Project, Qt, we will do a QML File.
Click Choose, and then the first thing will do is to go to this Path and select Browse, go to where you want
to create our new directory.
And we'll actually create two files, so the first is going to be called the "imports" folder.
And once we have our "imports" folder, we're going to create another folder, which we are going to call
"blue_elephants", which is going to be the name of our module. Now, we'll go ahead and select OK and then we'll
select our "blue_elephants" file or directory as our path and then we want to create our actual Qml file
which is the second piece and will go to name this "MyModuleType" because again this is our new type
and it's in our new module which is going to be named "blue_elephants".
So we hit Next.
And then one thing is we want to make sure that we don't add it to our current project. So, we're going
to change this to "None".
And keep that version control if you want or not, doesn't matter and click Finish.
And then in our actual new "MyModuleType", let's go ahead and create a function here.
Just a simple hello world that logs out.
And then we'll just call this function whenever the object is instantiated by using the "onCompleted"
handler. Perfect. So, we've created our new folder or directory, we've created our type.
The last thing that we need is the Qml.
So go to File, New File or Project and then we just need "General" here and create an empty file because
Qml is just an empty file.
Here we want to make sure that we're still in our "blue elephants" path which you can see from here.
And then the name and you must get this correct.
It's qmldir and we hit Next.
Let's make sure this isn't part of our project, since this will be in a separate, its own little project
there and we hit Next.
And then we'll go ahead and name our module, which is the module name here and the module name of the
folder must be the same thing so since it's called blue_elephants the folders called blue_elephants.
Our module name in Qml will be "blue_elephants".
And then we need to actually name the type, define a version number before defining the file name.
So we've only got one type which is my module type.
So let's go ahead and define the type, the version number and the file name.
So this is going to be the type name in our module.
This is the version which is 1.0 and then this is the actual file name.
So I deliberately didn't match these names to show you where you can customize.
Typically instead of naming you'll keep the actual same name.
So "MyModuleType" would be the actual type name that you declare here
and the file name, but I just wanted to show your customisation that's possible in case that's useful
for you.
Now that's all we need for our actual modules.
So we have created the directory, we've created an actual type which is MyModuleType and we created
the qmldir file.
So let's go ahead and import this into our project here.
So you need to go to the "main.cpp" and the first thing we're going to do is to add the module to the import path.
There are multiple ways to do this but we're going to add it using the "engine".
Now this is important.
We need to add the absolute path to the parent directory to the module not the module itself.
So instead of passing in the absolute path to the blue_elephants directory, we're going to pass in the
absolute path to the parent directory of the blue_elephants directory.
So if you followed along with me right that'll just be the import path.
So going to cheat here quick and go ahead and snag that
and we can add this to the "engine" using the "addImportPath" method. Awesome.
So now if we change to our Qml code and go to the top we can now import our blue_elephants module.
Note that we will have to provide the version number that we want which in our case will be 1.0 and then
let's scroll all the way to the bottom and go ahead and instantiate this.
And that's all we need.
Note that this just brushes the surface of what's possible.
Qml modules and I encourage you to dig further.
I would also say with some painful experience the importing of Qml modules is not very robust.
So if you have an error within the code in your module you're likely to import error rather than what
is actually wrong with your module.
So just be careful with that.
The last thing that we want to do is go ahead and create a new type from our C++ code.
So how do we do that.
Well if we look at our "colorpicker" code, we can see an example of how to integrate C++ code into our
Qml code.
So notice a couple of things here with this header file.
The first is that we're subclassing
"QQuickPaintedItem".
This class allows us to use the Qt raster engine to create some of our graphics by overriding the
paint function.
The other thing to note in this class is the use of the macro
"Q_INVOKABLE". In order to expose method Qml we need to either decorate our functions with the
"Q_INVOKABLE" macro, make them public slots or use the properties macro for this particular code.
The easiest thing to do was just to use the "Q_INVOKABLE".
Now note if you do want to extend some C++ code into Qml you don't actually have to subclass the
"QQuickPaintedItem". Any subclass of queue object will do. So,
Once we have our implementation finished we just need to navigate to wherever we instantiate the
QML application engine and call "qmlRegisterType".
So we'll go ahead and pass into that function.
The namespace, version and type number.
So let's go ahead and do that right now.
Note that we've already been using this code as part of the implementation.
So if we change into our color dialog "ColorChangeDialog" you can see the actual module name that we've
defined in our "main.cpp" so we defined the module name here as "ColorPicker" and the type as actual
"ColorPicker".
So again if you change and you'll see "import ColorPickers 1.0".
So let's go ahead and hit Play and make sure we get everything correct.
Now see that we actually got our "hello world!" so our module was correctly imported and use just as expected.
So with that we successfully generated and demonstrated how to create Qml type and module from
C++,
In addition to creating a new Qml module as well as demoing how to create a new Qml type.
Join us in the next section where we cover Visual Representations.