This is video 5.2 communicating with Qt Which covers signals and slots in this video.
We're going to cover C++ signals to QML Slots, QML signals to QML slots before finally finishing
up with QML signals to C++ slots.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Now we're going to start with the least amount of code we have to write and then go to the most.
So the least amount of code we need to write is to connect an already existing C++ signal to a
QML slot.
So go ahead and do that.
Our photo model is going to have two types of data changed events.
One where we change a single index and one or we change the entire model.
So let's set up something to tell us which is which.
So we're going to go ahead and define a function called my data change slot and we're going to do this
oncompleted signal as part of our list view.
So those three variables that we're going to take in an upper index a lower index and the rolls which
is what the signal is going to give us.
And we want to do two things.
So if we are only have one index that we're changing we want to go ahead and log that.
And if we have two indexes that are changed go ahead and log that as well.
Perfect.
So once you've got that slot defined Let's go ahead and connect that up in the signal that we're going
to connect it to is our data change signal on our model and we'll just call the connect method on the
data change signal perfect So that's an example of connecting a C++ signal to a QML slot.
Notice that QML slots are literally just javascript functions so we just defined a new javascript
function and then went ahead and connected that up.
So how do we connect QML signal to a QML slot.
Well we first need to define a Khumalo signal.
Note that while javascript is a weakly type, our signals are actually strongly type.
So as part of the signal definition we are going to have to define argument types in addition to the
argument.
Let's go ahead and create a new request for new colors which is going to be our signal in QML.
And now we're going to find this in the roots here and going to say signal then request new
colors and then we'll type pass in our type which is going to be a stream type and then we'll pass in
our unit which we're just going to call our urgency and it's how you define a QML signal.
So with our signal and with QML in general things are likely to go wrong at some point.
So when we're doing QML to QML connections Let's go ahead and connect our signal to some working
on the QML side, to the window we're passing to the C plus plus side.
So we'll set up a signal function that logs the signal that we emmit and we'll go ahead and call this
log_the_urgency it's going to take in one urgency which is actually the urgency in you know we're just
going to call console.log perfect and then we'll go ahead and connect this up and we'll use the
onCompleted callback again to get that set on and we'll just use the connect method and pass in our
function that we want to connect to.
There we go when we've successfully connected our QML signal to our QML slot which is just
a javascript function.
So now that we've done that let's go ahead and wire up a QML signal to a C++ slot.
Specifically we've got this request new colors signal that we defined so we want to connect it to the
corresponding slot which we've actually implemented in our photo models.
If you look here we've got a public slot which is randomized Corelli's.
So you want to go ahead and connect our request news colour's signal up to our randomized color value
slot.
Now one thing that we did is we went ahead and defined the signal at the roots and it's very important
that we do that because it makes it easier to access on the C plus plus side.
So the first thing that we need to do is go ahead and get a reference out to our root object and we'll
do that using the engine the Cucumis application engine that we created earlier has a root objects and
we'll go ahead and grab out an instance of the first one.
So are root objects is actually a list.
And so we go ahead and grab the value of the first one which is actual Our root object.
Now our signal is already connected to this root object so the signal that we defined are requests new
colors is actually already attached to this Root objects.
The only thing that we need to do is go ahead and connect it just like we would to any other C++ signal
and slot.
Now one thing is we have to use the old style signal and slot connection connections that's a little
bit more verbose but that's the same thing.
Awesome.
Now one thing to note is that we need to actually pass in the typesetting interiors for our custom colors.
What are you doing here.
You.
But the last thing actually isn't going to.
We're not handling the urgency value currently.
So we're currently just calling this but the urgency is going to be dropped here in our handling.
But that's how we've successfully connected up our signal to our slot.
The only thing that we're missing is we haven't actually emitted our signal here requesting the colors.
Let's go ahead and do that.
And what we're going to do here is if you look at this list view code we get as part of our actual header
value.
So we created a header.
It's a rectangle.
It's got a high to 50 and width the parent.
And we've got a couple things here.
We've got a timer and a MouseArea.
So if we click the mouse area you can see that we actually call this change_header_text() function which all
it does is tells our user that we're going to go and change the color and then sets our timer equal
to running and our timer whenever it's triggered.
We're going to go ahead and admit our request new colors signal and we'll go in passing and urgency
which to say we want that to happen now.
And then once that is actually finished that's going to go ahead and trigger or emit our signal and
is going to pass everything in.
So let's go ahead and run this now.
Perfect.
You see at the top here we've got our new header that we've created which has just says clicking the item
changes color.
And if we click this top one says it's changing the colors now.
And you see we have successfully changed all of the colors in our list so every time we click that we
go ahead and do that and you see that we've got our debugging enabled right so our function which actually
allowed us to see if we've changed many indexes go ahead and fires.
And so saying to index of change we say many indexes change.
And then you can also see if we click and change a single value you'll only get one index change.
So with that we've successfully learned how to connect C++ signals to QML slots, QML signals
to QML slots and QML signals to C++ slots, so join us next time and we cover how to define QML
types and modules.