In this lecture, we're going to look at
FontDialog, a dialog that allows you to
choose a font and use it somewhere in your application.
Let's go to Qt Creator and play with this.
Here we are in Qt Creator.
We're going to create
a new project as usual.
We call it 'FontDialogDemo',
save it in a location on our drive,
choose our Qt Version, choose our desktop kit,
and we are here. We want to 'import'
'QtQuick.Dialog', let's import 1.3.
We also want to 'import' 'QtQuick.Controls'
because we want to use a button control also,
so we're going to say '2.4', the
last version we have available as of now.
We change the title here to say
'FontDialog Demo' and we put a 'Column' here, inside.
You must be familiar with this already.
'spacing' 's going to be 20.
Why not?
it's going to be in the center and
inside we want to have a 'Button' control.
The 'text' is going to say 'Change Font'.
It's going to be  in the centered horizontally
so we're going to say this.
'parent.horizontalCenter' and when it's clicked,
we want to start a dialogue. Okay we're
going to say 'fontDialogId'. Okay we
don't have this dialog yet, but we're
going to have it and this is going to work.
Down here we want to put a 'Text' component.
Its 'ID' is going to be 'textId',
the 'text' is going to say 'Hello World'.
And down here we want to have a 'FontDialog',
ID is going to be 'fontDialogId',
the 'title' 's going to say 'Choose Font'.
I want to give it a default font of
this one. Okay this is how I specify it.
I use the Qt global object and I pass in
the font that I want to say. I hope you
remember this from the Qt global
object. And you can see that. This is a
grouped property, you can specify many
things on this font. This is going to be
the default font, that is shown when we
open this dialog here. Okay when it is
accepted, we also want to know and we
want to know, when it is rejected too.
On rejection, we want to say 'console.log' and
when it is accepted we say 'console.log',
say the font that was chosen and we say
it like this. We also want to take the
font and set it as the font property for
the text here. So we're going to say
'testId.font' equals 'fontDialogId.font'.
Okay the font that the user selects is
going to be available in the font here.
I think we can run the application now and
see how it behaves. If you click the button,
you see that you have a window
here to choose the font. We can choose a
font.
Okay let's increase the size here, make
it 48 for example and choose my favourite
font, which is 'Consolas'. Let's see if we
can find it. 'Consolas' is here. If I hit 'OK',
you see that the font here changed.
This is really how you use the font
dialogues and you can then capture the
font and set it to other UI components
that have the font property like we did
here for the 'Text' component. This is all
I've to say in this lecture. In the next
one we're going to see how you can use
MessageDialog to pop up some messages
for the user. I'll see you there