In this lecture, we're going to look at
the ColorDialog component. It is a
Dialog that allows you to choose a color
and use it somewhere in your application.
We're going to go to Qt creator and
play with this. Here we are in Qt
creator, we're going to go to the
documentation and type in ColorDialog.
You see that they suggest multiple
places where we can find this UI
component. We don't want to choose Qt
Labs Platform, we want to choose Qt Quick
Dialogs. We go in there, click on More
to see the description, and you see that
we can use this to select a color. The
Dialog is initially invisible. You need
to set the properties as desired, then
set visible-check to true or call open.
This is how you use it, you define it
like this. When it is accepted - when the
user confirms the color that they want,
you know it in the onAccepted signal
handler. And when it is rejected - when the
user doesn't choose anything with this
ColorDialog, you know in this signal
handler here. And if you go up, you're
going to see a few properties. You have
the color property, which is used to
store the color that the user has
selected, this is the confirmed color. We
also have currentColor, which is the
color that the user has selected but
hasn't confirmed yet. We are going to
create a project and play with this.
Click File, New File or Project. It is an application,
a Qt Quick one. We call it
ColorDialogDemo, store it in a location on
our drive and use this as the default
project location. You can choose this if
you want, click Next, choose the QT
version, and we want to use the desktop
kit for this. This is our project here,
we want to change the title here to say:
ColorDialog Demo and import Qt Quick
Dialogs.
You see that the import they
suggest is 2 but the latest one is
3 as far as I know. So
we're going to put the
rectangle inside here and the user is
going to click a button to pop up a
Dialog to let the user choose a color,
and we are going to use that color as
the color of the rectangle.
I am going to put in a Column component,
the spacing is going to be 20, and it is
going to be centered in the parent. We
are going to have a Button on top and
for having access to Button,
we need to import Qt Quick
Controls. So we say: QtQuick.Controls,
let's choose 2.4 and it is recognized. We
give it the text that is going to show.
You're going to say: Choose Color. It is
going to be centered, and when it is
clicked, we want to know and do something.
Down here we're going to put a Rectangle
component. We want to put a bunch of
properties inside. Click Ctrl A, Ctrl I
to align. It has a width and height and
id. The color of the border is black and
it has a width. It doesn't have any color
set for now, so it is going to be white
by default. We also want this rectangle
centered, so we can copy this and put
that down here, kill this space to make
things a little bit nicer. And down here
we're going to put a ColorDialog, we're
going to give it an id,
we’re going to give it a title. These are
the properties that you can check in the
documentation. We're going to say: Please
Choose a Color. And when it is accepted, we
want to do something and we also want to
do something when it is rejected. We want
to console log the color that the user
chose. We're going to say: console.log. We
want to output the color that the user
chose, it is going to be stored in the
color property. We also want to do an
experiment and say onCurrentColorChanged
and say: console.log(“Current color changed”).
When the Dialog is
accepted, we want to set the color that
the user chose as the color for this
rectangle here. So we're going to say:
rectangleId.color = color. This is
the color property of the Dialog here.
And when the user rejects the Dialog,
we don't want to do anything special, but
we want to log that so that we know in
our application, so we're going to say:
User rejected dialog.
I know you have a
temptation to run the application and
see how it looks, but if you click on the
button, nothing is going to happen
because we really didn't do anything in
here.
So we want to say:
colorDialogId.open. We want to open the
Dialog. Now you can run to see something
when you click on the button here. We see
the UI here, click on the button, you see
a Dialog that allows you to choose a
color. Notice what happen when we
choose a color, you see that currentColor
changed and I hope this shows the
point of the difference between currentColor
and color. color is the color that
the user has chosen. When you click
OK to choose this greenish color for
example, it is going to go in the
rectangle here. This is
the color property right now, but as long
as you haven't confirmed, what you are
changing is the currentColor. I
hope this makes sense. And when you click
OK, you see that your color is applied to
the rectangle here, and this is the
effect of what we did in the accepted
signal. We set that color property
to be the color of this rectangle here.
And this is really how you use a ColorDialog
to choose a color and use it in
your application. In the next lecture,
we're going to look at the File Dialog
UI component. I’ll see you there.