In this lecture, we want to look at the
MessageDialog component. You use this to
pop up messages for the user and let
them choose something by clicking a few
buttons that are available.
We're going to go to Qt Creator and play with this.
Here we are in Qt Creator, we are
creating our project. It's a Qt Quick Application.
We call it 'MessageDialogDemo',
save it in a location on our drive,
choose our Qt Version, choose your kit
and finish. We want to change the title
to 'MessageDialog Demo', 'import' 'QtQuick.Controls'
and 'import' 'QtClick.Dialogs'.
To save you some typing time, I'm going
to put in a piece of code I have
prepared, and try to explain it a little bit.
It's really simple.
So we have a button here. When you click it,
we open a dialog and this dialog is a
MessageDialog. It has an 'id', a 'title' and
the 'text' property that is going to be
shown in the message dialog. You can
specify the buttons for the user to
click. We want to have an 'OK' button and a
'Close' button and we want to know when
this dialog is accepted and rejected.
And if it's accepted we say something.
If it's rejected we also say something.
It's really this simple. We want to run the application
and see how it works.
It is a pop-up dialog that lets the user
know something about your application.
Click this button and you see it says
something. So this is the text property
that we specified in here. You see that
it says this piece of text here. When we
hit ok and accept, we have the message
from 'onAccepted', if we close we have a
message for 'onRejected' signal handler here.
And this is really all there is for
the MessageDialog. We can click F1 when
we have it selected, go to full help mode
and have more information about it.
This is all I had to say about the message dialog.
The next lecture we're going to
see how you can use your custom dialog
to have something, at least
usable on mobile devices. I'll see you there.