In this lecture, we're going to look at
the Application Window Control. Along the
way, we're going to look at menus, menu
bars and stack view. The Application
Window Qt Quick control gives you
ready-made spaces where you can stuff in
your content. You have a menu bar for
example, you have a header and you have
the footer, and you have the main content
area. If you look at what we have on the
right here, which is what we're going to word
in this course by the way, the file
edit hub thing here is the menu bar. In
the header, we have put these buttons.
These are really convenient buttons for
menus that are inside these file edit
help menus. We have the main content
which contains these rectangles here and
we have a footer which contains our
Tab bar. And to be able to navigate through
these pages, we are going to use a StackView,
and you're going to learn how to
use that too. We're going to go to
Qt creator and do all this. Here we are in
Qt creator, we are going to create
our project. It's Qt Quick Application.
We hit Next,
choose our Qt version, we choose our kit
and click Finish. We want to import Qt Quick
controls and we want to change the title
here to say ApplicationWindow Demo.
Let's put a space in here, go to the
documentation and look for this. If we go
to the description of this, it is a
window which makes it convenient to add
menu bar, header, footer and things
like this. And you have it here, this is
how you word it, and you have all these
components that you can work with: menu
bar, header and footer and you put in
some contents inside. This is exactly
what we're going to do in this lecture.
Let's go back to our code and change our
Window here to the ApplicationWindow,
and what we should do is come here to
speed up things a little bit.
We're going to copy all these things
because we're going to need them, so no
need to type them again. The Qt
documentation has done the job for us,
and we're going to fill in these
placeholders. Click Ctrl A, Ctrl I to align. But
before we go any further, I want to
explain a little more on the StackView.
I'm going to click F1, open in full mode, and
it basically is a component that can be
used with a set of inter-linked
information pages. It allows you to have
a stack of UI components as you see here,
and you can do many operations on them.
You can push new items to the stack, or
you can pop or remove items from the
stack. You're going to see how we use
this, I just want you to have an idea of
what we are using here. Let's close this
and work on our Menu bar. It is basically
going to contain menus. So our menu bar
here is going to contain three menus:
the File, Edit and Help menu. So we're going
to say Menu here, and you can learn more
on this by going in the documentation
yourself. It really is easy and you
probably know how to navigate the
documentation by now. A Menu can
have a title, so we're going to say File
here and the way you put content inside
in a Menu, you use an Action element. I am
going to put in an Action that I had
prepared. Type Ctrl A, Ctrl I to align. Let's go
to the documentation for it and you're
going to see that an Action represents
an abstract user interface action that
can have shortcuts and can be assigned
to menu items and toolbar buttons.
It basically is something you can have
in the Menu, in the toolbar and you can
have shortcuts for it. One of those
things for example is to copy
something, you can have a UI
component to allow you to copy in the
toolbar, you can have it in the menu and
you can have shortcuts for doing that.
So this is what we have here in our
code. It is an Action. This is a New, File
menu items that we’re going
to have. We can specify an icon for it,
and we can know when it is triggered.
When the user clicks on this Action in
the Menu, we're going to know. You
see that it also has an icon source
property. This is how you specify an icon
for it. I think this is a chance we have
to provide these icons. So I am going to
go to the Resources folder here, click Add New,
Qt, Qt Resource File,
I choose resource here. I add a
Prefix, you probably know how to do
all these. And I need to go where these
things are stored on my drive and add a
new Images folder. I am going to go in
the folder and paste in a bunch of
images that I had prepared. These are
the icons and you can see that it is a
set of different actions you can do in
your application. So what I want to do, I
want to come back to our resource file,
go inside this folder, select
everything in there and add it to our
resource file. I'm going to save and if I
come here, this file icon should be
available now. We want to add a bunch of
other actions that we're going to need.
So we have the New menu item, we have the
Open menu item, we have the Save menu
item and we have the Save as menu item.
Another thing you can do is separate
menu items in your Menu here. The way you
do that is you come here and put a
component called MenuSeparator, and
you put it here. there's going to be a
horizontal line separating these menus.
Let's add the last Action in this Menu,
which is the quitAction. Type Ctrl A,
Ctrl I to align, and you see that
when this Action is triggered, when we
click on the Quit menu item, we are going
to quit the application and you
recognize this Qt.quit method
from the Qt global object that we have
seen before.
This is our first menu, we need to
do the same for the Edit menu and Help
menu. I am going to put in those menus, I
have them prepared to save you some
typing. We're going to go down here and
put in those menus. Type Ctrl A, Ctrl I to
align. And you can see that it basically
is the same thing. I put these actions on
one line to have things readable a
little bit. And you see that we are using
qsTr to make this things translatable,
you can do that if you want.
Let's change the first Menu
here to be like the others. I’m going
to come here and change the title to say
this and change this to File. This
is the way to go, this is the way you do
it in a real application if you want it
to be translatable. This strings here
are going to be translatable in
different languages, but we're not going
to go deep into this subject in this
lecture. Now we have our MenuBar
complete, the next thing we want to focus
on is the ToolBar, and what we really
have to do is adding a bunch of buttons.
These buttons are going to be tool
buttons. We basically put them in like
this. We have a Row component and inside
we have ToolButton with a few
pre-selected actions that we have to the
top. These are the actions we want to
show up in the ToolBar. We have the New
we have the Save, Save as and Quit action.
If you go up, you can find all these
actions where we define them here and we
give them IDs. The next thing we want to
do is to adding the pages that we are
going to navigate through, and this Stackview
component here. So we're going to go
to this qml qrc file, that's where we
want to add them so that they are with
the other qml files. Click Add New, Qt, QML File.
We call this Page1.
We change this import to say Qt Quick
2.11 because that's what we are using
here. If you come to the main qml file,
you can see it, and we want to have a
rectangle component inside, and we want
its color to be green for example. We
want to do the same to have three pages.
So click Add New, Qt, QML file, it's going to
be Page2, hit Next, we finish this. We
come to Page1, we copy it and we
paste it here, and we say this should be
red. Come back here, click Add New, Qt, QML file,
it's going to be page3. And we
paste in our thing here which is going
to be blue. We have our pages, now we
can come back to our main QML file and
work on our StackView. It is going to
fill the parents so they did this for us.
We want to give it an id and stack id,
and if you go to its documentation, let's
see if we can find StackView, you
see that it has a property called
initialItem. It holds the initial
item that should be shown when the Stackview
is created. So we want to assign
Page1 to this property, we show it
like this. And in our footer, we're going
to have a TabBar that is going to allow
us to navigate through all these pages.
The way we do that is we give this TabBar
an id
and we want it's width to be the same as
the parents’ width. Inside we want to have
a few tab buttons, so we're going to say
TabButton. The first one is going to say
qsTr(“Page1”),
and we want to do something when it is
clicked. The first thing we want to do is
to take something that is on top of the
stack and remove it, and we do that by
calling the pop method. And we want to
put the Page1 component so that it is
shown on this stack and we put on the top of
this stack immediately, and we do that by
saying mStackId.push. And we want to
give it what to show, the way we refer to
what is in the qrC file here. You
say qrC and you say Page1.qml
because that's what we want to be shown
when this TabButton is clicked. And to
make sure that our thing is working here,
we are going to console log the number
of items in the stack. We're going to say
console.log(“Number of items:…)
And it’s going to be the depth of the stack.
You can look at this depth property in
the documentation. When you click this
button, we're going to pop whatever is on
the top of the stack, and we are going to
push the item that we want to put in
there. In this case, it is going to be
Page1.qml here. We want to repeat what we
just did here and do it for all the
items, the remaining two. So we copy and
paste, here we say Page2. Number 3 is
going to be easier now, and here it is
going to be 3. And here it is
going to be 2,
here it is going to be 3. And ladies
and gentlemen we have everything in
place to test our Application Window thing,
and now it is convoluted there is a lot
of information. Now we're going to run it
and I'm going to try and explain it
again, and I hope you're going to
understand it a little more better.
we have our application here, ignore this
thing for now, and we can click to
navigate through the pages. The
first page is green, red, blue, which is
what we specified in here: page 1 is
green, page 2 is red, page three is blue. And we
have menus to the top here. If you click
on File, you’re going to see New, Open, Save,
Save As. If you come back to our code, the
File menu has New, Open, Save, Save us.
You basically specify
things you want to have in the Menu bar.
I want to have the File menu, this
menu here. I want to have the Edit menu,
which is this menu here. I want to have
to Help menu, which is this menu here. And
if you come back to our application, you
see these menus here, the File/ Edit menu. The
way you put things inside, you use
actions. This is our Action and a few
properties inside, and it really is the
same thing. The MenuSeparator here, I
hope you saw it. You can see it is
this line here, then we took
a set of predefined actions and put them
in the ToolBar. You have the new
Save/ Save As/ Quit actions in the ToolBar
and it is what we have down here in the
header.// We have a toolbar and we
define ToolButton and passing the
actions that are going to be in here. And
by now, I hope you see that the
flexibility of the Action item is that
you can use it in multiple places. We
define it here in the menu bar and we
are using it in the header component
here, through these tool buttons. An
Action can be used in many
places in your user interface and the
logic that you defined on that action
for example here, the logic that is going
to happen when you trigger this action
is to quit the application. We can
quit the application from the File menu
and we can quit the application from the
tool bar by clicking on this ToolButton
here. And we have to prove what we just
said, we're going to come to File here,
click, you see that the application dies.
We start it again, we click on the Quit
action here in the toolbar, the
application quits.
And the
rest is really specifying the icons in
the Resource folder and making sure they
are available when you pass them to the
actions to be shown like this. And this
is really all there is to working with
the Application Window. You work with it
when you want to take advantage of this
menu bars and toolbars and footer
locations. And you're going to see it’s mostly
used with the stackview component because
it allows you to navigate through pieces
of user interfaces defined in different
components like this, and it makes it
very easy to do. If you go back to the
Help, you're going to see there is a
bunch of methods that you can work with
with the stack view and you can learn
more about them by clicking on each one
of these. This is all I had to say in
this lecture, I hope you enjoyed it. I'll
see you in the next chapter.