In this lecture we are looking at the
Drawer Qt Quick component. This is a
component that allows you to have a
sliding panel like this.
You see that when we click, it would have something
sliding again. A drawer allows you to
build something like this. So we're going
to create a new project in Qt creator
and play with this.
Click File -> New project -> Qt Quick Application.
We're going to call it “Drawer Demo”,
save it in the usual location, choose our
version of Qt and choose our kit, and
we're going to have a project here. We
should change this title to say “Drawer Demo”,
import our Qt Quick Controls. Let's
go down and change the last number, and
while we are here, we should import
Qt Quick layouts because we're going to
need that. Layouts 1.4 is
available for us and another thing we
want to do is to change this to
ApplicationWindow. This is a
component that is available from Qt
Quick controls. We are actually going
to look at this in detail. If you want to
know more about it right now, you can
click on F1 and you're going to have a
bunch of things you can know about it. It
basically is a window which makes it
convenient to add menu bars, status bars
and things like that. We want to give an
id to our Window here, we're going to say
rootID and we want to change its
width and height so that it looks like a
mobile application. We're going to change
0:01:53.280,0:02:00.299
this to 520. We are going to specify a
header property for this Application
Window and we are going to put in a
Toolbar. The toolbar can contain a bunch
of things. We give it a height of 50, why
not? and we give it a
background: Rectangle. We give it a color:
mintcream. If you want to know what this
color looks like, just hover on top of it
and it looks like this. Inside the
Toolbar we are going to have a
Rowlayout component. It's going to have a
spacing of 20 and it's going to fill its
parent. Its parent happens to be this
ToolBar component here and inside we're
going to have a ToolButton component, a
thing that is clickable by the user, and
we're going to have a little piece of
text. The ToolButton can also have a
background. We're going to change it to
the same background as the “ToolBar” so
that things look the same. It also
supports providing an image that is
going to be shown in that “ToolButton”
and you provide that through the icon
source group property and we are going
to specify the path to the image here. So
what I want to do is to add in another
resource file. You already know how to do
this.
So I'm going to go pretty quick. I call
it resource, hit Next and add it here.
I am going to add a prefix and take
out everything because I want my files
to be where they are, and I am going to
show this in an Explorer to open where my
project is stored on my drive. You can do
the same thing or similar thing on a Mac
and Linux computers. I am going to create
a new folder in here and call it images, and
I am going to open it and put in an
image that I had prepared. I'm going to
come back to my resource file and add
files, and if I go in, I am going to see
my drawer image provider. I want to save
this
and if I go back in the toolbar of ours,
I can say “images/ drawer.png” and I
am going to have my icon here. I also
want to know when this ToolButton is
clicked so I'm going to say console.log
Toolbutton clicked and we are going to do
something else. So we are going to
open the drawer, let's flag this here.
Now we should put some information in
the label here. I am just going to paste
in some code that I have and I am going
to try and explain it. ctrl A -> ctrl I to
align. It basically is a label and it has
some text to show and a few properties,
and we want this Label component to fill
any word that is available in this
RowLayout component. Now that we have our
ToolBar, which is slightly complicated to
be honest, we should provide our Drawer
component, I'm going to say “Drawer” and we
should look at this documentation to see
what they have to say about it. So we say
Drawer provides the
swipe-based side panel, similar to those
often used in touch interfaces to
provide a central location for
navigation. This is what it is and they
have it here. So we should give it an ID
we call it “drawerId”.
Its width is going to be the
minimum. So we're going to say Math.min
We can do this from JavaScript
if you remember and it's going to be
the minimum between the width and the
height of this Application Window
element. We want to take into account if
the user interface is rotated.
That's why we're doing this. So we're
going to say: rootId.width, rootId.height
So we want to
have the minimum of these two things and
make the width of this drawer equal to
two-thirds of them.
The height is going to be the same
as the root element. So we're going to
say rootId.height and we want it to be
interactive. We want the user to interact
with it. Now that we have the drawer,
we need a way to lay out components
inside of it. We defined it, now we
want to put some content inside. If you
remember what we had when we started
this lecture, we had a few buttons inside
the drawer so we're going to do the same.
We're going to put a ColumnLayout.
Spacing is going to be 20 and
we want it to fill its parent which is
this drawer here and inside we can put
in a few buttons. I'm going to put in the
first one. Control A -> control I to align.
It basically is a normal button. It has
the width of its parent, it's hard to
hide, it says item 1. It has a font size,
It has a color for the background. It
basically isn't nothing you haven't seen
already and we are going to copy it and
paste it a couple of times. So we're
going to paste it here and paste it here
again. The second one is going to say
Item2, the color is going to be “yellowgreen”.
You can put in whatever you want.
“Clicked on item2”. The third one is going
to say Item3, the color is going to be
dodgerblue
and it says Clicked on item3.
And you see that whenever we click on
any of these buttons, we close the drawer.
Let's go back and see that we call it
drawer. We should say drawerId.close
và lặp lại.
Copy, paste and paste here. So we
should go back to the ToolButton for
the ToolBar here and when we click, we
want to open the drawer, so we should say
drawerId.open and before we run the
application, I know you want to run to
see what is available, but we need to
provide the main content for our user
interface and you put it in the root
element right here. So when you run
the application, the drawer is not going
to be visible. It is invisible by default.
You show it by calling the open method
and you hide it by calling the close
method. Our main content is going to be
nothing but the good old Rectangle, it's
going to fill the available width and
height, and it's going to have this color:
lightsteelblue. And if you want to see
what it looks like,
0:10:06.430,0:10:11.320
hover over it and you're going to see
this. Now I think we are ready to run
this thing and see what it looks like.
We have our thing here, if we click
here, you see that our drawer opens and
it says Toolbutton clicked. If we click
on item one, the
drawer closes and you see the same
0:10:30.100,0:10:36.640
effect if you click on any of the
buttons in here. The only problem is that
we have too much space between the
elements in here. So we're going to go
back to our code and examine what we
have in our drawer. We basically don't
want it to fill the parent. We want it to
have the same width as the parent. So
We're going to say width: parent.width and
let's put this spacing at 0. Let's see
what we get. We have our app here.
Click here and you see that this is what we
set out to do. Click and you see the
drawer goes away and if you click in the
Tool button here, you see that the drawer
opens. And you can close it by clicking
outside of it as well. We can do
something more interesting when we close
it. We can actually change the color of
this rectangle here. So we're going to
give an id: contentRectId and when
we click, before we close the drawer,
we're going to say contentRectId.color,
change this to red for the first
button, change it to green for the
second button, let's steal that, and
change it to blue for the third button.
Let's run and see if our thing works. We
have our application, click on first item and
the background turns red, green. Click
again, and blue. And ladies and gentlemen
this is how you work with a Drawer
component. In the next lecture we're
going to look at the Spin box QT quick
control. I'll see you there.