In this lecture, we'd like to see how you
can upword custom dialogues that look
decent enough to be used on mobile
devices. This time we're going to do
something a little bit different than
we've been doing all along. I want you to
come to the Welcome tab here in Qt Creator,
I want you to come here
in the search tab and type in "Gallery",
and you're going to have a few example
applications in here. I want you to click
on this one, the greenish one. We're going
to run it and see what we can learn from
it. Okay, you are going to see it opened
here. I want you to close this window
here, and you're going to see a configure
project message here. It is basically
wanting you to configure the kit for
this project here because we can click
on it and directly run it into to Qt Creator,
I am going to choose the desktop kit
but I do recommend to run this on a
mobile device because it really looks
good there. Now that I have my kits
selected, I'm going to configure project.
And it's going to configure stuff. You
see that we had a few errors and now
they've gone away because Qt has done
the configuration for us. You're going to
see a new project open here on the Left,
it's called the gallery. If you go in,
you're going to find resources. If you
go down here, you see the resources. This
is where we have our qml files, but I
don't know why Qt creator is not
showing the contents of the qml files.
But no worries, we can actually click on
the gallery.cpp file here, show in
Explorer. We're going to open where it is
located and we're going to see a folder
called
pages here, which contains different
pages that we can show. I want you to run
this application. And you see that we
have an application like this. It is a
good one. Okay, you see that if you click
on this then you see a drawer come up
here, and they have a bunch of buttons
that you can click to do the
different things. For example, we can show the
group box here. They basically showcase
different Qt Quick Controls that you can
use in here. We have seen a lot of this
things if not all. But what I want you to
see now is the dialogue because they
have pretty good dialogues that we can
learn from. Click on dialogue here and
they have a few things that you can try.
Click on message here, it shows a
dialogue with a message, this is pretty
good for mobile devices. Click on
confirmation here, you have a dialogue. It
has a title, it has a message and you can
let the user check some boxes like this,
and you can accept or reject the
dialogue. We have content dialogue that
you can use to show some content and let
the user scroll. The user can close this
when they are done with it. And we have
another one that can collect user input.
I think these dialogs look very good and
we're going to try them in our
application. But before we try them we
need to see the source code that is
generating them. The way we see that,
unfortunately, this is not opening up in
Qt Creator but we can go there
ourselves and find this things. Click on
gallery.cpp here, show in explorer, go in
pages inside here, and you're going to
say a file called dialog page. I want you
to open it with an editor of your choice
you can actually open it with Qt Creator,
I guess, you can choose an
application that you want to open it
with. I chose Qt Creator here and it's
going to open here. What we want to see
is how these buttons are generated. You
see we have a Label here that says
dialogue blah blah blah. We have a button
here, and this generates our dialogue.
Okay, when you click you open this
dialogue here. so what we can do is copy
these things and adapt them to be run in
our own application. so I am going to
keep this dialogue page open here, keep
it open,
I can close gallery here because
we don't need it anymore, and create a
new project. It's going to be Qt
Quick Application, we're going to call it
CustomDialogDemo, save it in a location
on our drive. Hit "next",
the usual thing really, choose the QT
version, choose the desktop kit, and
"Finish". Okay, we have our project here. We
want to say Custom Dialogue Demo. We also
want to do our imports. We want to import
QtQquick.controls and QtQquick.Layouts
because we're going to use those as well.
We want to put in a column component.
This spacing is going to be 40 and it's
going to be the same width as its parent,
so we're going to say "parent.width" here.
What we want to do is to go to dialogue
page here and copy these two components,
this label here and this button here. We
select, copy this, come back in main.qml
and put them here. This is a column
component so things are going to be laid
out from top to bottom. We're going to
see this label here and this button, and
when we click this button, this dialogue is
going to pop up. One thing you see is
that we have a property that is not
defined, this button width property is
not defined, and if we run without having
it defined, we're going to run into
problems. so we can come to the top here
and say "property int"  and say "buttonWidth"
It is called like that, buttonWidth.
I think it is true and we want to make
this 300. Another thing you might do to
improve security, you can make this
readonly in Qt and you can do that.
You can make it readonly, you can do
that. Okay, we have our thing here. so we
have our label, I don't think there's
much to say about the Lable, you're ready
how to work with that. But the button
here, it has a text that is going to be
shown in. It's going to be this width and
when it's clicked, we're going to open
this dialogue here that we defined. And it
has an Id. Okay, so look at the position
we gave it here, we really want to Center
it in the parent. The dialog has also a
title and it has a label inside. Let's
run the application and see what it
looks like now. Okay,
you see we have this thing here. If we
click here, you have your message here.
This is very easy to do and we just
learned this from a Qt example. The
next button is going to be a
confirmation button. We want to capture
it and copy it. We go to
main.qml which is here, go below the
button that we had for message and paste
them the confirmation button. Okay, it has
a width as well, we have this dialogue that
we open, and we have a few properties for
this dialogue here. We can run it, click
on confirmation, and you see the title
here, they say a text here, and we have a
checkbox in here. Down below we have two
buttons yes and no. If you click yes, it's
going to accept. If you click no, it's
going to reject. Let's see what we have
in here. This is how you specify the
buttons. Okay, you say standardButtons
and you pass in these values here. We
want to have a yes button and the no
button. This is how you specify the
content inside the dialogue. We have this
label here, we have this checkbox here,
and the buttons are going to be below
these components that you specify in
here. And the dialog is also going to be
centered in the parent. We want to go to
dialog page again and look at the next
piece of content we
have. so we want to copy this button here,
come back to main.qml, go below this
button here, paste it in. Okay, this is a
pretty long one. We give it a close
button like this. It is a modal dialogue,
Inside, we have applicable component
because we want to be able to scroll to
see all the content inside the dialogue.
Notice that we specified the content
height property here. This is because we
might have more content to display than
our window could possibly display, so
we're going to have to scroll through
the content to be able to see everything
in there. so we have a Flickable, that is
going to allow us to flick through the
contents. Inside, we have a column
component that contains an image and a
label with some text. so we need to
provide this image here, and the way I'm
going to do that, I'm going to add it as
a resource file. so I'm going to select
the project here, and say add new. It's
going to be Qt Fesource File. I'm
going to say resource here, I'm going to
add the prefix and take it out
because I want to not use a prefix. I
want to go where my main.qml file
is stored we've been doing this quite a
lot. And I want to add in an images
folder. I am going to open this folder
here and put in my logo here that I'd
prepared. It is called LearnQtLogo,
so I'm going to come back to our project
and select add files, put in images and
I'm going to find my local in there. I'm
going to save this, come back to main.qml,
not main.cpp and here I'm
going to say "images...
LearnQtLogo.png. Let's run this
so that you see what it is. Okay, we have
content here, and if we run, you see that
the button is not displayed correctly.
Why is that? Let's look at this error
here, 92, and it says page here is not
defined. We should change this to parent
because we don't have the page component
defined. And we want to display this
dialogue here in relation to its parent
which is the button here. Let's run again,
click this, and you see that we have our
content here. Okay, you can scroll to see
things. We can close and open it again. This
is the behavior you have. and in fact, this
dialog is usable on mobile devices. It
looks pretty decent. so we want to go
back to the DialogPage.qml file and copy
the last button that we have in there,
that's the one we're going to look at
right now. And it is a dialog that you
can use to collect data from the user. We
go down here, paste it inside, look and
see if we have no boo-boos inside. You
can't really see the skin mean. We
have to run it to see if it works, and
let qml catch the errors for us. Ok, it
looks like this. It has a title Input and
you can type in stuff, ok,
John Doe, for example, and you can
navigate through the tab key. This is
pretty design. And if you look at how
it's made, it's no different than what we
have seen before. We have a button, we
have a dialog inside. It is centered in
the parent. It has focus, it has a title
we have a bunch of
buttons that we can show in it, and we
have a layout that contains things we
want to see. Okay, this is a layout of our
own input fields, we have a label and we
have a text field for the username and
the text fields for the password.
It really is nothing fancy but it is
very usable on mobile devices. And I
thought it was a good idea to show you
this things.
I didn't want to type all these things. I
could have done that. But I wanted you to
have the information that you can go to
the examples here and find some useful
things you can even learn from and
learn things that I didn't even have a
chance to tell you about in this course.
Okay, this is really all I had to say in
this lecture. I hope you know how to
display good looking and useful
dialogues that you can use on mobile
devices. And in the next lecture, we're
going to look at the interesting subject
of Model View architecture using QT
quick. I'll see you there.