In this lecture, we are looking at FileDialog.
This dialog allows you to choose
files or folders from your file system.
Let's go to Qt Creator and play with that.
Here we are in Qt Creator.
We're going to create a new project. It's a Qt Quick Application.
We call it 'FileDialogDemo',
save it in a location on our drive,
hit next, choose the Qt Version and
choose our desktop kit. We are going to
change the title here to 'FileDialog Demo'.
We want to import QtQuick.Controls
because we are going to need to use a button.
We want to put a 'Column' component
as usual, 'spacing' is going to be 20. It's
going to be in the center and it's going
to contain a button control. The 'text' is
going to be 'Choose File or Folder' and it is going
to be centered horizontally and when it
is clicked, we want to know and do
something. Down below we want to put the
'Text' component.The 'text' is going to say
'User hasn't chosen yet' and here we're
going to show the path to the file or
folder that the user has chosen. By
default, we say this because the user
hasn't chosen yet. We want to set the
'wrapMode' to Text.Wrap. The next thing we
want to do is to import the Qt Quick
Dialog module. So we're going to say
QtQuick.Dialogs.
It's going to be 1.3 and down here we
can create one 'FileDialog'. The 'title'
is going to say 'Choose File or Folder'.
We want to give it an ID and we want to set
another property that is called selectFolder.
We want to set this to 'true' and
this says that this dialogue is going to
be used to only select folders.
We're going to see that you can set this to
false to allow the choosing of files.
We want to know when the user accepts the
dialog and when the user rejects the
dialog. We want to give the 'Text' a ID
and set the path to the chosen file as
the text property for the Text here when
the user accepts the dialog. So we're
going to say 'textId.text' equals 'fileUrl'.
Now when the user clicks this Button,
we want to open the file dialog. So we're
going to say open here and run the
application. And by now you might see a
pattern in how you use these dialogues.
It really is the same you define a
dialog component and when something
happens, when the user clicks a button,
for example, you open the dialog and you
go from there to do whatever you want to
do with the dialog. Our UI is here we can
click this button and you see that we
see a dialog like this. Okay let's go to
'D:' for example and choose 'artwork', choose
a folder and you see that the path to
the folder is stored in here. Let's try
to choose files with this dialog here.
You see that I go inside the folder but
I don't see any files inside there
because this one is set up to allow us
to
only choose folders. If you want to
choose files, you can come in here and
set this property to 'false' and run again.
Mm-hmm.... Choose file or folder, go in 'D:', go
in 'artwork', you're going to see the files
in here. I can choose one file, click OK.
You see that I have the path to that
file. I can also select multiple files I
guess. Let's try and select multiple now.
We can't we can only select one file but
if we close this and come back to file
dialog I think we can allow the user to
choose multiple files. Let's go there,
QtQuick Dialogs and let's see if we have a
property called 'selectMultiple'. Whether
more than one file name can be selected.
By default,
this property is false. We need to set it
to true to allow the user to choose
multiple files. So we can say selectMultiple,
set this to 'true', run again.
Click to 'D:', 'artwork' and we can hit Ctrl and
select multiple files and you can see
that we have a list of those things in
here.
If I open you see that there's nothing
inside fileUrl. That's because when you
have multiple files selected, the
affected property is not fileUrl as we
did here. It is fileUrls and let's do
that we're going to say fileUrls and
this is a list. Let's try this. We are
trying to assign a list to a text
property. Let's run.
Mm-hmm.... fingers crossed
We are going to 'D:', 'artwork', you select multiple
files in here. Let's do this and when we
do this, cannot assign a list
to a string. This is a problem. You cannot do that.
But if you want, you can do
something like 2, to set the second
file Url as the text property for this.
Let's run. Run the application, choose in
artwork, we're going to choose the first
image here, hold Ctrl down and choose a
few others and if we run you see that
the image number 4 is chosen because
it is at index 4 in our list of images.
And if you want to show all the files
that have been selected, I hope you
remember this. You can say
'for (var i = 0; i<fileUrls.length; i++)'  and say
'console.log'. Let's say "Value"+i+"is"+fileUrls[i]
and we pass in the index that we
are at in the loop. Let's run to see if
this works.
Choose file or folder, go in our
directory. You can go wherever you want
in your file system. I'm going to choose
this 5 qml and when I open you see
that 0 through 5, I have files selected
here. I can loop through this list of
file Urls and extract each path that is
stored in there.
And this is really how you use file
dialogue. You can use it to select files
and folders or you can use it to select
one or multiple files. This is all I had
for this lecture and the next one we're
going to see how you work with font dialog.
I'll see you there