In this lecture, we are looking at Qt
Quick Dialogs. Dialogs allow you to
show transient information, the kind of
information you want the user to see for
one or two seconds and let them choose
what they want to do with the
information. You can also use them to let
the user choose something, for example
they can use Dialogs to choose files
in the file system, they can use Dialogs
to choose colors, fonts and things like
that. Here we have a few classes we're
going to look at in this chapter. We're
going to look at the Dialog class,
which is the parent of all these
Dialogs: ColorDialog, FileDialog,
FontDialog and MessageDialog. They
allow you to do these things you see here
to the right. And if you go to the
documentation, you're going to find more
details on this thing here. Another thing
that should be noted is that these
Qt Quick Dialogs are part of the Qt Quick
Dialogs module as we're going to see.
And they are mostly meant to be used on
desktop platforms. We're going to see a
way you can use them on mobile devices
towards the end of this chapter, but
mostly you're going to be using these
Dialogs on desktop platforms. Now we're
going to look at some of the shared
properties between all these Dialogs. A
Dialog can be modal in that it blocks
the user to do something else until they
have closed the Dialog. The modality
can be application-wise in which you
block action in the entire application,
or it can be window-wise where you block
application in the entire window. In the
Dialogs that allow the user to choose
something, for example the File Dialog,
the Color Dialog, the Font Dialog, we have
these properties. For File Dialog, you
want to know the file that the user
choose or the files if they happen to
choose multiple files. You can also let
the user choose a folder, the same
happens for the color. Color holds the
color that was chosen by the user.
Current Color holds the color that the
user has chosen but hasn't confirmed yet.
You're going to see this. And the same
happens to Font and Current Font. A Dialog
is invisible
by default. To make it visible, you can do
one of two things: you can set the
visible property of it or you can call
the open method, which does that for you
in the background. To make it invisible,
you set the visible property to false or
you call the close method. And this is
all I have to spice up your appetite to
work with the Dialogs in Qt Quick. In
the next lecture, we're going to start
working with them and we're going to
start with the Color Dialog. I'll see
you there.