In this video we are looking at the SpinBox
Qt Quick control. This control
allows you to choose a number by
pressing the button. On the top one here,
you see that we can select a number by
pressing this little thing here and on
the bottom one here, this is a new look
from QT quick, and this is what we're
going to look at. You press the plus
button to increase and the minus button
to decrease, and you can capture these
values using any of the methods we have
seen before. We’re going to go to Qt
creator and play with this.
Here we are in Qt creator, we
create a new project as usual. Click
Qt Quick Application, we call it Spinbox Demo,
save it in the usual location and
hit Next, choose a QT version, we choose
our kit and finish. The first thing we
want to do is to import Qt Quick controls.
So we say import, go down here
and choose 2.4, and change the title
here to SpinBox Demo. We want to put a
column in here, spacing is going to be
20 and it's going to be the same width
as the parent. If we go to the
documentation and look at SpinBox, look
at the description, it says it is a
control that allows the user to choose
an integer value by clicking the up or
down indicator buttons, or by pressing up
or down on the keyboard. It looks like
this, and this is how you define it. We're
going to go back to our code and put in
a SpinBox. We give it an id. We say where
it starts from, it's going to start from
1 to 100, this is what we've been
doing all along. And the value is going
to start at 20, you can choose whatever
you like. We want it centered and we want
to know when the value changes. Let's run
and see what we have so far. You
see that we have our SpinBox control
here, the value is 20 by default, which we
specified. We can decrease by clicking on
the minus button here and you see that the
values change accordingly, and when we
press the plus button here the value
increases, and we are able to capture
that in our code. One thing you can
specify is the step size, which is the
increment that is going to happen each
time you click on the plus or minus
button. You specify that by using the
stepSize property. We can specify
5 for example. If we run again,
we are at 20. We click plus, it's going
to be 25. We click plus again, it's
going to be 30. We are incrementing and
decrementing by 5 every time we press
any button here. Another thing I want you
to see is that you cannot select inside
the spin box here and type a value. I am
doing that but it is not being
recognized. So if you want to do that, you
can set your SpinBox here to be
editable. So we say that and we set this
true, run the application and I can
now delete what is inside
and type 55 for example. Hit Enter and the
value is changed, and I can increase or
decrease. You can change the value
manually when you set this editable
property to true. The last thing I want
to do in this lecture is capture the
value here manually without waiting for
the onValueChanged signal. We have been
doing this a lot because it is more
convenient. When you need the value, you
capture it without waiting for a signal
here. It is very easy to do. We put a
Button here. We center it by using this
statement here. We copy it and put it
down here, and we want to give it a text
property, say: Capture value. And we want
to know when it is clicked at which time.
We're going to say: console.log The
current value in the spinbox is :” +
spinBoxId.value.
If we run, change the value in
here to 41, why not? We hit Enter to
change it, current value changes to 41, we
plus a little bit: 61. Click Capture value, the
current value is 61. You can capture it
and use it in your application. This is
really all I had to say about the SpinBox
Control, you can learn more about it
and its properties from here. There's
quite a bunch, so if you need them and
are interested, you can look at this and
look at what they do in the
documentation here. In the next lecture,
we're going to look at the Application Window component
from Qt Quick controls.
I'll see you there.