in this lecture we are looking at page
and table components but to make the
examples a little bit more fun we are
going to try use SwipeView component
again and have something pleasing to the
eye that the user can play with today.
Go to QT create or and play with us okay
here we are in QT create or before I
start any project I want to come to the
help here and look at the things we are
interested and I'm going to look at the
page component and if you look here it
is a container which makes it convenient
to add header and footer items to a page
okay you have a header here you have the
content and you have a footer if this is
what you are interested in the page
component is your thing okay you see
that we also have a couple of other
properties that we can use let's look at
the top bar component it provides a tab
based navigation model okay basically
like what we had in a page indicator but
now we are using tabs if you scroll down
here you see a better visual on what
tabs will look like and this is what
we're going to try so now let's create a
new project
it's a QT quick application we call it
page tab bar demo save it in the usual
location choose our QT version choose our
kit and finish we want to change this
title here and say page and something
like this and we want to import our QT
quick controls module
we are trying to build something like
this if the user has the ability to
swipe through user interface components
but down here you see that we have a tab
bar that the user can click on to move
to the location where they desire, it is
possible to use the tab bar like this.
Now that the destination is display,
let's start with our frame, We want
to add a page component, given ID
of page and we want it to fill the
entire parent inside we have a swipe
view component because we want the user
to be able to swipe through the UI
components. ID is going to be swipeViewId and
it's also going to fill the parent which
is going to be this page component here.
A page component must have a component
that is the main component inside and
this SwipeView explained that role for us.
Here the next thing I want to do is to
provide a footer, our footer is going to
be a tab bar component and we are going
to put some tabs inside, we want to give
it an ID as well and we want its current
index to be the same as the current
index for our swipe view component here
so we're going to say swipeViewId
a current index and we should come here
and do the same so current index is the
same as the current index as the tab bar
component now we want to put some
content in the tab bar so we're going to
say TabButton and we want to give it a
text property of first,
we're going to copy this two times
because we want to have three components
that we can show, this is going to be
second, this is going to be third, you can
do that and now we want to put something
inside the swipe view here I am going to
put in three image components and set
their source property to something we
are going to get all images from the
internet this time if you want to use
local images you already know how to do
that please check the swipe view and
page indicator lecture and in fact we
are going to use the same images we used
in that lecture so I'll copy and paste
this a couple of times and change the
names for these images like this and run
our application mm-hmm we have our thing
here and it should be loading the images
from the internet now okay you see our
image here click on second you see it
click on third you say that and they are
coming right from the Internet
but what I want you to focus on is that
this UI you see here is wrapped in a
page component and we don't have to do
any anchoring to have this top bar
displayed here we just use a page
component we give it the main widget to
show which is our SwipeView here
and then we specify a footer we just
specify the footer component but if we go
to the documentation for page component
you're going to see that it can also
take a header okay it can be any item so
let's look at the header here we can
actually copy this example and put our
header on top of our SwipeView here
okay we can change this text here
because we want some static text can we
say Page and TabBar Demo because
that's what we are working on, let's run
okay you see our header here is being
displayed if you want this you can use
it like this you can really put anything
here even if you want it you could put a
rectangle okay give it a width of parent
with give it a height Oh 50 and give it
a color of red for example and run and
you see our rectangle here header and
footer components are available to you
to put in whatever is if it to serve
your particular needs. This covers all I
had to say in this lecture it really is
simple to use a page component you just
have to provide the main component which
is the swipe view in this case and then
you can specify a header and footer
components and put in whatever you want
in the next lecture we are going to look
at the text area component I'll see you
there