in this lecture we are looking at the
SplitView Qt quick
control, this is a control that is only
available in a q-tip quick controls one
series because it really targets desktop
it allows you to split your user
interface into resizable pieces of
content let's go to QT creator and play
with us.
okay here we are in Qt creator we're
going to create our new project it's a
Qt Quick Application, we're going to
call it split view demo save it in the
usual location choose our QT version and
choose our kit finish if we go to the
documentation and search for split view
we're going to find the documentation
for it and I notice that the import is
one that they suggest for a QT 511 so
this says that it is from QT quick
controls one series and what it does is
allow you to design something like this
you have resizable pieces of user
interface and you can click on the
delimiter between the two components and
you're going to have an icon that
invites you to drag to resize your
content this is actually easier to show
that talked about so we're going to play
with us in our code if you go down here
they show an example of how you can use
this actually you know what we are going
to use this we are going to use this so
let's copy go back to our code and test
it then you see that there are some
things that are not recognized we have
split view is not recognized
we should import our QT quick controls
controls 1.4 this is the latest version
we can use now you see that layouts are
not also recognized so we're going to
import QT quick
layouts we can only import 1/3 and when
we do this you see that our errors go
away we should change this title to say
splitView demo and we can run our
application but before we run it let's
go through it we have a split view
component it is going to fill our window
here inside we have a few rectangles we
have the light blue rectangle the light
gray rectangle and the light green
rectangle okay they specify the maximum
width for this rectangle so you can't
extend it parent width this is what
it means we instruct the second
rectangle to fill the available width
and its minimum is going to be 50 inside
we have a text that is centered and the
third rectangle has a width of 200 and
the text components inside as well let's
run this and see what we have okay this
is basically what we had in the
documentation if you put your cursor
here you see that we have this icon and
it invites us to resize this thing the
second rectangle can not go below and
minimum width of 15 if you remember
that's why we are saying this behavior
here let's look at the rectangle one and
see it has a maximum width of 400 so if
we take this down and keep expanding you
on there is a width it can go past okay
this is the maximum for it and you can
see that rectangle 3 the green one here
has no constraints as to how much it can
grow in wealth it can occupy whatever it
wants and again you see these things are
growing in the horizontal direction you
can also make them
grow in the vertical direction and the
way you do that you specify the
orientation for your fan okay so if I
change this orientation to vertical
let's say orientation Qt.Vertical
what else do we need to change we need
to change all this width property to
height properties so we should say here
layout maximum height and say 400 we
should go down here and comment these
two layout and say layout minimum height
make it 50 and say Layout.fillHeight
make this true we should also set this
to height instead of width let's comment
this out so that you have it for
reference I don't like to delete plans
in lectures like this so we're going to
say height to 200 do we have another with
let's say height here and make it 200
and if we run now and here is our program
we can expand and shrank our rectangles
as we see in here. These covers all had to
say in this lecture the next one we're
going to look at the drawer QT quit
component I'll see you there