In this lecture we are looking at the
switch to to quit control this control
is really like a checkbox but it is more
suited to mobile devices we're going to
go to QT creator and play with it okay
here we are in QT creator we create our
new project it's a two to quick
application we call it switch demo save
it in the usual location choose our QT
version and choose our kit hit next and
finish we should import our QT quick
control module change the title to say
switch demo down here we want to put a
column component the width is going to be
the same as or the parent and we give it
a spacing of 20 so I want to put in a
couple of switch components so going to
say switch the text is going to say
Wi-Fi for example I copied this a couple
of times this is going to say bluetooth
and this is going to say NFC.
let's say that we want the user to
choose the technology that they want to
use to share data if you look at the
documentation there are a couple of
properties that this switch component
has, and one of them is checked, you use
this to control if the switch is on or
off okay so if we set the Wi-Fi one to
true and run you see that it is turned
on if you turn it off it goes off like
this if you turn it on it turns black
and it goes to the right okay you can
also turn on NFC or Bluetooth or
whatever you want I want to Center my
fence here because
think it looks better if it is centered
so I'm going to say anchor.horizontalCenter
parent horizontal
Center copy this samething and put it in
these buttons, another thing you can do
is disable one of these buttons and all
you have to do is say enabled and set
that to false and if you run we're going
to have the NFC switch turned off okay
it is disabled you can also capture the
jet state you can say unchecked changed
and say if checked because to true Wi-Fi
switch is turned on let's say that and
if it is not true we say Wi-Fi switch is
turned off if we run this we turn it off
it is turned off we turn it on it is
turned on okay you can do all this done
if you want you can see that this is
really no different than a checkbox and
it is a matter of preference which one
you use QT quick does its best to give
you more components on your menu and let
you choose what matches better your
requirements for your project this is
all have to say in this lecture in the
next one we're going to look at Page and
Tab bar components, I'll see you there