in this lecture we are looking at the
text area Qt Quick Control, this
control is used to collect multi-line
text information from the user. We're
going to go to QT creator and play with
that okay here we are in Qt creator.
we're going to create a new project so
Qt Quick application as usual we call it
text area demo hit next choose our
Qt version, we choose our kit here
and finish we want to import QT quick
controls we import the latest version we
have install which is 2.4 we say what
this demo is about I want you to put in
a column component give it a spacing of
40 and make its width equal to the width
of the parent inside the one to put a
label that is label what we wanted,
do ctrl a and ctrl I to align this and
down here I want to put a text area
component I wanted to have a width of
600 a height of 115 I want it to be
centered so I'm going to say
anchor.horizontalCenter is parent horizontal
Center we can give it a color which is
going to be the color of the text let's
put in red we can give it a wrap mode
we're going to put in TextArea.wrapMode, if
we go back to text area and look at some
of its properties it inherits from text
edit I don't think we explained this
wrapMode so this is a good chance
to talk about it. Set this property to
wrap the text to the TextEdit item's
width
okay if the text is longer than the
available width these are different ways
you can wrap it to the next line and
they say what all these things do so you
should read this if you are interested
okay you see the default is NoWrap if
you don't set wrapping it's not going to
wrap it's going to try and show this on
one line I also want to put in a text
property it is going to show a long
piece of text that cannot fit on one
line we want this let's run and you see
that we have our text displayed in here
we are using this text area for now to
display some text but you can also use
it to do edit on and capture what the
user has typed then for example you can
delete some text and put in some text of
your own and you see that as we type
more gibberish here the text disappears
in the area that we cannot see so if you
want to see all your text it is a good
idea to wrap your text area inside a
scroll view and that's what we're going
to do so we're going to put a scrollView
component here and take all our text and
put that inside our Center and should
move to the top so the root level of
this ScrollView, and our width and height
properties should also fall out the same
they should move to the root level and
if you run now it looks like it is the
same but when we have hover on top of this
you see that there is a scroll bar to
the right indicating that we can scroll
up and down in our text here and another
thing I want you to see is that you can
specify a background component for your
text area so you can say something like
that ground and we are going to put in a
rectangle component why not
and even the color of black and we want
to change the text to white because it's
going to be on top of a black background
let's run mm-hmm
this is better I like it now when you
want to use your text area as a data
collection element how do you capture
the text that the user type then we're
going to disable the text property here
and put in some placeholder text they're
going to say placeholder and we're going
to say Type in your query when we run
this it's going to say type in your
query we should provide a button
component at the bottom of the ScrollView
component and say submit in the
button
we should Center it in the middle and
when the button is clicked we would want
to capture the text inside this text
area so it is a good idea to give it an
ID right now and we should say console.log
the text inside the text area is and
put in the text that we have in there so
we're going to say text area ID text
let's run okay this is what we have it
says type in your query the moment you
start typing something the placeholder
goes away and if you delete again the
placeholder comes back and if you type
in some text for example
something like this if you click Submit
you see the text here and of course in a
real application you should do some
validation on the text that you get from
the user okay this is all I have to say
about the text area component it really
is easy to use you just stuff it in your
user interface if you want to have
scroll bars around it when you have a
longer piece of text you should wrap
this inside the scroll view element in
the next lecture we're going to talk
about the text field QT quick control
I'll see you then