you use a text field when you want to
collect one-liner pieces of text from
the user we're going to go to QT creator
or and play with this Qt quick
component, in QT create or we create our
new project we call it text field demo
save it in usual location, choose our QT
version and choose our kit we want to
include our QT quick controls module and
we want to state what we are doing in
this lecture. A text field is really
something like this you see here it's a
step in your first name I can say Daniel
and I can do something with the data in
here for example can collect it when the
user hits this button so right now we're
going to do the structure like this
we're going to go back to our code and
put a column component inside we'll put
a spacing of 20 and we want to Center
this in the parent so we're going to say
the usual instead. We want to put another
row component put some spacing of 30 and
give it a width of 300 and this row
component is going to have a Label
component that says first name and we're
going to have a text field element to
capture that first name from the user so
we're going to put in a Label component
like this, Ctrl A Ctrl I to align
it basically has a width and height we
specified the wrap mode and we align
tents in the center and the text says
first name if you want to know about the
Label component you can come to the
documentation and look at it the label
extends Text with styling and font
inheritance, okay add some features to
detect what we have seen now we can add
in our text field
we can give it an id
they better width of 200 for
example give it a height of 50 I think
it has a placeholder - yes it does so
you can say first name or type in your
first name invite the user to do
something and if you look at this
component in the documentation let's go
to f1 you see that it inherits TextInput
component we have seen before if
you go to it you're going to see some
signals that this thing has, and one of
them is added and finished that is
emitted when they returned key is
pressed or when this component loses
focus so you can use it to know when to
capture the text that is inside because
you can say onEditingFinished
console.log text edit finished and show
the new text which is going to be
available in the text property of this
thing here so down here below there are
component we're going to put a button
remember that this is a column component
that we are inside so we can keep adding
stuff to it the text is going to say
click and then the on click event we are
going to capture the text that is in the
text field we can do this and we pass in
the textfieldID and capture the text
property let's run the application and
see what we have so far ok we have our
thing here and you see that this click
button is not centered but that's not to
be deal
I type in Daniel and when I click this
you see that I am capturing the two
signals one is coming from the fact that
the text field is losing focus and
onEditingFinished is being emitted and
inside we are type in text edit finished
ok we should say finished and the other
one is when we click on this button and
it says text is Daniel you can use
whatever way you find more convenient to
capture your text. And ladies and
gentlemen this is all you need to know
about the text field component it really
is very easy and you use it to capture
one-liner pieces of text from the user
and the next lecture we're going to look
at the split view in Qt Quick Control I
see you there