And this is video 7.3 of Qt on desktop which covers static linking on Qt. In this video we're going
to cover when we would static link, building Qt for static linking,
and finally static linking our application.
So when do we need to link things statically?
I've got a couple of reasons why it would appear but the main one is if we're distributing a package
to a client and we don't want our client to introduce bugs into our project by dynamically linking the
wrong versions of the code.
Now please note that if you statically link a project you need to either buy a Qt license or be willing
to distribute your code as per the Qt license.
But now that we've decided to lock down our code, we need to actually compile Qt for static linking
If you installed Qt using a Package manager or in Windows,
the binary is that you got didn't come with the actual static binaries. So we need to download the Qt
source code, change into the source code directory, call the 'confgure' command, pass the '-static' parameter
and then compile using the 'make' command. All the basic commands here. For Debian specifically, we
can use the package manager to help us out.
So specifically we can use the 'build-dep' command to go ahead and build on everything that we'd
need for Qt base 5 developer (qtbase5-dev) and then we can use the 'source' command right here to go ahead and get
the source code.
Once we've got that we can go ahead and change into that directory, use our 'confgur' command and
then our 'make' command.
So you have to do that on yours by yourself and it should actually take a fair amount of time.
But once we've got our static libraries built. Let's go ahead and put them to use.
Now I've installed my static qmake in my app directory which is very important because you need to
use the qmake generated by the static compilation,
not our system compilation.
So if I use the 'which' command, you'll see that qmake is tied to my userq/bin/qmake, not the actual
static compilation ones so I need to pass in the fully qualified path to my static qmake.
So in my case that will be 'opt/bin/qmake',
so in my source code directory and I want to go ahead and do the release so I'll pass in a '-config'
'release'.
Let that run. And once I've actually done the configuration, I'll go ahead and call 'make'. Perfect.
So let's go and see if we able to statically link this or not.
And the best way to do that is to call the 'ldd' command on our actual binary.
In doing so we've got a bunch of binary is in here.
So let's see if we actually dynamically linked any of our  libraries. And you see when we run that
commands,
grepping for libQt, we didn't actually return anything which is good.
So if we look at the ldd of a binary that has been using dynamic linking, you can see that we actually
when we dynamically link, we link to Qt5Widgets, Qt5Gui and Qt5Core.
So our statically link to one we passed in our fully qualified qmake for our static compilation
successfully. Statically linked are binary.
So with that we've successfully figured out how to statically link an application, how to build Qt
for actual static linking and when to use static linking.
Join us in the next section where we cover
Qt on mobile.