This is the video 6.2 visual representations which covers Animations and Visual Transformations.
In this video we're going to cover Common Animation/Transformations, Demo of Sequential Animation before
finishing up by demoing a Rotational Transformation.
So let's get started. What are Animations? In Qml animations are applied to property values in order
to smoothly interplay between current and future property values.
So for example we could apply an animation to a rectangle to get it to shift to the right.
Thirty pixels, barely make room for something else or to smoothly change it between vertical and horizontal
views.
The most common types of animations include X and Y, Scale, Rotation and Transforming the origin.
It's important to understands animations are applied to both the object gets originally applied to
as well as any child higher fees that that object might have. In this video,
We're going to make a loading screen that lets our user know our application is still working.
You might see this for application has a bunch of networking or maybe a bunch of processing required
in the background.
So when I open up our project and go ahead and open up our main document and the first thing that we're
going to do is go ahead and create a blue_ball.
Now let's animate this to bounce up and down.
We want to pick the ball up from its min height to its max and then let it back down.
So we use a sequential animation type to let you know that we want these things to happen one after
another, instead of doing everything in parallel. We'll be manipulating the Y variable and let's have
this loop an infinite number of times.
Now let's set in our first animation where we pick the ball up from its min height to its max height.
And we'll use the NumberAnimation type to do this. We also want to get a time frame for it to
complete in and easing.type which controls how it looks when it gets animated.
Now let's put a pause in this and then we'll go ahead and run this.
So let's go out and run this now.
And you see that our ball picks straight up from its min height up to its max height and then it pauses
for half a second and you can also notice this kind of stuttering right now because it's jumping from
the top down to the bottom without any bounce between.
So once you take this ball up let's go ahead and drop it and have it bounce.
So we'll add in another NumberAnimation in order to do that
All right.
Now let's play this and see.
Now we've got this smooth pick up. Before we drop it down and it bounces slightly which happens from
OutBounce easing.type
Now if you're wondering what the different types of easing are, you can go ahead and go to the Animation
QML Type.
And if you scroll down you'll see all of the available types for easing in this documentation.
And if you look to the far right you can see graphics of how each of those look and how they actually
animate. Sweet.
So that's pretty good.
It's pretty simple but it's pretty easy.
But let's go out and take this a little further.
And now instead of just doing straight property animations, let's go ahead and apply our first rotational
transform.
So the reason for doing this is maybe our app has a loading section or it's loaded and our user needs
to take action to progress.
Now if our user gets stuck or distracted for too long, it's possible that they don't know what they need
to press or what they need to do.
So let's go ahead and create a button that makes it clear for them.
We went ahead and made a button and we gave it a property which we called the wiggle_value which is what
we're going to do to actually wiggle the button back and forth to draw our users' attention to our button.
So in order to do that we're going to need to use a transform and transform that we're going to use
is a rotation and we need to get this the X origin and the y origin which for us is just going
to be the center of the button and then we'll go ahead and set the angle to be our property, which we
just called wiggle_value.
Perfect.
So whenever we change this angle, we want this to do any other specified transformation here and other
sequential animation.
So let's go ahead and define that by using a behavioral type.
So we'll set Behavior on angle and then we'll go ahead and start our sequential animation.
And we're going to go ahead and run this twice. Since we've got everything set up,
We go to the down into the right for 60 seconds and then we'll go all the way back for 120 seconds and
then back to zero for 60 seconds.
So now the only thing I need to do is actually go ahead and change these values.
So when we originally change our value we're going to go ahead and use a timer to do that.
I'm just going to copy and paste this code in. So we'll look at this quote,
We're creating a timer.
We've got this "first" property which means it's the first time through, an "interval" and you see this
OnTriggered callback or handler wiggle original and we check to see if the go_buttons.wiggle_value is equal to
zero and if it is we change it to 10.
And if it's not currently zero then it does tend to change it to zero.
And then we reset this interval to make sure that it's a little bit longer on the second and third go
around.
So now we've got that when we change the wiggle_value from 0 to 10.
This NumberAnimation will handle that first.
But we want to do is go ahead and set some values for the wiggle back which is going to be to
a negative 10.
This is all angle.
This is all in degree.
So the first change goes to 10 degrees.
The second change is going to go all the way back to negative 10 degrees.
And then we're going to go to zero.
So let's go ahead and set that up real quick with those values.
Perfect. So let's go ahead and run this and see how it looks. See down here at the bottom we've
got our button which will actually go ahead and wiggle let our users know: Hey you need to push this
button.
So that looks great.
With that we've gone ahead and covered how to use rotational transforms, sequential animations,
in addition to covering common animations and transformations. Join us in the next video which covers Graphical
Effects and Particles.