This is Section 6 of mastering you programming which covers visual representations.
So let's go and get started with charts and Qml. In this video, we're going to cover: Static graph
resources, Dynamic line graphs and finally Dynamic scattered graphs.
Let's get started.
If you're working with static data the qtcharts Qml examples are going to be your best bet.
Here you can find demos for pie, line, spline, area scatter and bar series examples.
So what is there left to cover.
Well, these examples are great if you have static data, you know, data that you can write into your source
code.
And my experience static data graphs are the hilarious minority of cases for graphs needed in the
applications.
Most of the time we are only to need to generate graphs on the fly after doing some calculations.
So how do we generate graphs on the fly.
Let's go out and find out.
The first thing to note here is that the qtchart is actually dependent on qt widgets so as before
we're using a Qapplication if you're going to use q charts with Qml you need to actually
switch to a Qapplication that can save you some time.
So once we've got that, set up the first thing that we're going to need is some data.
Now for this example it actually included some data.
We're going to plot the land speed records from the last 60 or 70 years.
So the first thing that we need to do for this case and these are basically the speed that it was done
and the actual date.
So we need to create an instance of our data. And one thing to note here is that our data is actually
in a list model.
And the reason I do this is so that it can be easily incorporated into a list view so that you can display
the list view in the chart right next to it.
You can do it after we're done with this example and you've got everything running.
So now that we've got our data. The next thing that we're going to need is chart view which is where
our data will be displayed.
We're going to create a ID in ChartView in lower case and we'll give it a title of land_speed records
Perfect. So our land speed record data is going to be the actual date that it was broken and the value
in kilometers per hour that were driven.
So we're going to need to create two accessories one ValueAis for the speed and one DateTimeAxis
for the date.
The next thing that we're going to do is set Mins and Maxxis for both of our accessories because the
data will be plotted off the chart with the default values
if we don't. So we'll go ahead and set the min and max properties for both of these.
The last thing that we're going to do is go ahead and set a format up for the DateTimeAxis because
the default is a little
for those. Cool. so now we've got four axis to find.
Let's go ahead and create a line series that will plot this for us.
Awesome. So we're going to go ahead and uncomment this initialization of this Component.onCompleted
line and which you see here is we call this function _add_data_to_series and we actually pass in the
"LineSeries" that we just created. So we scroll down to where we define this add_data_to_series function.
Basically we need to iterate through our data.
That's what we're going to do here.
We've got a for loop and we're going to go from i equal to zero to i equal to the count of all our data and then we're
going to get access to each of our list items so just as a reminder list items look something like this
and we're going to get access to them each individually using a get method passing in our i value
and we want to get a hold of our two data information which is our speed and our date. Now we do need
to change our year in our data into a date format instead of a stream.
And we can do this using the Parse method.
So once we've got our data in both the speed and the date, the last thing we need to do is go ahead and
append it or add it to our actual series.
Awesome.
So let's go ahead and run this and see how it looks.
You see we've got our line chart with our min, max and our land speed records.
Now this isn't super helpful because it's kind of hard to tell exactly where the data points are.
You see it in the elbow of the band but it's kind of hard to see it for our more linear stuff where
it is.
So let's go ahead and add a scatter chart here.
So you could go all the way down the bottom you see that added a ToolBar to do that and a ToolButton
to do that "Add Scatter".
So let's go to its onClicked and you see I've got a here, we only create this one time.
So let's go ahead and really release the Create series function in our chart view to add any other series
to it.
And then move past in this names, should be "scatter" and are x and y axis.
So the last thing that we need to do is go ahead and add our data to it.
So we created the chart successfully and the series successfully but we haven't added data to it.
Luckily we've got our method that we created and implemented this and did a series.
And so we'll just call this again with our scatter series that we just created.
So let's run this one more time and then click this add scatter button and you see now it's much cleaner
and easier to see where the individual points are happening on our land speed records.
Now this still is slightly wrong.
And the reason is we should have really just thought of this as a scatter series and then typically
what you'll see for charts is we actually use a line series to show us the trends how our land speed
record is trending.
So I challenge you to react to this code and convert our line series to a scattered series and then
dynamically calculate and plot the linear trend line of the land speed records as a line series.
And with that we've successfully demonstrated how to create dynamic and linear and scatter graphs in
addition to reviewing the static graph resource documentation.
Join us in the next video where we look at animations and visual transformations.