This is video 6.4 visual
representations which covers 3d in Qt
quick. In this video we're going to cover
creating QML 3-d windows, setting up the
Rendering Pipeline before finally
finishing up with the Rotating Sphere
Demo. Alright so we've made the Qt 3D in
C++, for example, and now let's make it in QML.
This is going to be a little more
concise because QML doesn't have C++
typing information. First thing we
need to do is create our QML 3d window.
Let's start in our main.cpp, we'll be
using the Qt3DQuickWindow as object,
the Qt3DQuickExtras model in the quick
name space which looks something like
this.
And once we created our window, we'll go
ahead and set the source to be our main.qml
and I'll go ahead and show it.
Awesome! So now let's switch to our
main.qml. The first thing that we want to
do is go ahead and set up our scene
route. Once we've got our scene route,
we need to set up our rendering pipeline,
one of the first things that we need in
our rendering pipeline is the camera so
let's go ahead and create that first. Now
I'm just going to paste in some options
for our camera so that will set its
field of view, aspect ratio, near and far
planes, and it's positioning. Awesome! so
now let's get to setting up our
rendering pipeline. We're going to use
the components property on our route
entity to do that. Now as part of our
rendering pipeline, there should be no
surprises here: we're going to use a
forward renderer as our active frame
graph. We're going to set the camera to
be the camera that we just created and
set the clear color to be a nice blue.
Let's also add some default input
settings to our components so that we
can interact with our rotating sphere
example. Now the last thing that we want
to do as part of our route entity
settings is create some first-person
camera controls, which we can do using
the FirstPersonCameraController.
Awesome, so now that we're finished
setting up our rendering pipeline, let's
create our rotating sphere demo. Let's
create two entities to track our two
spheres. Now that we've got our entities
let's go ahead and create our SphereMesh
to give them some volume.
And then we also need to create our
material so that it can interact with
our lights floors.
Awesome! So let's go ahead and add these
components to our entities using the
components property.
So we've got our two spheres, but we need
to create one sphere that orbits the
other, so we're going to create a
transform to do this. We'll create a
property called user_angle and then set
the matrix to rotate and translate with
the user_angle.
So now we just need to create something
that'll change our user_angle from 0 to
360 so that it goes in a full circle. And
if you remember from last time, we can
use a number of transformation or a
number animation to do this.
So you can see we've managed to
successfully create our rotating sphere
demo and we can click this and look
around as well. So with that we've
successfully created our rotating sphere
demo demonstrateing how to set up a the
QMl rendering pipeline as well as
created a QML 3D window. Join us in the
next section we'll cover Qt on desktop.