And this is video 7.1: Qt on desktop which covers packaging on Windows. And in this video we're going to
cover building for release, building an installer,
and lastly how to install and install our package.
So the first thing that we need to do is go ahead and make a release build.
So we need to actually open up our colors.pro file and then we're going to go down to this project
thing right here and we're going to change from de-bug into a release build.
And give that a second to work through what that means.
And then when the icon comes back we'll go ahead and click the build project.
Now if we go to our project tab we can actually see the directory that we've got.
So we'll go ahead and we're going to change into this directory.
And we need to change into the release directory as well.
Now we need to run windeployqt on color.pro file. As soon as it's done building, it is still compiling.
So we need to run windeployqt command on colors.exe.
So let's go ahead and do that now.
So this is going to go ahead and create some of the background files that we need now.
I've got windeployqt linked in my path environmental variable.
But you might not see to have to run this from the actual source.
So, for example, windeployqt for me is located in the
C:\Qt\Qt5.10.0\5.10.0\mingw53_32\bin\windeployedqt.exe.
So it'll depend where you actually installed Qt on your directory but you'll need to go find it
and go ahead and run that so it can create some of the folders and files that we need
So now that we've done that let's go ahead and make our installer, so we'll go to Visual Studio and we
need to make a new project.
Now where we need to do is actually do a new visual studio installer.
So it should be located in Installed> Other project types> Visual Studio installer
If not you'll need to run the install Visual Studio installer debility and install this into your local
computer to do that and I'm gonna change the names, and change it to be colors. Awesome!
So we need to go ahead and dump all the files that we just created into this directory.
So let's go ahead and do that now.
And basically we need to grab everything except for the object files which are .o and the actual Mocs.
So you need to grab everything.
Other than that and then we'll just drag it into our application folder.
Awesome.
So the last thing that we want to do is go ahead and make a shortcut on our user desktop.
So right click on colors.exe, create a shortcut and then we'll drag that over to the user's
desktop and then we'll go ahead and change it name to be colors.
I think it can be helpful to change the default name,
So I’ll change the name of the author and the manufacturer.
So I'll change the author to be my name and the manufacturer to be the course name. With that we need
to change from debug to release and we'll go ahead and build the solution.
Awesome! So once we get the build succeeds we'll go ahead and change into that repo go into the release
and then we'll go ahead and run our installer. Perfect.
So now if we minimize everything we should see the shortcut on our desktop and if we run that we can
see that we successfully installed this program and we can run and change colors as we need.
So let's go ahead to
Uninstall now.
So if we click the installer one more time and we select to remove colors we have successfully uninstalled
it.
So with that we successfully learn how to install and unstaller project, buil a Windows Installer and
also build a qt project ready for release.
Please follow the next video we’ll talk about packaging on GNU/Linux.