This is the video 6.3 visual representations which covers Graphical Effects and Particles. In
this video, we're going to cover types of Qt: Graphical Effects, Using gradients before finishing up
with creating particles.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Qt has a large amount of graphical effects that are available for creating graphics.
The best way to know what's available is just run through them all and see what they do.
Let's go into that right now.
Some of the graphical effects that kit has available include Blending, Color Effects, Gradient Effects,
Distortion, Drops Shadows, Blurs, Motion Blurs, and finally Glows and Masks.
So as you might have noticed most of these are actually used for pictures with the exceptions of gradients.
So let's go ahead and we'll go back to our loading screen application that we created the last time.
And let's go ahead and use a gradient instead of a white background so that we can demonstrate how to
use gradients effectively.
So I added in this "Rectangle" and basically it fills the entire window and fills everything else that
we've got our blue ball right beneath it.
And if we scroll down we had our button that went ahead and wiggle back and forth.
So the "Rectangle" will encompasses both of those.
So let's go ahead and add a "gradient" to this "Rectangle".
So the way to use gradients is we go ahead and create an instance of our gradient.
And then we go ahead and put in a couple of "GradientStop".
So for us we're going to use two gradientStops: one at the zero position and one at the 1.0 position
and we go ahead and have this make a gradient from black to blue.
So now if we run this again we can see we've got this nice gradient that starts at the bottom and goes
all the way to the top from black to blue just like we said.
Now we've been using this bouncing ball to let our users know that everything is working.
But let's use something a little more subtle.
So what we could use instead is a particle system.
So let's go ahead and create our particle system.
So go ahead and create this right in our "Rectangle", below our "gradient" so the type is called "ParticleSystem"
and we need to make sure this "fill" is "parent". Now, for every particle system
there's three things that we need to fill in for our particle system to work.
We need an "ImageParticle" and "Emitter" and a "Wander" instance.
So our image particle instance is going to lower the image for us and control its opacity.
Qt comes with 3D thought image particles: a star, a glow dot and a fuzzy dot. When you use the glow dot since
that works best with a lower opacity.
So let's go ahead and we'll create an instance of our image particle.
We'll set the source to be the stuff that Qt comes bundled with and we'll set the opacity.
Perfect.
Now that we defined what our particle is. Let's go ahead and define how it gets emitted by defining the
"Emitter".
Right now I'm just going to find a bunch of stuff really quickly and then we'll talk about what each
of it does.
Perfect. So we go ahead and defined our "Emitter".
So obviously with the actual emitter "height" defines how far up our particles will go. We're anchoring this to
the bottom. Anchor 3 pixels above the bottom.
So this "lifeSpan" is how many milliseconds each particle should last.
And the "startTime" is when we originally started our application that says how far in advance as you
go.
So if your "startTime" and your "lifeSpan" are the same that means that it will start fully initialize
and "emitRate" is the number of particles per second.
"Size" is the size of the particle, "sizeVariation" gives us some variation.
And then this "acceleration", this is the point variation, for this point direction, rather.
So this basically varies our X and varies our y.
As far as our "acceleration" goes and tells our particles that we want to go up.
So last thing that we need is a "Wander" instance.
So we want our particles to wander side to side as they go up.
So we're going to create the instance and go ahead and set the experience.
Perfect. So let's go ahead and more remove our bouncing ball since we don't need this anymore.
And let's run this and see what it looks like.
So now you can see we've got these particles that are coming up from the bottom.
We've got our button that is wiggling.
So it's a little less distracting.
It's much more casual than our bouncing ball was, which is important because animations can become distracting
if you've got too many of them.
So with that, we successfully learned how to get a particle system moving in the background to let our
user know that everything is still working.
We demonstrated using a gradient system to remove just a single color in the background to have that
actual nice fade in the background.
And when we reviewed specs in graphical effects. So, join us in the next video recovered a 3D in Qt
Quick.