And this is video 7.2 of Qt on desktop which covers packaging on GNU and Linux. In this video, we're
going to cover some specific Linux QMake scopes, how to set up for Debian packaging,
And lastly how to uninstall and install our package.
So let's go ahead and start with QMake scopes.
So we're going to want to open our profile. Perfect. So, when we run this we're going to run this as the
release configuration.
So we want our release configuration on Linux to have a couple of specific values.
So let's go ahead and set up some scope conditionals to do that.
So there are two things that we want specifically here and the one is to set up the target path. So, our
"TARGET" is "colors", which is going to be our binary file that gets produce when you run this.
So we want to go ahead and set that path up to be "/urs/bin" and I really want to make sure that when
we run making install, ưe actually install this target. Perfect.
So if you look at this directory here you can tell that I actually put this using semantic versioning
which is important because our helper function dh makes actually uses the directory name and semantic
versioning as part of its setup.
So let's go ahead and install dh-make quick.
Perfect.
And then we'll go ahead and run it.
So it was going to ask if it's a single binary, independent library or Python. So, this is going to be a single
binary.
And then this is some configuration information which we can change later so the details can be fine
and the first thing that's going to do is go ahead and tell us that it couldn't find the original source
code tar file and you can either specify one or create one using "createorig".
So if we look at this folder you'll see that we've got the source code here.
So we're just going to go ahead and use that "createorig" to have dh_make make one for us.
So if we look in the directory, behind this, we've got this "orig.tar.xz" which stands for
our original source code now.
Awesome.
So dh_make is going to make this Debian folder for us. So, let's go ahead and change into there and
if we run into this we can see there's a lot of files in here.
And the first thing I can do is remove all of the example files or you can go through these if you want
but for us I want to focus on what's absolutely essential. Awesome. So, now we've got our "changelog" compatibility
which is used for dh_make control rules and source.
And so really all of these files,
The only two that are important are control and rules.
So the first thing that we're going to do is use the control file to go ahead and define some of our
dependence and remember how I said that we could change everything.
Here's where it changes.
So if needed change the source name or the priority of the maintainer or anything like that.
But the two things that we're going to change in here are the dependence.
And there's a build dependent and a package dependent and we're going to set these both to be dependent
on qt5,
which you could probably narrow down some but for our case this is 5.
And this "Depends" use some helper methods to figure out what exactly it depends on.
So we'll just go ahead and leave that alone and add our "qt5-default". Perfect.
So the other important file in here is the rules file.
So let's go out and open that up.
If you look at the very top here you can see this is an actual "make -f".
And so this dh is the help command for us.
And what this is going to do is actually run the three basic commands for us for any qmake.
So it's going to run.
So these are the three commands that the dh command is going to run in a
qmake until it's in make the release file and then it's going to actually build it and then go ahead
and install it.
Ever since version 7.4.12 of this helper method, qmake already built in.
So we're not going to do anything, we're not going to touch this file at all.
But if you needed some custom functionality as far as the actual building and making. Here's where you
do it. For example, you can override the configuration to set "this example for Cmake". That's all
we need to do.
So we're going to go ahead and back up a directory into our source code directory and go ahead and use
the "dpkg-buildpackage" to build this out.
So a couple of things.
The first thing you need to see is you're probably going to see an error here that says that we were not able
to successfully sign this. For our case and purposes it's not going to matter since we're just distributing
it locally.
But if you're trying to push it up into the debian files, you need to actually have a new public
key.
The second thing that we should note if we backup directory, we can see we've actually created quite
a few files.
So we still have our original source code file the "orig.tar.xz".
We also have this "debian.tar.xz", which would capture any sort of patches that we applied to the
source code and then we had our signature file.
The dsc file right here, couple other administrative files "buildinfo".
And this "changes" for the change file. And in this "amd64" which is the actual architecture amd64 is my computer
".deb" that's the actual package files.
Let's go ahead and install that.
And one thing to check before we do this if we use that "which" command to see colors we can see that
we don't actually have the binary colors currently installed in our system.
And now if we run "which colors" we can see that we've actually successfully been able to put that binary
in there and if we go to a graphic user interface and run "colors" you can see this binary it pops up in the
release form and we can go ahead and change anything in here just like we want for if we run it out
of our Qt creator.
But now it's actually in our file package manager and being tracked there.
And so the nice thing about being in our package manager is that we can actually use our package manager
to remove it for us.
And now for using which command, you see that binary is removed.
So with that we successfully manage to learn how to install and uninstall our package, went through a simple
example of Debian package and went through some Linux
Qmakes specific scopes.
Please join us next time where we go over Static Linking for Qt apps.