in this lecture we are looking at the
the checkbox QT Quick Controls element.
you use this element when you want to
select among multiple options. Let's go
to Qt createor and play with that.
Here we are in Qt creator, we are
going to create a new project. It is a QT
quick application, we call it check box
demo. Choose the QT version we have
installed, choose our toolkits of
interest, Android and desktop, and finish.
We want to import Qt quick controls, and
change the title here to say... checkbox
demo. Inside here we want to put a column
component... because we want to lay things
out from top to bottom. Inside we want to
put three checkbox elements. This is
going to say option one. We're going to
copy these two times option two, option
three. We want to put the spacing of 20...
between these elements, and we want to
center this and the parent. We're going
to say anchors, horizontal, center,
parent, horizontal, center. Let's run this and see how it
looks.
mm-hmm we have three check boxes here.
You see that you can check them and
uncheck them. What I want you to see is how
to capture the check state... if you need
it in your application. This is the
natural fence to want from this control,
right? But before we do that I want you
to see that you can control the check
state here. You can say check and set
this to true, for example, and set the
third one to false.
If we run again, the first one is going
to be checked and the third one is going
to be unchecked, which is the default
setting for these controls. Another thing
you can do is disable one of this, so you
can set the enabled property to false.
Okay, it is enabled by default. Let's run
this. Option 3 is going to be unchecked
and disabled. You cannot click on it now.
So how do we capture the choice of the
user? How do you know when one is checked
and is unchecked? You can capture the
uncheck state changed signal... and check
if it is checked. So you're going to say
if checked equals to Troue, console.log
option 1 is checked, and if it isn't we
say that, ok, you can capture this in your
application. And you can do whatever you
want with this piece of information.
Let's run the application when we check
on one. Ok,
one is unchecked. One is checked and you
can do the same thing on all these
checkboxes here. This is really all there
is to use the checkbox element. If you
need to know more about it you can come
to the help here, and type it in, and see
its information. Or you can select it
here, hit F1. You see that the
documentation opens up on the right here.
And you can come to the top, click on
open in help mode, and have the help
available to you to try out. These covers
all we have to say about the checkbox
element. In the next lecture, we are going
to look at the combo box, a Qt quick
control element. I'll see you there