In this lecture, we're going to look at
the button element from the QT quick
controls module. If we go in QT creator,
click on the help tab here, and type
"button" in the search bar here. We are
going to be taken to the documentation
for the button QML type. And one thing
you should notice right away is that the
import statement imports from QTQuick
controls 2.4. It was introduced here and
it is inherently an abstract button. We
are taking some feature from this to qml
tag here, so if we go down in the
description, you can see that a button
presents a push-button control that can
be pushed or clicked by the user. And if
you look down here, you see that there is
a set of signals that we can get from
the button. You can know when it is
clicked,
you can know when it is doubleClicked,
pressed, released, PressAndHold. These
signals are very similar to what we saw
on the MouseArea, but the button is very
compact in that you don't need to wrap
MouseArear inside rectangles. You just
use a button and you have these signals
available to you to use. Right now, we
like to start a new project and play
with this. Create a new project here. It's
going to be a QT Quick Application. We
call it "button demo", save it in a
location on our drive, hit "next", choose the
QT version we are using. Right now,
because we want to test this application
both on Android and desktop, we are going
to choose the kit for Android, the x86
version because we want to run this in a
virtual device. If you use araeabi
here, it's going to be very slow, so we
choose x86 which speeds things up a
little bit. We also choose desktop
because this is our default environment
we want to work on. And hit "next", and
"finish". We want to work with QT quick
controls, so we should import that. Ee're
going to say "import...
controls 2.4". We are going to change the
title here and say "button demo", and
import layouts because we want to use
that. So you're going to say QtQuick.Layouts 1.3,
we're going to put in a RowLayout. And
inside, we're going to put two buttons, so
we're going to say "button". Its Id is
going to be "button1". It's going to have
a text property. It's going to say "button1".
We're going to add another one. And we
want this RowLayout to fill the
available width. One thing we can do is
to anchor it to the left and to the
right of the parent by saying "anchors.left".
Ok, the left side of the RowLayout
is going to stick to the left side of
the window, and the same thing is going
to happen to the right side. Because we
want the buttons to fill the available
width, we're going to do something like
Layout.fillwidth and set this to "true".
You know this from the layouts lecture.
And set this to "true". Let's run and see
what we get. And you see that we have two
buttons. One to the left,
and another one to the right. This is how
this buttons look. One thing I want you
to notice is that this is the default
style. If you want to change this style,
how do you do it? One way to do this is
to come
to the main file and set the style that
you want to use in the main function
here. But before we do that, there is
another module that we need to import
here, which is called "quit". This is going
to give us access to a class called
QQuickStyle. But if we try to
include that class here, QQuickStyle,
you see that it is not recognised in the
autocomplete feature here. So for include
be available, we need to run QMake
after we add something to the project
file here. Every time you add something
or remove something from the project
file, you need to run QMake. So
let's save our project file here and do
work run to make. And if we come to
main again and include QQuickStyle,
you see now that it is available. We
include it. And before we load the QML
file, we want to do something. Ok, we want
to load our style. The way you do that,
you say QQuickStyle, setStyle, you
call a static method on this class. And
you pass in the name of the style that
you want. So for now, we want to try the
"Material" for Android feel and look. We
are going to try the other ones. Don't
worry. If you run the application now, it
is going to look different
mm-hmm. This is the look you have on
Android devices.
Another style we can try is "universal" to
make it feel home on Microsoft devices.
So you can type in "Universal", run the
application, mm-hmm, this is another look.
You can try "fusion",
let's see how it works. This looks like a
desktop app. You can try imagine to look
at the default style of it. This is how
it looks and you can put in the default
style, which is what we had before when
we didn't specify any style. So you type
"default" like this and it's going to
look like it looked at the start of this
lecture.
This is it. Okay, now you have a way to
test all the styles that we looked at.
Now that we have our application running,
we need to know when each of these
buttons is correct. And it's not very
different from what we did in the MouseArea.
If you come to the documentation
for the button, you're going to see that
we don't see any signal here because all
the signals are coming from the abstract
button QML element. If you click on it,
and look at signals, you're going to see
a bunch of signals we can play with on
our button element. So let's try click, ok
button1, say onClicked, you see that
it is recognized here, console.log, and we
do the same thing for button2. Run. If
you click, you see that our signals are
being captured. You can try all these
signals if you want. We are going to try
doubleClicked. Let's try it on button1,
onDoubleClicked, console.log.
If you run it, mm-hmm,
double-click, okay, you see that the
double-click Signal is emitted but also
the click signal is emitted, but you can
process whatever signal you want in your
qml application here. Another thing I
didn't show you is that you can also use
QT quick controls 1 series. Let's change
this to 1.4 and you see that this signal
was not there in QT quick controls 1,
so we can comment it out and run the
application and see how it looks. It is
going to look like a desktop application.
This is what you see here. Okay, this is
how you can try QT quick controls 1 if
you want to use them. And if you want to
know more information about them, you can
come today online documentation here and
look at whatever it is you want to look
at. For example, if you want to know what
is available for your buttons, you can
come here, see the signals, you see the
clicked signal. This is how the button
looks. And these are different properties
that are available to you. Ok, let's turn
this back to Qt quick controls 2, one
thing I want you to know is that this QT
quick controls components are world
using the elements we have seen before
like rectangles, images, text as raw
ingredients to give you something that
you can use very fast and that is very
efficient to use. So behavior wise, they
really do the same things, for example,
you can put them in a ColumnLayout here.
Let's try this. And if we do this, they
are going to be laid out from top to
bottom but button1 is going to be to
the top, button two is going to be to the
bottom. And it is going to fill the width
that is available. Let's run the
application and see what we have.
Button1, button2, you can click on
button2, you can click on button1, and
you can double click
button1. And you see that we have our
signals. Okay, this is all the information
I had to share about the QT quick
control button element. In the next
lecture, we're going to run our app here
on an Android device and go through the
entire process of how that happens. I'll
see you there.