In this lecture, we're looking at the
BusyIndicator QT Quick Control element.
You use this element to show that
something is going on. Let's go to Qt
creator and play with that. Okay, here
we are in QT creator. We are going to
create a new project.
It's a Qt Quick Application. You have to
make sure to store it in a location
without spaces, so if you have spaces in
here, you're going to have problems
running your application on mobile
devices like Android. So be careful about
that. We are going to call it "BusyIndicatorDemo",
use this as the default
project location, choose our Qt version,
choose our toolkits, Android for x86 and
desktop. We don't want araeabi because
it is very slow to run on virtual
devices. You already know this and "finish".
We want to put in our import QT Quick
Control 2.4 and QTQuick.Layouts because
we're going to use this. We change the
title. We say "BusyIndicator Demo". And if
we go to the documentation, type in
BusyIndicator, you're going to see the
type here. What it does, it is used to
indicate activity while content is being
loaded or the UI is blocked waiting for
a resource to become available. You
basically use it when something is going
gone to let the user know. And this is how
you use it. What we're going to do is to
put in a ColumnLayout. Inside, we're
going to put in BusyIndicator element,
so we're going to say BusyIndicator. We
want to set a width property to the
layout,
and the height property. Set it up like
this. And below the BusyIndicator, we
want to put another ColumnLayout that
is going to contain two buttons, so we're
going to say "Button.. Id: button1"
"Button.. Id: button2". The first button is
going to say "running", meaning that
something is going on. And the second one
is going to say "not running". Let's run
the application and see how it works. We
are going to run it on desktop. Click the
green button and you see that we have
something pinning, meaning that something
is going on and we have our two buttons
down below here. But you see that it
doesn't look great. We need a way to push
the entire thing to the top, put this
BusyIndicator in the center and I make
the buttons fill the entire width. We're
going to start by the buttons because
it's easier to do. We're going to say
Layout.fillWidth, "true". And the same thing to
the second button. And we should correct
this piece of text, and say it "Not Running"
here. Run again, see that effect of all
changes, mm-hmm, we are filling in the
entire width. Now we want to center this
thing. Okay, how do you do that? One way to
do that is to use alignments, so we're
going to say Layout.alignment and say
Qt.AlignHCenter.
If we run, it's going to be in the
center. The last thing we need to do is
to find a way to push this to the top.
And one way I can think of right now is
to use an item to the bottom
of this ColumnLayout, and make it fill
the remaining space in the window. Let me
show you what I mean. I'm going to go
down below this ColumnLayout, the second
one that contains the buttons. I am going
to put in an item element and I'm going
to make it fill the width and the height.
This is like a spacer item in the C++
side of Qt if you have worked with
spacer items. If we run, we're going to
have our two things, push to the top just
like this. And all this space here is
being filled by the item that we put in
here. To make it visible, we can put in a
rectangle inside. This is of no practical
use, I just want you to see this space
here. We want to make it fill the parent.
It fills the item and we give it a color
of red, for example. Choose a color you
like. If you run the application, we're
going to see a red rectangle down in
this space. Now that you have seen it, I'm
going to take it out because it is
useless. I'm going to comment it out, and
this is one way to push things to the
top by specifying an item that is going
to fill the remaining space. I just
wanted you to see this technique because
you might use it in other places. But you
can completely leave all this out, okay,
and not specify the height property of
this ColumnLayout here, and things are
going to be laid out to the top as well.
Let's run the application so that you
can see this. Okay, this is the same
effect. These are two ways you have to
make your user interface look like this.
Now we want to focus on our BusyIndicator.
One thing you might want to do
is to get the ability to start and stop it.
How do you do that?
Let's use our buttons here, handle
the onClicked event, give an ID to our BusyIndicator,
and when you want to make it
run, you just set its property of running.
Let's look at its documentation and you
see that it has a property "running". This
property holds whether the BusyIndicator
is currently indicating
activity. If it is true, there is some
activity. If it is false, there is no
activity. So what we want to do is to say
here BusyIndicatorId.running equals
"true" because we want it to run. And when
you click on "Not Running", you want to
make it not run and what we're going to
do is set its running property to false.
We wanted to start not running so we're
going to set the running property to
false. When we declare it right here and
run the application. So what we should
have is the BusyIndicator not running
and not visible here. And if we run it, it
becomes visible. When we stop it, you
don't see it here. Okay, run it, you see it
running. Stop it, and you don't see it
here. A natural thing to want here is to
make it not occupy space while it is not
visible. How do you do that? It actually
is very easy to do. You can come back to
the code and make it invisible when it
is not running. And you can say "visible,
false" Do the same thing here. When you
run it, you also make it visible,
say "visible" and said visible to false
here. Let's run again, it is not visible.
When you run it, it becomes visible, and
the entire UI moves down a little bit to
give it some space. When you stop it,
mm-hmm
running, not running, it becomes invisible.
But it doesn't go up to fill the space.
0:09:15.580,0:09:26.770
What is going on? This is "true", it's not
"false", my bad. Run again. We run it, it
becomes visible. We stop it, it becomes
invisible. And this is really all there
is to using a BusyIndicator, you show it
when you want to show it. And you show it
like this by making it visible and
setting its running property to "true". You
hide it by setting these properties to
"false". Okay, you have seen the BusyIndicator
in the default style. How does
it look in different styles because we
want to see that till? So you already
know how to work with different styles.
We have two other QT Quick Controls 2
include here. And we have to go to the
main file, the cpp one, include QQuickStyle,
and down here say QQuickStyle,
setStyle,
and set "Material" because we want to see
how this looks on Android. You changed
something in the project file, so you
should run QMake. Qt Quick Controls 2
is not recognized here, so I messed up.
Let's go to the first project, and change
a bit. Okay, it is quickcontrols2. It is
not qtquickcontrols 2. My bad. Run again.
Okay, this is how it should look in
material style. If you run it, it looks
like this. And you stop it just like we
did before. You can try all these
different styles if you want. For example,
we can use the "Fusion" style. Run again,
and this is how it works in fusion. Stop
it. The last thing I want to do is to run
this on an Android device and see how it
looks. You should build up this habit of
running your application on multiple
platforms if you can because that's
really what Qt is all about. So I am
going to put "Material" back because
that's the home style for Android
devices. I am going to go down here,
choose my Android kit, clean the project,
Run QMake,
and ribald the project. Just to make sure
that we start on a clean slate. And if
you want to try this on an Android
device, you should have your virtual
device start in running. I have mine here.
if the work is successful, I am going to
hit the button to run the application.
Okay,
the work is successful, I can run the
application, choose my device here, hit OK,
bring the device up again and we should
have our UI running on our Android
device in a minute. Okay, here is our
application. Click on "running" you see the
BusyIndicator here, click on "not running"
and it stops. These covers all I have to
say in this lecture. In the next one,
we're going to look at the check box QT
quick control element. I'll see you there.