In this lecture we are looking at QT
quick controls. These are a set of QML
elements that allow you to work
beautiful user interfaces very fast. With
QT quick controls, you are enabled
to work to user interfaces like this. If
you look here we have radio buttons, we
have sliders, and we have a button here.
And of course this is a small subset of
what is available in QT quick controls,
but you can see that you can apply
different styles and themes to your user
interface, to have different looks and
feels. There is a predefined set of
styles that you can use in your QT Quick
controls and they are listed here if you
are interested. Then before the style is
what you have, if you don't set any style,
the fusion style tries to match what we
see on desktop platforms. Imagine it's the
style that is customizable with your own
icons that you put in a special folder
in your project and they are
automatically used as your icons. You use
material style when you want your QT
quick application to look like an edit
Android application, and universal style
is used when you want your QT quick
application to look like a Microsoft
native application on mobile devices, or
this new fluid interfaces you see in
newer versions of the Microsoft
operating system. There are two versions
of QT quick controls you need to be
aware of. QT quick control one series.
We're targeting desktop devices. They
were used a long time ago and they are
on their way of being deprecated. What
you should use now is QT quick control
2, which are more performant on mobile
devices. And if they are performing on
mobile devices, they should also be
performant on desktop devices. So if you
can use QT quick controls 2. Here we are
on the online documentation for QT quick
controls one series. Tou can see that the
module was introduced back in QT 5
one, and if you scroll down here you see
the components that we have in QT quick
controls one. We have application window
that we can use to have a main window
with menus, status bars and things like
that.
We have controls like buttons, checkbox,
combo boxes. We're going to look at this
thing. On this side you see the online
documentation from QT quick controls 2,
they basically look like QT quick
controls one series. But in terms of
performance they are very different from
QT Quick control one series, because a lot
of effort has been put into making them
as less resource hungry as possible. Okay.
To use them you have to import them like
this. The latest version of QT Quick
controls is 2.4, that comes with Q 511.
You can see it here. And if you go down
you see different versions for Qt Quick
controls and the matching QT version. So
if you are running QT 5 7 you learn to
have to use QT quick controls 2.0. And as
you go up you see that the version changes.
You can see that there are many things
you can use, but for now we are
interested in Qt Quick controls. So if
you click here on Qt Quick controls you
wait to see a list of elements that are
available to you in QT quick controls 2.
you can see that we basically have the
same things we had in QT Quick
controls 1 but they are very different,
in the way they look and in the amount
of resources that they consume on the
device where they ran. Ok you can click
on any of these elements to know more
about them. But this chapter is about all
these elements, so we're going to cover a
good number of them in detail. I also
want to show you a little bit more
information about these styles that you
can use so you can see the default style
looks like this and they say that it is
a simple and lightweight all-round style
that offers maximum
performance. So if you want to have
maximum performance especially on mobile
devices you should use this style. Fusion
style is designed to give you a desktop
experience. Iit is designed to look like
desktop platforms. Imagine style is
designed to be customizable, so you can
define a folder in your project that
contains your icons for your style and
they are going to be picked up
automatically. And if you look here they
say it is based on image assets, the
style comes with the default set of
images which can easily be changed by
providing the directory with images
using the predefined naming convention.
So you can do that if you want to
provide your own icons for your style.
But we're not going to do that in this
course. if you are interested click on
this link and you're going to have
more information on that. Material style
is for Android devices and a key piece
of information here is that it is
resource-hungry.
This style and it is the same as the
universal style that targets Microsoft
universal design guidelines. It is also
resource-hungry the same as material
style. So we are going to have a chance
to look at these styles and how they
look as we go through the QT Quick
controls. And we are going to focus on
QT Quick controls 2 because that's
the way forward. You don't really want to
focus on critically controls one because
they are going to be deprecated pretty
soon. But if you want to use them the API
is pretty much the same, all you have to
do is look at the documentation on some
things you need to be careful about. Okay
this brings us to the end of this
lecture, and the next lecture we're going
to start playing with these QT quick
controls, starting with the button
control. I'll see you in the next lecture