in this lecture we are going to look at
the combobox
element it is an element that allows the
user to choose between different options
if you come to Qt creator go to
tools options and choose Build & Run
here you going to have an option here
stop application before building I just
want you to see that a combobox is
something like this you click on it and
you are given a few options you can
choose from and you choose one by
clicking to it
let's create a new project QT quick
application we call it combobox demo
hit next choose our Qt version we
want these toolkit we are working on
desktop in this demo we change the title
to combo box demo and we should put in
our import for a QT quick controls
controls 2.4 that's what we want down
here we want to put a column element we
want these spacing to be 40 and we want
its width to be the same as the parent
in this we put the label element
and the label element is really like a
text element if we click on it and press f1
going to help mode you're going to
see that the label element extends text
with styling and font inheritance it
really is a text that is enhanced with
more features so you can give it some
text to show and we are going to say
"Non Editable Combo" because this is what we
want to show out mean the combobox that you
cannot edit we want its wrap mode to be
level wrap we want it to be aligned in
the center so we're going to set
horizontalAlignment
Qt AlignHCenter and we
wanted to have the same width as its
parent okay we put the label to keep
things organized and so that you can
know what we are aiming at down here we
are going to put a combobox element
okay let's look at its documentation
click on f1 go in full help mode and
you're going to see it is a combined
button and pop-up list this is a better
explanation actually when you click on
it there is a pop-up list that shows
with the options that you can choose
okay and you use it like this the model
property allows you to give it a list of
things that it can show and we are going
to Edit, in a moment let's give it an
ID okay this is the ID we want let's
close this we want to give it the data
to show using the model property we put
this in an array so let's say 1 2 this
should do we want it to be in the center
horizontally too so we can say anchors
horizontal center because parent
horizontal Center and we want to know
when somebody selects something in the
combo box if we go back to the
documentation and look at its signals
there is one signal that is called
activated and it is emitted when the item
at index is activated by the
user okay so we can say on activated
this is the handler we want and inside
this handler we want to output the
element that was selected and there is
another property that should give us
that on a plate and that one is current
text so we can say console.log
we want to put the current index inside
square brackets so we're going to do
something like this okay we first want
to show the index which is current index
this is another property of the combo
box element if you go there you see that
it is this property that holds the index
of the current item in the combo box
okay we are going to append the current
text to show the current element and we
are going to append a string literal
that says is activated okay you going to
see what I mean when we run this let's
run the application mm-hmm you see that
when we click on the combo box here we
have a list of options you can select
one through four for example if we
select three it says to the index and it
says the text and it says is activated
okay the index for 3 is 2 because the
indexes start from 0 so this is 0 1 2
and the last one should be 3mx and it
says the text and it says it is
activated
I hope this shows you how you can
capture the currently selected item in
the combo box and another thing that is
not obvious is how you give your combo
box a list of things it can show ok this
is a model property we haven't really
talked about models in qutilat we are
going to talk about that later in the
course but for now know that it is a way
you feed the data to show to the combo
box and this is really what we did here
now you know how to work with a non
editable combo box that you feed static
data using model property here the
next thing we want to do is to use
an editable combobox that we can add
data to at run time okay we're going to
call this editable it's really going to
be the same the other properties and we
are going to copy these combo box and
give it a bunch of other properties okay
we are going to call it editable combo
because we want to edit it and we want
to set its editable property to true to
make it edible
okay another thing I want you to see now
is that you can feed this with an
explicit model we are going to use a
model that we call list model we are
going to give it an ID of model and
again I haven't really explained models
in QT quick for now I just want you to
have something to show in the combo box
and just look at how I do things here
don't focus on the model stuff
focus on how they feed data to the combo
box okay I'm going to try and explain it
as I go
to save some time I am going to put a
list of elements inside this model let's
hit ctrl a and control I to align fence
I just put these list elements, this
element is an element that allows you to
add items to the model okay you see that
we have objects inside we have an
attribute of text and an attribute of
location we have a few animals inside we
have a dog chicken cat and meerkat and
the location Kigali Beijing Mumbai and
Paris just look at this as a way to feed
data to the combobox don't focus on the
details of how this works I am going to
have a chance to explain this when we
talk about models and using into the
Qt quick, because our list element has two
attributes we need to specify which
attribute is going
to be shown in the list model just like
we saw one two three in the first combo
box here the way you do that you specify
a text role property and you pass in the
name of the attribute that you have in
your model here and this name should be
in quotes don't forget that and by now
if we run the application let's see what
we see mm-hmm you see that our elements
are showing inside we have a dog chicken
cat and meerkat you can see that this
combo box is different from what we had
before because it allows us to change
the data inside for example if we set
dog111 and hit enter we see that
our data is not added to the model why
is that this is because you didn't
capture the on accepted signal of the
combo box if you go back to the
documentation for the combobox
look at signals the accepted signal is
emitted when the return or Enter key is
pressed on an editable combo box so we
need to capture this signal and manually
add the data to the model and before we
do that I want you to look at another
property which is called edit text which
contains the text that the user typed in
in the combo box to add to the model we
are going to use these two things let's
come down here and set on accepted but
before we add the item to the model here
we need to check if the combo box
doesn't have this element already for
example if you try to add dog again
while dog is here we should be able to
detect that and not add it
again the way you do that you use the
method that is provided by ListElement
which is called find okay it is here in
methods this method returns the index of
the specified text or minus one if no
match is found so what we can do is set
if find
edit text because edit text is the text
that the user typed in the combo box if
we cannot find it in the combo box
already this is going to return minus
one and this is when we want to add the
element to the model so we're going to
set model which is the ID of our model
and set append and we are going to
append an object okay we are going to
set text edit text and because of our
model takes two attributes in list
elements we can add a dummy location
like location let's say us why not can
we do that let's try this if we run this
okay you see that we have our four
elements if we delete this and set
Buffalo hit enter and look down again
you see that we have buffalo and if we
select it you see that index 4 has been
added and it is buffalo okay we can
manually add data to our model here
let's add giraffe hit enter look down
you see we have buffalo and we have
giraffe the last thing i want to show
you is how you can manually capture the
current element without having to select
another one sometimes you need that
let's go down here and add a button
you already know how to use a button the
text is going to set capture current we
want it to be in the center so we're
going to copy this and put this here and
the one it is clipped we want to capture
the current element and show it in the
debug output so we're going to say
console.log we want to get the text and
the location of the list element here
for the current item that is selected in
the combo box the way you do that you
want to put things in square brackets
like this so we want to say inside here
model yet okay this is a method that is
provided by the model it basically
returns this list element object and
then you can call these properties using
the dot notation I am going to show you
what I mean so I am going to say
editable combo box ID current index okay
when you do this this is going to return
the ListElement that is the currently
selected I am and we can say text to get
its
text we are going to put a column here
and add its location so we're going to
say model get all this things and put
this on the next line so that things are
readable a little bit and say location I
hope this makes sense this is a method
for the list model here that gets the
list element at a given index we are
passing the current a text and when we
get the object here we captured the text
by saying dot text here and
captured the location by saying that
location we're going to run the
application if we click on capture
current element you see that it says
Dog Kigali which is what we have our
dog is located in Kigali let's add our
own element and say Buffalo remember
that the elements we add manually are
going to be located in the US by default
which because that's what we did here
okay if we say this Buffalo is going to
be added to the list if we get the
current element we are having Buffalo
located in the US let's add giraffe it's
also going to be in the US okay select
chicken it's going to be in Beijing
select giraffe it's going to be in the
US okay it's Giraffe, I
realized this is a bit useless because
the location is hard-coded in here but
it is not difficult to get the location
from another location in your
application and use it here I just
wanted you to have a way to read the
data that is stored in a model that you
specified and supposedly to your combo
box here and by now you have all the
information you need to work with the
non editable combo box and an editable
combo box okay you can pass in static
data like this or you can pass in an
explicit model like this okay don't
forget to set the textRole property for
your model when you do it like this
because when you forget it your combo
box is not going to know what it needs
to show in here okay if we comment this
out and run the application we are going
to have an error on the combo box is not
going to know what it needs to show this
is an internal error on the combobox
because it doesn't really know what
to show
you need to set this property to have a
model that you set like this to work
this covers all I have to say in this
lecture in the next one we like to look
at a component called a delay button
I'll see you there