in this lecture we are looking at the
delay button to to quick control this is
a control that allows you to kind of
prevent accidental clicks let's go to QT
creator and play with us
here we are in QT creator we are going
to create a new project as usual it's a
QT quick application we call it delay
button demo and save it in the usual
location in next choose our Qt version
and choose our kids we change our title
here to the delay button demo and down
here we put in a column component we
want to import QT quick controls 2.4
because that's our version and down here
we want to put a label that says what
this component does inside I am going to
put a bunch of properties that I have
already prepared we have the width that
is equal to the width of the parent we
set the wrap mode to wrap to make this
text wrapped the next line if it happens
to be wider than the available width and
we make the font a little bit bigger you
probably know all this down here we're
going to put a delay button control it
has a lot of similarities to the usual
button so it has properties like text
we're going to call this delay button
how creative we also want to put this in
the center so we're going to say n
anchor.horizontalCentor parent.horizontalCentor
and we want to look at
some specific signals from this delay
button component selected hit f1 going
to full help mode if you look at the
description for this button it is a
checkable button that incorporates in
delay before the button B
comes checked and the activated signal
is emitted it basically is designed
by default and you have to hold it
down to activate it and it is activated
after an event period of time the period
of time is specified in this delay
property and the progress says how far
you have progressed in that time we're
going to come back to our code set a
delay of one second
a thousand milliseconds and we want to
know when the button becomes activated
so we're going to say on activated you
want to console.log and we want to know
the progress as well if we go back to
the documentation you see there's a
progress property here we want to know
it so we have an automatic signal called
on progress changed we want to console
log progress is well dim let's run the
application and see what it looks like
you see that this stand is not as we
wanted we want this to fill the
available width but it isn't so we need
to set something we need to set the
width of this column to be equal to the
width of the parent and let's put in
some spacing if we run again we're
probably going to see a change and here
it is if you click on this button you
see that it just shows you some progress
okay the progress is between zero and
one and if we keep holding it down it
keeps going when it gets to one it says
button activate
I can click again and the button is
activated ok we now when the button is
activated when this signal is fired and
you can see that it is one when
you reach the progress of one ok you can
use the button like this if this is the
behavior that you want in your
application but a common usage that are
seen for this is to let the user hold
down the button until the button becomes
activated and when it is activated you
allow the user to click once and then it
becomes deactivate at it again we want to
use some custom JavaScript to have this
behavior so what we're going to do is
come to the top here and define a custom
property we're going to say property you
say activated and we set this to false
we also want to handle the signal when
the button is pressed we want to check
and see if the button is active we
console log button is clicked in here you
can do whatever you want to do when the
button is activated and collect and we
set the activated property to false
after we do our crackin so we saying
false here and when the button becomes
activated we want to set the activated
property here to true
to make it possible for the user to
click but as long as you click it is
going to become inactive again and the
clerks are not going to be handled
because activated is not going to be
true I hope this makes sense and we are
still going to see our progress as we
hold down the button
let's run hold down this pen and you see
that when we release the activated
signal is not being fired okay let's
hold it down till the end it says button
is activated but it is not click we
click they say button clicked and the
progress restarts to zero this is really
all there is to the delay button it is
very easy to use in nature but it can
come in handy when you need something
like this
in the next lecture we're going to look
at the dial control in QT quick I'll see
you there