in this lecture we are visiting the dial
control including quick this control
basically allows the user to spin around
a circle like this and choose values
from a predefined range let's go to QT
creator and play with us
okay here we are in QT creator we are
going to create our project it's going
to be a QT quick application as usual
we're going to call it diode demo save
it in the usual location it next choose
your QT version and choose your kit and
finish we are going to change the title
here to dial demo and inside we are
going to put a column component import
QT quick controls the latest version as
of now which is 2.4 we want this to have
the same width as the parent and we want
to have a spacing of 40 as usual and
inside we want to put a Label component
that says what this thing does down here
we put it dial component and we can go
to the documentation of it to see what
it is and what it does it is similar to
a traditional dial knob that is found on
devices such as stereos and industrial
equipment it allows the user to specify
a value within a range it basically
looks like this if we look at the
properties there is a from value and to
value and other properties that you can
look at if you are interested we're
going to go back to our code close this
down we want this Center and
horizontally so we're going to say
anchor.horizontalCenter
parent.horizontalCenter we want this
to start from one and go up to 100 and
we wanted to start at 50 right in the
middle we also want to know when the
value changes so we're going to say
on value changed and we are going to
console.log value say let's concatenate
this to this later string and say value
and I notice that we have a typo in here
so we're going to say parent with
instead of only saying parent because we
want this to be the same width as its
parent which is this window here if we
run now we're going to see our knob here
okay you see that it is right in the
middle if we try and move it you see
that the progress is going towards 100
we reach the top it says 100 and we
can turn it back ok the user can
choose a value in between here
another thing I've seen people do a lot
is if you don't want to have decimal
values here you can turn this value into
integers very easily by using some
JavaScript functions that are available
to you you can say math.floor to have it
rounded to the lowest value so you can
say math.floor value and if you run
again you're going to see integers you
can also round up by saying math.ciel
something like this run again
it basically looks the same it is a
matter of your own choice what you want
to use depending on your requirements if
we go back to the documentation there is
another property I want you to pay
attention to and it is this wrap here
what it does it holds whether the down
wraps when dragged for example when this
property is set to true dragging the
dial past the to position will
result in the handle being positioned at
the from position in our case if we go
past 100 it is going to go back to one
if we go past one it's going to go to
100 I personally don't like this
behavior because it confuses the users
but if you need it it is a matter of
coming here and saying wrap and set this
to true and run the application and if
you go past 100 you see that it comes to
one you can go up again and if you
decrease and go past one you see that it
jumps to 100 okay now you know how to
use the dial control to let the user
choose a value from a predefined range
in the next lecture we're going to look
at the frame control I'll see you there