in this lecture we are playing with the
flickable component and the scroll bars
you use Flickable component when you
have more content than your available
window area can display and the scroll
bars are used to show you that you can
scroll to see more contents, let'go
to Qt createor and play with us
here we are in Qt creator we're
going to create a new project the Qt
Quick application as usual we call it
flickable scroll bar demo save it in the
usual location hit next choose your QT
version choose your kit and finish we
want to change the title to say
flickable and scroll bar demo we want to
import QT quick controls let's choose
the latest version we have in our suit
installation and if we go to the
documentation and search for flickable
we're going to see that this component
places its children on a surface that
can be dragged and flicked okay you can
basically scroll through more content
than your window area can display so
what we're going to do is put the
flickable component inside here and
inside we want to put a column component
to have them layout vertically give
it an ID make it fill the parent and we
want out flickable component here to
have the same width as its parent and
the same height as its parent but we
want to tell it how much content it is
expected to show and that content is
going to come from this column component
here it's going to depend on the number
and size of the items that the
column here contains so we should use
implicit hide here to play it safe we're
going to say mColumnId and place
implicitHeight, now we should put some content
inside this column of ours I have a
rectangle here prepared I'm going to put
it in to save some time it basically is
a rectangle it has a color it has a
width that is the same as the parent and
it has a height and inside we have a
text component that says element 1 and
the text color is white so I am basically
going to copy it and paste it turn a
couple of times and change the colors to
have different things okay this is going
to be in blue and it's going to say
Element 2 this is going to be yellow
and it is going to say element 3 this is
going to be magenta why not and it's
going to say element 4 and we're going
to keep going until we have a twist 7 of
this okay I'm going to keep doing it and
come back when I'm done okay I have a
bunch of rectangles inside this column
if you want to make you things a little
bit more visible you can collapse these
rectangles like this okay this is better
if you want to know for example the
number of rectangles that you have
inside or something like that so we have
a Flickable component and we have a
bunch of rectangles inside we can run
the application and see how it looks
mm-hm you see we have our rectangles the
rectangles are bigger than the available
space in height but we can scroll up and
down because we have a flickable
wrapping around our column component
this is cool
another thing I want you to see is that
you can put scroll bars on this
flickable component to kind of let the
user have
idea of how much content is still
available the way you do that you come
back to our code here come to the bottom
of the column component or you can even
come to the top it really doesn't matter
you just have to be in the flickable
component and say scroll bar vertical
okay and say scroll bar and that create
a component like this this is an
attached property that adds scrollbar
capabilities to our flickable component
here okay and you put a scrollbar
component like this you don't need to
specify anything else you're going to
have scroll bars when you run this
application and you see that if you
scroll you're going to see a scrollbar
to the right here this is cool isn't it
so whenever you have more content than
your available window area can display
think of the flickable component
this covers all i had to say in this lecture
about the Flickable component, in the
next one we're going to look at this
slider component I see you there