you use a frame control when you want to
have a visual group and of your qml
components let's go to Qt creator
and quickly play with this control okay
here we are we're going to create a new
project
it's a QT quick application we call it
FrameDemo save it in the usual
location choose our QT version choose
our kit if you want to run this on
Android you can choose this kit and use
it as we have seen before I am NOT going
to use it now so I uncheck it we are
going to change this title to frame a
demo and import our QT quick controls
2.4 our version I want to have a frame
control inside here inside I want to
have a column layout you see that column
layout is not recognized can you know
why we didn't import the layout
components so we should say QT quick
layout and I choose one and four as our
version inside we are going to put three
buttons this is going to be button one
to copy
let's past two times to have three
buttons button 2 and button 3 and before
we run this application we want this
frame centered in the parent so we're
going to say Anchorage Center in parent
and if you run this you wait to have a
rectangle around these buttons this is
what really this frame control is all
about giving you a visual representation
of the group and
qml components and you can do
normal stuff with your controls for
example you can handle clicks on these
buttons or really do whatever you like
with these buttons let's look at the
documentation to have an official
statement of what this does so we're
going to click f1 while having Frame
selected here let's close this up and
help in full mode and what it does it is
used to layout a logical group of
controls together with them a visual
frame ok frame does not provide a
layouts of its own but requires you to
position its contents for instance by
creating your own layout or column
layout which is what we did here and
this is really all there is to this
frame control in the next lecture we
need to look at group box radio button
and check boxes I'll see you there