in this lecture we are looking at how
you can use the group box component to
group radio buttons and checkboxes
together let's go to Qt creator and
play with us, here we are in QT creator
we are going to create our project
it's a QT quick application we are
calling that GroupBoxDemo, saving it in
the usual location choose our QT version
and choose our desktop kit, we want to
change the title here to reflect what we
are doing inside we want to quote a
column component set the spacing to 10
and I wanted to feel the parent we have
to include QT quick controls so we say
QT quick controls 2.4 and we also put in
a Label component that says what this
does okay it's a group box that is going
to wrap around radio buttons that we're
going to look at right now we're going
to put in a group box component it is
going to have a title that says choose
corners we're basically going to let the
user choose what they want to take a
step on us and we want it centered in
the parent horizontally the group box
doesn't have a layout system of its own
so you have to layout your own pants
inside we're going to put a column
component and we're going to say radio
button to put one radio button text is
going to be cook ok we're going to put a
bunch of other radio buttons
let's say green tea and why not by now
if we run this application we will have
three radio buttons laid out vertically
and in a group box component this group
box is not only visual because it groups
these radio buttons together allowing
you to only check one let's run and show
you what I mean mm-hmm
you see that we have our title on top
and we can only check one check box
inside this group box this is the effect
you usually want with radio buttons to
let the user only choose one thing among
a list of options that you give them and
you can know when one is checked by
handling the checked signal for example
let's choose the coke radio button here
we can say on check state changed okay
and say if checked equals to true I like
to do it this way because it is more
understandable and easier to see we say
console.log and if it's not checked
we're going to say it's not checked
let's run again mm-hmm I check it they
say that the button is checked I click
on another button the cock button is
unchecked and we know here ok you can
capture all this information in your
handlers if you happen to need that
this is really all there is to working
with group box and radio button I am
going to add another group box that
wraps around checkboxes just to show you
how you can use that and in fact I can
copy this group box to save some type in
let you copy and paste that down here
and I'm going to change this to check
box paste paste here we're going to say
choose cute soap or red platform for
example and here we can say Windows Mac
Linux and let's specify Desktop
platform here
to be specific okay if we run this
application what shall we see we will
see check boxes down ok a group box
wrapping around check boxes you see the
title here choose support a desktop
platform and you can choose one okay it
says coke button checked I don't want
this
it should say windows button checked, this
is the evil thing about cookie tasting
run again and you can now when the
windows checkbox is checked and I want
to draw your attention to something and
that is that when you group checkboxes
inside the group box they are not
exclusive you can choose multiple stuff
together like here when we have when
it's much selected but notice that
with radio buttons you can only
one so if you need to have your choices
exclusive use radio buttons if you need
your choices to be not exclusive use
check boxes from the c++ side of Qt it
is possible to make check boxes also
exclusive but from QT quick I still have
to see a way to do that but you probably
not going to need that because radio
buttons are enough for this purpose okay
this is really all I wanted to show you
about the GroupBox component in the
next lecture we're going to look at the
page indicator component and how you can
use it with this wide view I'll see you
there