in this lecture we're going to look at
the progress bar to to quick component
you use this when you want to show the
progress of something that is going on
sometimes it is very similar to the busy
indicator that we have seen before but
it also can show specific progress of an
action if you happen to have the data
for that we're going to go to QT creator
and play with us
okay here we are in Qt creator we're
going to create our project the Qt Quick
application we're going to call it
progress bar demo save it in the usual
location yet next choose your QT version
and choose your desktop kit we are going
to change the title here and say
progress bar demo we want to import QT
quick controls 2.4 and we want
to lay things out from top to bottom
we're going to use a column component we
want it to be the same width as the
parent and we want some space and let's
do 20 let's see we'd like to see how
this looks
we want to put in a button component the
text is going to say start some action
and it's going to be in the center
horizontally down we want to input a
progress bar component we wanted to
start from one and finish at 100 we give
it an ID of progress bar and we wanted
to have a volume of 40 so what we want
to do is that when the user clicks we
want to change the value of this
progress bar to something else I'm going
to say onClicked
in the button and we like to do progress
bar value let's set this to 78 why not
we also want to Center this progress bar
so we can actually copy this and put it
here and run the application mm-hmm if I
click you see that the progress changes
this is one way to change the value in
the progress bar but you can also do
another kind of progress bar that
doesn't have a specific value to show
okay let's call this progress bar ID 1
to make it different from this we don't
need to specify from 2 of value
properties but you need to make it in
the terminal and you do it like this if
we run this we're going to see something
going on like this it basically is the
same as a busy indicator it is just a
different kind of that okay to make
things a little bit interesting and give
you a chance to do some practice we're
going to put a dial control on top of
the first progress bar here and what we
can do is basically very easy we change
this to a dial control let's call this
DialId the inside is not going to
change but when value changes okay we
want to change the value in the progress
bar we're going to say progress bar ID
we want the first one I'd say value
equals value the value from this dial
let's run the application
and you see that as I increase the value
in the progress bar also changes this is
cool isn't it, this should give you a
good introduction on how you work with
progress bars to show that something is
going on in the next lecture we're going
to look at another UI component and that
is range slider
I'll see you there