in this lecture we are looking at
another QT quick control component which
is range slider it basically allows you
to choose a range specifying the minimum
value and the maximum value let's go to
Qt creator and look at this okay
here we are in QT creator we are going
to create our new project QT quick
application it's going to be called
range slider demo save it in the usual
location and next choose your tutee
version your kit and next we want to
change the title here to range slider
demo and import our 2.4 quick
controls module to that form that is but
before we do anything with this land I
want to go to the documentation and show
it to you so we say a range slider
and if you look at it it is from the QT
quick controls module what it does it is
used to select the range specified by
two values by sliding each handle along
the track
you basically have something like this
let's go back to our code put in a row
component that is going to contain our
range sliders you want the spacing to
be 40 and the width is going to be the
same as for the parent inside we want to
put a range slider we don't wait anymore
if you go back to the documentation and
look at its properties you see that you
can specify the first value and the
second value the first value is
basically the starting value for your
range and the second value is the ending
value we want to specify a first value
of 25 and the second value
of 75 after we specify this we also have
to specify the from and to
properties because it needs to know the
range where it is operating okay we're
going to say from 1 and to 100 let's run
and you see our range slider here okay
if you move it you're going to change
the values for the first component and
you're going to change the value for the
second component by dragging this second
handle here if you need to know the
values as they change you can do
something like first on value changed
and you can counselor okay
and you can do the same thing for the
second value second let's run mm-hmm you
see that when you first run the
application
the signals are emitted okay as you drag
the first handle you're going to see the
value change okay you can drag it up to
the second handle you can't go past it
the second handle can be dragged up to
100 the maximum if you drag it down it
can't go past the first handle this is
what this control does if you happen to
need it it is available to you another
thing you should see is that you can
make this vertical okay you can
basically use the orientation property
okay and make it vertical
you want it is horizontal by default
we're going to copy this and come back
to our code and say orientation and
passing the vertical orientation if we
run this our rangerslider is vertical
okay when it is vertical the first
handle is to the bottom as you can see
here as we drag it we see that the first
value changes to something the second
handle is to the top okay this is weird
I thought that the first handle should
be to the top and the second one to the
bottom but you can play with us and
organize things as you want okay this is
all i have to say about the range
slider it is available to you if you
happen to need it in the next lecture
we're going to see how you work with the
flickable component and scrollbars I'll
see you there