in this lecture we are looking at the
slider QT quick control component, it
basically works the same as the range
slider that we have looked at in a
previous lecture but we only have one
handle with this control let's go to
Qt Creator and play with that okay
here we are in Qt creator we're going
to create a new project it's going to be
a QT quick application we call it slider
demo save it in the usual location and
finish we want to import QT quick
controls 2.4, change the title
here to say slider demo and we want to
put the Row component here the width is
going to be the same as the parent and
we're going to have some space and let's
do 20 inside we're going to have a
slider component it's going to start
from 1 and end at 100 and the value is
going to be let's do a 40 and we want to
know when the value changed ok so you're
going to say console.log before we run
we should come to the top and correct
here I always met this mistake the width
equals to the width of the parent
let's run mm-hmm we have a slider here
and as we move it to the right we
increase in volume and as we move it to
the left we decrease in value until we
reach the minimum value which is the
from value here to make things a little
bit interest
then I'm going to change this to the
column and below the slider I'm going to
put a progress bar we have worked with
this before it is a matter of changes
this to progress bar okay and when the
value changes in the slider we want to
change the value in the progress bar
okay let's say progress bar ID here
should start with the lower case letter
we don't want to know when the value
changes in the progress bar we just want
to see it but when the value changes in
the slider we want to change the volume
in the progress bar so we're going to
say progress bar ID value equals value
something like this from 2 and volume
should be like this this is okay if we
run and move this around you're going to
see that we move this slider and the
value in the progress bar also changes
and this is really all there is to
working with the slider but this is not
centered and I want my bars to always be
centered so I'm going to anchor.horizontalCenter
parent.horizontalCenter to
Center and do the same for the progress
bar run again this is better this covers
all we had to say in this lecture and
the next one we're going to look at
another Qt Quick control component
and that is switch I see you there