in this lecture we're going to look at
swipe view and page indicator controls
we're basically going to let the user
swipe through pages to select one page
or another and on the UI we are going to
put the page indicator to let the user
know which page they are at and all of
the user to navigate quickly to one
specific page let's go to Qt creator
and play with us okay here we are we are
going to create a new project
it's a Qt Quick application we call it
swipe view page indicator demo hit next
choose our QT version and we want to
choose the desktop Kit I recommend
running this on Android because this
project is a little bit fun but if you
don't have your virtual device around
you can only run on desktop that's fine
too hip next we are going to change this
title I think this is a good time to go
to the documentation and look at these
components we're going to type page
indicator ok you see that this is a
QtQuick control component and it gives
you things like that in this case we are
at page three and you see that the dot
is not like the others it is black while
the others are gray this is what this
control does and this is how you really
use it you can use it with multiple
components this is how you define your
page indicator we're going to play with
us in a minute and if we look at this
wipe if you control it also comes from
QT quick controls and it allows you to
navigate through pages okay so what
we're going to do is import QT quick
controls
they are 2.4 version and down here
we're going to put a SwipeView control
want to give it an id and we want it
to fill the parent, At the bottom of this
right view we want to put a page
indicator component you want to give it
an ID and we want to stick it to the
bottom of the window we're going to say
anchor is bottom parent bottom and we
are going to put a bunch of properties
that are specific to the page indicator
the first one is going to be current
index we wanted to know which page it is
at and the way you do that you give it
the current index for the SwipeView
would like to say SwipeView current
index because this SwideView has this
property too if you look there and go up
you're going to see that this container
inherits container and if we go to the
container component we're going to have
current index okay so this property is
available to us in the swipe view and
page indicator components we want these
to be interactive
we want the user to be able to click it
we need to tell it how many pages it is
dealing with and the way you do that you
use the count property and the count is
the same as the count in the swipe view
component so we're going to say
swipeViewId.count, we also need to swipeView
note the current index so
we're going to say current index equals
page indicator ID current index okay
they take data from each other so the
result of this is going to be that if
the user changes the current page from
the SwipeView then
the page indicator is going to know
and if you change the current page from
the page indicator, the SwipeView is
going to know, now that we have the swipeView
and it's basic properties set up
we need to give it the content to show
because right now it doesn't have
anything to show to make this a little
bit fun I am going to put in a image
component the source is going to be an
image from the internet we're going to
start with images from the internet and
then we're going to save them locally so
that you can play with this a little boy
let's copy this a couple of times say
image tune here an image 3 I am going to
grab a few images from our website I am
going to go to the blog and choose this
blog entry and I am going to choose
these images I can use okay so I am
going to select this image and copy
image location we're going to come back
to QT creator and paste the location of
that image these images are numbered in
increasing order so I'm going to paste
here again and say two and three okay
let's run to see what we have we're
going to have a swipe view to the top
and a page indicator to the bottom okay
you see that frame is loading and you
have the image here I like this but our
page indicator is not centered so we
should go back and look at that and see
if we did that no we didn't Center it so
we're going to say anchor.horizontalCenter
is parent.horizontalCenter
just like this run
again this is better wait a minute the
image is going to load it is here we can
swipe left and right to go through the
images we can also select through the
page indicator this is really good I
think this is the most fun application
we've done in this course and I like it
better okay now that we are getting
these images from the Internet
I want to also do the same but get the
images from the resource folder I am
going to comment these source property
out so that you have the same thing and
you can try to load images from
elsewhere it is going to work I am going
to put another source property here okay
the first thing I want to do is to go
where my project is stored I'm going to
right click on mainl.qml and
choose show in Explorer it's going to
open where my project is stored I'm
going to create the folder inside call
it images I am going to open the folder
and question the images that I have
prepared okay if you look it is the same
images that we had from the internet the
next thing I want to do is to add a new
resource file that is going to contain
those images so I'm going to go to the
resources folder add new select Qt and
choose new resource file we've done this
before
it next next we don't want any prefix so
we're going to deselect prefix check
this out and hit enter and we're going
to add files to this resource file of
ours we're going to select the three
images and when we do that
they became available here we need to
save this come back to our main KML file
and we can say images and you see that
they appear ok images to 1d second one
and here we say images three dot PNG
let's run again and now you see that the
images are loaded instantly because they
are local ok but it looks the same there
is no visual difference between loading
the image from the internet and loading
it locally I just wanted you to see
different ways to do the same thing
these covers all I had to say in this
lecture and the next one we're going to
look at the progress bar to the quick
control I see you there