The next thing we want to look at is the
"Image" element. And this is used to show
an image on your window. I want this to
have a width of 100 and height of 100. I
want this to be down below the "Text"
element. I'm going to give it an x of 10.
Why not? And a y of 150 so that it is
below this "Text" element which happens to
be at 100 in y coordinates. Okay, if we
run the application like this we're not
going to see anything.
Okay, that's because we didn't specify
the "source" property for the image that
we want to show. There are three
different ways you can specify an image
that you want to show in an "Image"
element. And we're going to look at the
first one. One thing you can do is showing
the image that is located in the working
directory of your project. And what is
the working directory of our project?
Let's go to "Projects" here and you can
see that we are working with the "Build settings".
Click on the "Run settings" and
you are going to see your working
directory here. In our case it is this
location here. So I can actually copy the
entire thing. Hit Ctrl+A and Ctrl+C to
copy. You can do equivalent commands on a
Mac. I am going to go in my file system
and paste in this location. Okay I'm
going to go there and I am going to
paste in an image that I had prepared on
my drive. It is a simple image. So now
that we have the image in our working
directory. We can say "File", say the name
of the file and pass in its extension.
And if we run the application now we
should see our image in this location.
Let's run the application. Mm-hmm... you see
"Learn Qt" here. This is the first way you
can pass your image. The second way is to
store this image in the resource folder
of your project. And the way you do that
even if you look here, you see that we
have a resource file that contains our
QML files. It is this qml.qrc file. But we
can add our own resource file to this
project. So we can click on the project,
add new, choose Qt, choose "Resource
file" and choose that, give it a name.
We're going to call it "resource". Hit
"Finish". And you see that this file is
opened here. It is saying "resource.qrc".
And you may notice that it is the
same extension as this qml.qrc file. Ok
so we want to add the prefix which is
what we would start our paths with if we
want it to point to a file that is in
this resource file. Hit enter. Because we
don't want any prefix and you can
click on "Add files" like this and choose
a file in here. But before we do that I'd
like to go where our main.qml file is
stored by right clicking on it and
choosing "Show in Explorer". And I am going
to add that image of ours in the images
folder that I am creating right now. Ok I
am going to paste in the image. You can
see that it is the same image. And now
that I have the image I can "Add files",
choose images and choose our image here.
Now I can go back to our QML file,
specify a second image. And by the way
you see that it is saying that "This file
or directory does not exist". Ignore this!
It is just QT creator not recognizing
that this file is actually existing. We
are going to position this thing at 150.
And here we are going to specify the
image from the resources. All you really
have to do is to specify the path to the
file relative to the location of the
main.qml file. And it happens to be in a
folder called "images" and you can see that Qt
Creator directly recognizes that this
file is existent. I think we should also
note that we are loading the image from
the working directory. And this first
image here, and in this case we are loading.
Ok, let's run the application. Ah...huh, "Learn
Qt". The first one is coming from the
working directory. The second one is
coming from the resource file. There is
another way we can do this, and that is
by specifying the full path to the image
that we want to show. Let's copy the
image. Show it at location 300. Why not?
Okay, if you look on my drive, in the
D:\artwork\ folder I have this image here. So
I'm going to copy its path. Note what we
are doing. And what we can do is saying "file"
specify 3 '/' like this. And
specify the path to the file. We are
going to use '/' and say "Learn
Qt.png" because that's the image that's
we want to use. If we run the application
we are going to see the same image. But
it will be coming from the full path of
the image. I can close this lecture
without showing you that you can also
load images from the Internet by
specifying the URL to the image. I am
going to extend the width of the Item
element to 600. Run again. And you're going to
see that we have a little more space to
work with. I am going to go to our
website and just grab some image. Okay so
I'm going to copy image location. And if
I paste this in another tab you're going
to see that. This is the path to this
image and we see it in our browser. So
what we can do
is copying this. Come back to Qt creator.
We are going to store this here. I don't
want to type all this things. So I am
going to just copy this. Put this here
and grab our URL to the image, and use it
as the source property for our image
here. We also want to move the image to
the right because we don't want it to
overlap with this image here. Actually
let's do that because I want you to
see this. I don't think that I showed you
this. Let's run. Mm-hmm, you see that this
is the image that is coming from the
Internet. But one thing is happening here.
You are seeing that the image from the
Internet is overlapping with the image
that we had that was coming from the
full path, which is this one here. So you
have to be careful to not make your
elements overlap if that's not what you
want to achieve because this can be very
hard to debug. So what we're going to do
is put this image at x of 415. And if we
run, things are going to be normal. Here
is our image from the Internet.
Okay, this covers all we set out to do in
this lecture. And I hope by now you have
a better idea of how you can work with
item Rectangle, Text and Image and how
you can use Item to group items together.
In the next lecture we're going to show
you how you can build your own items by
combining some of the items we've seen
in this lecture. I'll see you in the next
lecture.