and this lecture we are going to visit
some basic elements in qml this include
things like rectangle image and text but
before we start I'd like to visit one
element which is the parent of all the
visual elements that we have used so far
and many others and that element is
called item let's go to the
documentation and look at it which I can
item here hit enter and you choose item
qml type choose the letters version of
Qt have installed here and if you look
at the description it says the item type
is the base type for all visual items in
QT quack and if you look at the
properties that it has we have been
using some of these properties you can
see that it has properties of anchors we
have been using anchors sent in parent
there are many anchors as we are going
to see and this properties comes from
the parent item and other elements like
rectangle and text happen to inherit
this so what we're going to do is create
a critical project and play with this
dance for you to see them in action hit
file new project we call the project key
ml basic elements demo store it in a
location on our drive hit next and
choose your kit which is desktop for now
we're going to it next and finish we are
going to change the title here and
create an item element I think this is
the first time we use this we give it an
ID this property also comes from the
item we'll give it an X location of 50 a
Y location of 50 and by the way you can
specify your properties on one line like
this by separating them with a semicolon
the other thing you can do is this this
is also another syntax that is
acceptable in KML and I find myself
mixing distance
okay inside we're going to put a
rectangle you already know the rectangle
the width is going to be 15 the height
is going to be 15 the color is going to
be red and inside we're going to put in
a mouth area that is going to fill the
entire rectangle so it's going to say n
course and we want to know when this
mouth area is correct
the other thing we want to do is to give
this rectangle a fixed position we are
going to put in at X 10 + y 10 and we
are going to define other rectangles as
well just like this one but we are going
to change the x position and the cutter
so this one is going to be at X of 60
it's going to be green another one that
is going to be at 120 and it's going to
be blue and another one that is going to
be at 180 and it's going to be magenta
what do you think we'll see when we run
this application we're going to have
this item wrap around this rectangle and
the coordinates of laying out these
rectangles are going to start at this
location because this is the wrapper
container around these rectangles let's
run the application so that you see
yourself so what is happening the red
and green rectangles are touching each
other okay let's put this back to zero
so that they don't touch each other okay
this is much better to make things much
more visible I am going to assign a
child rectangle to this item and make it
feel the entire item so I'm going to do
something like this
and I'm going to give it a color of
beige okay why am I doing this it is
because the I am element doesn't support
this color property and I wanted to put
in a rectangle which has a background
color so that things are invisible I'm
also going to give this a border and we
are going to give our item here a width
and height so the width is going to be
something like 400 why not and the
height is going to be 300 let's run
mm-hmm and you see that our item is
wrapping around this beige rectangle and
you can see that the elements inside the
item are laid out in the coordinate
system of the item you can see that X is
zero for the red rectangle and Y is 10
starting counting from the origin of the
item rectangle I hope this makes sense
and the others also keep increasing in X
the green rectangle is at a slightly
higher value of x and the some things
happen for the blue rectangle and the
magenta rectangle here ok one thing you
should notice is that there are some
properties that come from the item
element and some of these are I D X Y
width and height if we go back to the
documentation we're going to see those
you see X Y Z we have the width here and
if we go up we can find the height here
so these are the properties that are
coming from the item but there are
properties that the item doesn't have
and some of those include color and
border here because an item is not
supposed to be visible it can't have a
color like rectangle does one thing I
want you to see is that you can use the
item element to wrap around other items
we have actually done that by setting
the X&Y position for the item element
you can see that they start here so if I
comment out this
you wait to see that this beige
rectangle which is our item really is
going to move back to 0-0 from the
parent which is this window element
let's run again okay you see that it
starts at zero we are able to manipulate
all these elements just by manipulating
the X&Y position of the item element and
I hope this drives home the point that
you can use the item element to group
different elements together and carry
out group manipulations to the contained
items let's uncomment this back and give
it an x value of 150 why not run again
and you see that it moves slightly to
the right
another element I want you to look at is
the text element so let's use it down
here we give it an ID and we can give it
a text property which is the text that
is going to be shown so we can type in
here
this is my text and if we run this what
shall we see let's run you see that we
see this is my text to the top of the
rectangle that wraps around our item
element and the text is shown at
position zero zero which means that when
you don't specify the X&Y position for
your element it is going to be at zero
zero okay you should know this because
we want our text to show down below the
rectangles we are going to give it an x
value of let's say 100 and the y value
of 100 another thing we can specify for
this text element is the size of the
font and we do that by using their
grouped font property and calling point
size we can specify 20 here let's see
what we get mm hmm this is my text these
are the different basic properties you
can use on the text element and
as usual if you need to know more about
it you can select it hit f1 and you're
going to have its documentation up in
the text items can display both plain
text and rich text for example red text
with the specific font and size can be
defined like this hello world font
family her vertical point size desu and
color red let's actually copy this why
not come back to our text and put in
these properties hey control a control I
to align distance run again mm-hmm and
we have our text here and the font
property deserves a little bit more
attention because I don't think we
talked about it yet the font property is
a grouped property and that refers to
the fact that you can call font family
font down point size so to look at this
property let's go back to the
documentation and type the font click on
the latest version of cute we have
installed and you can see a font value
with the properties of cue font okay
it's like a cue font data type from the
c++ side of cube it is a grouped
property which means that it has many
properties grouped together you can
specify the family of the font you can
specify whether or not it's bold italic
underline point size and many others you
can use the font like this and this is
really what we have been doing they just
specify more properties than we did we
can copy this then and take it out and
we can specify these properties on one
line like this if you want to it's going
to work okay it's bold now another way
you can specify the font is by grouping
things together like
so you can say font-family just like
this and keep specifying the other
properties on different lines and
whether or not it is bold if you run the
application we are going to see the same
thing okay the same time and these are
different syntaxes that are available to
you to specify grouped properties
another thing you can do if you want to
is to specify this stance on one line
we're going to do that
you can actually copy this put this on
one line and separate things using
semicolons like this and this is going
to work as well okay this is the 10th
element and how you can specify some of
its properties