In this lecture I'm going to show you
how you can build your own components by
combining the elements that we have seen
like rectangle, text and images. Let's go
to QT creator and see how we can do that.
Okay, here we are in QT creator. We are
going to create our project as usual. It
is an application in QT quick one. We
call it custom component demo, store it
in our usual location. Choose the QT
version and we choose this desktop kit.
And we have our project here. But before
we start I would like to show you a
component that we are going to need. And
that one is "Column". Okay, it is an element
that you used to group elements together.
Let me show you what I mean. I'm going to
define two rectangles inside. This is
going to have a width of 300 height of
100 and a color of "red". And we are going
to put another one inside. And it's going
to be "blue". Let's run. And we should have
two rectangles laid out on top of each
other.
Mm-hmm this is what we have. This is what
this element does. It allows you to lay
things out from top to bottom. And you
can use some properties of the column to
control how they are laid out. For
example, you can specify the spacing
between these elements. Let's use 20 and
see what we get. Mm-hmm this is what we
have. There is another element that you
can use to lay this thing out from left
to right. And that is called "row". You
might have guessed that. Okay, left to
right. I am mentioning these elements
here because we are going to use them to
make a point that we want to make in
custom components. Now that we know this.
Let's comment this out. We are going to
build a button that the user can click
on and that button is going to be based
on rectangle. So it's going to be a red
and inside we are going to have a "Text
Element" and the text is going to say "Button".
For now the rectangle is going
to have a few properties. So it's going
to have a red color. And it's going to
have a border. Let's use group properties.
The color of the border is going to be
"blue". And the width of the border is
going to be, let's say, 3. We should
use a semicolon here. Sorry for that. The
text is going to have an id. And we want
the rectangle to have the width that
depends on this text so that it wraps
around them. So the way we're going to do
that, we're going to say the width of the
rectangle equals the buttonTextId
implicit width. And this is its width.
After it has been assigned width that
matches the text that is inside. I hope
this made sense. And we are going to add
a margin to it, like this. We are going to
do the same thing for the height. Button-
TextId.implicitHeight and add a margin
of 20. Let's see how our button looks. Run
your application. We should center the
text. So that's easy to do. You can say
anchors.CenterIn "parent". Run again. Fnd
the text is in the middle. But we have a
problem. The color should be wrapped in
quotes like this. That's an easy fix.
Okay we have our border. We should make
this button clickable. So we add a MouseArea.
It is going to fill this rectangle.
So say anchors.fill
"parent". By the way I am always using
parent here with the anchor.fill
property. But you can feel free to also
specify the idea of this rectangle if
you happen to have specified. I leave it
to "parent" because that's what I'm used
to. But you can experiment with that. So
onClicked we are going to say
console.log, "Clicked ON" and say what we
click on. We are going to say the
text that is in the Text Element. So
we're going to say buttonTextId.text.
I want you to see that you cannot
directly call a text property if you are
not in this element. If you do this and
click you are going to have a problem.
Because text is not defined here it is
also not defined in the parent element
which is rectangle here. Let's run the
application and tell you what I mean.
Okay if you click it is going to say
"Text is not defined" because it is not
defined. And this MouseArea here, so you
should use the buttonTextId to specify
where this text element is coming from.
So we should say button and that like
this. And if we run it is going to work.
"Clicked ON button". Now we have our button
which I click. But we would like to use it
multiple times and we don't want to
copy all these things. So what makes sense
is to create a separate component. Put
this rectangle in and instantiate it
whenever we need it. Let me show you what
I mean. I am going to go to our resource
file here and add new Qt QML file, Qt Quick 2.
We are going to call this MButton
because it is our button. And the
Qt quick version and these templates is
usually very old so you
can refer to the project that we created.
You see that the 2 Qt Quick version is
2.11. So we can update this here and copy
the rectangle we have here and bring it
in the button here. Let's take this item
out. And we have our rectangle. If we come
to the main element and say M button.
Okay you see that it is recognized and
we can instantiate it like this. Let's
say button. Ah ha, we have a button here and
we can click on it. We can actually
specify another one. Let's say MButton
again and see if we can specify the x
location 100. Why not? Run again. Mm-hmm it
is at 100. Everything looks fine. Okay our
button is working as we want. But there's
one problem. Sometimes you want to
specify the text that is shown in this
button because we don't want it to
always say button. Okay so how do you do
that? The way you do that, we can use a
property
"alias". What do I mean? You can do
something like "property alias buttonText" and
link this to buttonTextId.text. Okay
and when we specify buttonTextId now.
Let's set this first.
And if we run the application. You
are going to see that. It says button 1
and button 2. If you click on this it
says "Clicked ON: Button 1". If you click on
this it says button 2. We are defining
our own component and we are able to
expose some properties of this inner
component. But sometimes you don't want
other people to be able to access all
your properties in your components. For
example users can change the width and
height of the rectangle and the color
and the border. But we don't want that.
The way you do that, you wrap your
components into an "Item" component just
like this. And put it inside. And what you
have to do is to expose your properties
the same way you've been doing. And you
have to expose your properties at the
root level of your parent item. Ok the
parent item is this item here. And we
should give it an id. And this is where
we expose our properties. If we run the
application it is going to look like
it's working as expected. We click on
button, you see, button 1. You click on
button 2, you see button 2. But the user
has no way to specify what happens when
this button is clicked. And we need to
expose this signal. The way you do that,
you specify "signal" like this and say
buttonClicked. And when the user clicks
in the MouseArea you want to call your
signal here. And this is a signal that
the user can specify here. So we are
going to comment this out because we
don't want it to confuse us. We are going
to say rootId because it is at this
level that the signal is defined, and say
buttonClicked like this. Ok, now the user
can say
onButtonClicked use something, say
console.log. And we can do the same thing
for the button 2. And we are saying
from main file so that there is no
confusion about where this signal is
coming from, even if we commented this
out I am this paranoid. Run the
application, click button 1. Clicked on
button one from main file we are able to
capture this signal that the button has
been clicked. And the same thing happens
to button 2. We are almost done with this.
But when we try to wrap our buttons here
in a "Row" component let's do that or a
"Column". Let's use a "Column". I'll have to
lay my things out from top to bottom. Ok
put this in a "Column". And because the
column is taking care of our positioning
we don't want to specify this x anymore.
So let's take this out. Run the
application. And what we're going to see
is going to be very surprising. You see
that? We only see button 2? What is that?
What is happening here is: our "Column" is
trying to position these items but it
doesn't know the width and the height of
this button of ours. Notice that we
didn't expose the width and the height
of this rectangle. And it is impossible
for the "main" file to know the width of
this rectangle because we didn't expose
it. So if we want row and column to
position our custom component very well
we should expose the width and height.
You should remember this because these
errors are very hard to debug. And I've
had students come to me many times about
this problem so you should really focus
on this when you define your own
components. You should make sure that
they have a width and height as opposed
to external thermal files.
And the way you expose these properties,
you give your rectangle an id. So you say,
for example, and simply expose the width
to be container... and the height to be...
Okay, and this takes care of exposing
these properties to the outside world. I
am going to go to the "main" file. Run
again. Mm-hmm... and you see that it looks
like nothing changes. This is
because Qt Creator sometimes has a
problem when you change other files that
the "main" file is using you have to come
to the "main" and make it look like
something changed. So we are going to
click to our space here. Run again. And
you see that our buttons are now
positioned very nicely. I like this
better. And I hope this really exposes
you 2 ways you can define your run
components. You put them in a different
file. When you put them in that file and
that file happens to be in the same
location as the "main" file you don't have
to do anything. You just call your
components like we did here, for MButton.
Another thing you should do is to wrap
your components into Item to kind of
control what properties are visible to
the outside world. For example, we
wouldn't want people to be able to
change the color. Let's see what would
happen when we try to set the color
property to this MButton of ours. Let's
do that. You should try things out. You
see that color is not recognized. If you
try to run it's going to warn you of
this problem. It's probably going to say
color is not defined: "Cannot assign to a
non-existent property "color"". Okay, so this
is not exposed you can see that. You can
make your properties of your elements
private by wrapping your component into
an Item. And this is really important to
do. Another thing you saw is how you can
expose signals. You can
expose your signals by declaring your signal
like this and then calling it when
something happens. Let we did here. And
last but not least you should always
specify width and height for your custom
components. Otherwise you're going to
have problems laying them out in
positioners like "Row" and "Column". These
covers always set out to do in this
lecture and the instructor. We're going
to start look at user input elements in
QT quick. I'll see you in the next
lecture.