In this lecture we're going to look at
signals and slots in QT quick. Signals
and slots allow you to do communication
between different objects. You basically
have an object that has a piece of
information. And you have another object
that is interested in that piece of
information. And what Qt allows you to
do is to allow to transfer that piece of
information between the objects using
the signals and slots mechanism. This
mechanism is based on the observer,
design pattern. And in this pattern you
basically have an object listening gone
on a piece of information coming from
another object. Okay, so we have a
notifier object that has the information
to share. And we have a receiver object
that is interested in the information. In
practice and specifically in QML,
you do the connection using a connection
statement as we're going to see. And when
you've done the connection and the
notifier sends the signal the receiver
is going to receive the signal and act
upon it. And if you want to learn more on
this concept you can visit this link
here. But the book of it is explained
here. You basically have two objects. The
sender fires the signal and sends it to
be received by interested objects. And
the receiver listens in on the signal
and that's something when the signal is
fired. Don't worry if this doesn't make
sense yet. We're going to show you
exactly how you work with us in
QML. Okay, now we want to see how you
declare your signal. In here you see that
we have a "Rectangle" object. We have our
usual properties but we have something
new here. We have a "signal" keyword. And
then we have something that looks like a
function. This is how you declare your
signal. We are declaring the signal that
is called "greet" and it has a parameter.
Notice that we have only one parameter
but we can have as many parameters as we
want. When you declare a signal like this
a handler for that signal is
automatically generated for you. It
happens in the same way that we have
handlers when the properties that we
have here changed. For example
when the color changes we can be
notified in the on color, change setting
up. We have been using this quite a lot.
It is the same thing for the signal
but the handler naming is a little bit
different. The handler for this one is
going to be onGreet and it's not going
to be on reads changed. You just need to
know this the rest is really similar as
we are going to see. Now you know how to
declare you signal. The next thing you
need to know is how to fire the signal
that you have declared. And the way you
do it, you just call it like a function.
In the previous slide
notice that we defined our signal to be
greet(). That's a parameter that is a
strength. And notice that you have to
specify the type of the parameter here.
And when we want to fire it. For example
in here we want to fire it. When somebody
clicks in this MouseArea we call the
great signal that is in the rectangle
that is identified by RectangleId. And
if you go back you see that where
rectangle here is RectangleId. And this
is really all the need to fire in your
signal. You call it as you call a normal
JavaScript function in your QML. Cool?
Okay, right now we have declared a signal.
We have fired it to send the information.
Now we need to connect the receiver so
that it knows about the signal and that
it can do something when the signal is
emitted or is fired. The first thing you
need to do is to define a slot and the
slot is a normal JavaScript function. But
it has a property of being capable of
being linked to a signal. If you look
here we have a normal JavaScript
function that is called myGreeting. It
takes a parameter called mMessage and
it has a body inside. In JavaScript every
function you define can act as a slot.
This is a special behavior in QML and
you need to be aware of it. Every
JavaScript function can work as a slot.
In other words you can connect it to a
signal. And how do you do the connection?
You use this syntax we have here. We are
connecting the signal to the slot in
uncompleted method of our component. And
the way you do that, you type the name of
your signal, you type a dot (.) and you type
"connect". And then you type the name of
the slot function that you have defined.
In our case our signal is called greet
and our slot is myGreeting here. Notice
that we don't pass in parameters here.
But when you want to use the parameters
in your slot you just use the parameters
name that you used when you define the
function. For example here if we want to
use the parameter that is passed by the
Signal we're going to refer to that using
mMessage here. And you see that we did
that here in the console log message in
our slot. Okay, this is really all you
need to know to start working with
signals and slots. In your QML,
code you need to know how to declare
your signal, you need to know how to fire
it and you need to know how to connect
it to a slot. In the next lecture we're
going to open a QT creator project and
actually start playing with us. I'll see you
there.