In this lecture we are playing with
signals and slots in Qt Quick
hands on. Let's open QT creator and do
that. Okay here we are in QT creator.
We're going to create our project, "File"
=> "New project". It's a "QT quick application".
We call it SignalsAndSlotsDemo, save
it in a location on our drive. Hit "Next",
choose your QT version, choose your Kit
and "Finish". We want to change the title
here to "Signals and Slots Demo". And
inside we want to put a "Rectangle"
component. The "id" is going to be
rectangleId. It's going to have a width
of 200 and a height of 300. And we want
to give it a red color. Inside we want to
put a MouseArea. We want it to fill the
parent. And it's going to fill this
rectangle here, its parent. And we want to
know when it is clicked. You already know
how to do this. Now we want to define our
first signal. You define the signal using
the syntax we have seen before. So we say
"signal", we say the name of the signal
which is really like the name of the
function. And you pass in the parameters
to your signal. One special thing you
need to know is that you need to pass in
a data type for the parameters that you
pass in your signals. So in our case it's
going to be a string and we're going
to call it "message". And just like this
you are declaring your signal. Let's flag
that. Usually after you define a signal
you want to send it, you want to fire it,
you want people interested in your data
to know that you have sent the data. And
the way you do that you simply call your
signal
as a method.
And passing any parameter that you have
to pass in. In our case we are going to
go in the onClicked handler of our
MouseArea and we are going to say greet
"Hello there". Okay we are firing our
signal here. And any interested object is
going to know that we sent this message
here. Okay, we fired the signal "greet" and
it has a parameter that is a string.
Because we specify the string data type
here. Okay, let's finish this. Now that we
have our signal, we need to define a slot
that we want to connect to it. And
remember a slot is a normal JavaScript
function. Okay, so we can also define our
slot inside this Rectangle here. So say
function myGreeting and you pass in a
parameter. Let's call it mMessage to
have things a little bit different. And
inside we can do whatever we want, really.
In this case we are going to console.log
the parameter here "myGreeting slot
called..." and we say what the parameter is.
And it is going to be mMessage like we
have it in here. Now we have a slot. We
have our signal, how do we connect them?
We want to connect them when this
component here is loaded completely. So
we're going to say Component.onCompleted.
Okay notice that this signal
is at the root level of this rectangle
here and the rectangle contains this
component. So we don't need to call this
signal by passing in the "id" here. But you
can pass it in if you want. But in our
case for readability we're not going to
put it in. So we're going to say greet.connect.
This is how you do it. And we
want to pass in the name of the slot
that we want to connect to. The slot is
going to be myGreeting. And just like
this you have connected this signal that
is greet to the slot that is myGreeting.
So what is going to happen when we
run the application? We're going to have
a rectangle. We're going to have this
width. It's going to be this color of red.
When we click in the rectangle that is
covered by this MouseArea. We are going
to fire the greet signal and we're going
to pass in "Hello there". When the signal
is emitted because of this connection
here this slot is going to be called and
we are going to see the parameter that
was passed as a result of this
connection. We're going to see "Hello
there" even if we didn't type it in here.
Let's run the application. Mm-hmm... we are
here. When we click we should see the
console of the message from the myGreeting
function and the string that we
passed them when we called the greet
signal here. Okay so fingers crossed.
Let's click. "Greet is not defined", why is
that? Mm-hmm... looks like I was wrong. You
have to pass in the "id" of the component
where the signal is defined. So we're
going to say rectangle, I'd be here, greet.
And we're going to do the same. Wherever
we refer to the signal and we want to do
the same to the slots too. Okay, so this
is a good learning trend. You need to
remember this. Whenever you connect your
signals to your slots you need to pass
in this "id" here. Let's run again. If we
click we say "myGreeting slot called. The
parameter is: Hello there. Okay, we are
successfully connecting this signal to
this slot. And the syntax you use is this
one, you do signal that connect and you
pass in your slot. And you need to refer
to the components where the signal and
the slot are located.
In the last lecture I mentioned that
just like when you define a property
here and you have an automatic handler
generated for you. For example, if we say
onColor you see that we have a handler
called onColorChanged. And you have the
same for every property that you have
defined in here. In the same way when you
define a signal here you have an
automatic handler that says the name of
the signal. For example, you can have
handler that is called onGreet and this
handle is fired whenever this signal is
emitted. Okay, let's try this. And
console.log. Let's say "onGreet: Greet
signal emitted. Let's run again. Click
here. You see that this method is called
whenever we emit the great signal. Okay,
if you are interested in doing something
when this signal is emitted you can do
that here. Okay, and this is the same
behavior just like when you see the
width change in the onWidthChanged
signal handler here. To try this out, I am
going to define a property here. In the
root level of the window I'm going to
say property integer. Let's call this
"increment" and give it a value of 50.
We're going to make the width of the
rectangle depend on this increment value.
So we're going to do a property binding.
We're going to make it 200 plus
increment and every time we emit the
greet signal we want to change the
increment in the myGreeting slot here. So
we're going to say increment +=
50 which is really another way of saying
increment
equals increment + 50. It is the same
thing in case this confuses you. Okay,
right now, if we run the application
every time we click on the MouseArea we
are going to emit the greet signal
because of the connection that happened
in the uncompleted signal handler of
component. We are going to call the slot
here and we are going to increment the
increment here. When we increment this
because of the property binding we have
here the width is going to change of this
rectangle. Let's run the application.
Print this up. If we click you see that
the width of the rectangle changes and
this is property binding shown to you
again in action. And this is really all.
There is to declaring signals, firing
signals and connecting them to slots. In
the next lecture we're going to define
two external components have: one emit
the signal and have the other. We'll see it.
I'll see you there.