In this lecture we are going to define
two external components. We have one sends the
signal and have the other receives that.
We're going to go to Qt Creator and
do that. Okay, here we are in QT creator.
We're going to create our project the Qt
Quick application as usual we call it
ExternalComponentSignalSlotDemo. Save
it in the usual location. Hit "Next".
Choose our Qt version. Choose that kit
and "Finish". We want to change the title
here and we want to add two components:
one is going to be "Notifier" and the
other is going to be "Receiver". We click
on qml.qrc here to add a new file. It's
going to be a QML file. This is going to
be "Notifier". We want to add another one
that is going to be the "Receiver" and
we want to "Finish".
Notice that this Qt quick import is old.
We are using 2.11 in "main" so we should
change that to 2.11. Inside this item
here we want to put a "Rectangle". We want
to give it an id, a width of 200, a height of 200
and a color. Let's make it "red". Inside we
want to put the Text component. The id is
going to be displayTestId. It's
going to be centered in the parent. And
we want to make it a little bigger. So
we're going to say font pointSize. Let's
do 12. We're going to see how this one is.
We want to come to the root level here
and define a property. It's going to be
an integer.
We're going to call this "count" and it's
going to start at 0. The text of the Text
item is
to be the "count" just like this. So what
we wanted to have is to have a Rectangle
that is clickable and when you click it
this "count" increases and we can see the
count in the Text component here. So
let's put a MouseArea component that is
going to fill the rectangle, anchors.fill,
parent, onClicked. We want to
increment the "count" by one so we're
going to say count++ like
this. And when we do that the number that
we see in the Text component here is
going to increase. So to be able to use
our "Notifier" component here, in positions
like Row and Column we need to expose
the width and the height here. Let's do
that. So we're going to say width equals
notifierRectId.width and height is going to be
notifierRecId.height just like this.
We also want to expose the color of the
rectangle here so that users of this
component of ours can have the
flexibility to set the color. So we're
going to expose it using the property
alias, "property alias". Let's say rectColor
And it's going to be "notifier"
color, just like this. We can now save
this, come back to "main" and inside define
and notify your component just like this.
We can run the application and see if it
works
as we want so far. We're going to have a
red rectangle in the top left of the
window just like this. And if we click it,
it should increment and show us the
number going up. So we should have 0, 1,
2 and going up like this. This is what we
want. I also want to increase the pointSize
for the text in here. We made it 12.
I want to make it 20
and see how it works. Because we are
changing the code in the component in an
external QML file. Sometimes QT Creator
doesn't pick up those changes unless
you come to the "main" file and apply some
changes. So I am adding a few spaces here.
You may need to do this if you see that
your changes are not applied. And I like
this text better. Okay now we have our
Notifier component. The information we
want to send is this "count" here. Okay, we
are having it here and displaying it. But
we want other external components to
have this piece of information. So we're
going to define a signal that is called
"notify". And it's going to pass a
parameter that is a string and it's
called "count". We want it like this. We
have declared our signal. We want to fire
it. And we're going to fire it whenever
it changes here. So after we increment
the "count" we should say notify(count). And
our signal is emitted. So what I want to
do is to build up the "Receiver" object.
Because everything is pretty similar
I'm going to Ctrl+A, copy to the
entire "Notify" object. We're going to save it.
Come to the "Receiver", Ctrl+A, delete
everything put in the "Notifier" object
and take out what we don't need. We want
to take out the "property int count" here.
And the "signal notify...", we don't need
that in the "Receiver". But we want to
change the ids here. So we're going to
say a receiverRectId and change this
wherever we had that. We're going to say
copy, paste here, paste here, paste here... We
also want to expose the color. There's no
reason not to do it. We also want to say
receiver
DisplayedTextId. We want its text to
start at 0 like this. And we don't
want it to be clickable because it's not
going to be sending out any signal. It is
a "Receiver". But we want to define a slot
inside and it is this slot that is going
to be connected to the signal from the
"Notifier". So we're going to say "function".
Remember it is a normal JavaScript
function "receiveInfo". It's going to
receive "count". And we want to use this
"count" to do 2 things: one is set the
text of this Text component here. So
we're going to say receiverDisplayTextId.text
equals "count". This is done and we
want to console.log. We're going to say
"Receiver". And we're going to say the
number that we received which is the
"count" here. Okay, this is all we want. We
have our "Notifier" and we have our
"Receiver". So what we can do is come back
to "main". Let's save this first. Come back
to "main" and define a "Receiver" we want to
anchor the receiver to the right so that
we can say it. So we're going to say
"anchors.right:parent.right". It's going to
be forced to be to the right side of the
window and we want to give them colors
because we can do that. We're going to
say red color. Let's make this "yellowgreen".
The "Receiver" is going to be
"dodgerblue". Why not?
"yellowgreen". This is better. We want to
save everything. Run the application. We
have our 2 rectangles. When we click on
the first one the data changes but the
"Receiver" is not receiving the messages
because we haven't connected the signal
from the
center to the slot of the "Receiver".
That's what we want to do next. Okay you
can do your connections wherever you
want. In this case we want to do it when
the "Notifier" component is loaded
completely. So we're going to go inside
the "Notifier" and do Component.onCompleted.
We want to do "notify". Remember
it is a signal of this "Notifier"
component. We want to say "connect" and we
want to say "receiverId". Notice that
we didn't put in this id here. So we
should do that "id:receiverId". And
let's give the "Notifier" an id too. So
we're going to say "notifierId". So we want
to call the slot from the "Receiver". And
just like this we have done our
connection, "Connect signal to slot".
This is how you do it. If everything is
all right we're going to see the data
change in the receiver object and we are
going to see this message here. Let's run
the application. Fingers crossed. And you
see that? As we increase in the center we
also increase in the "Receiver". Our
connection in the "main" file is working.
And we just leave the connection here. But
nothing prevents you from taking it out
of here and putting it at the root level
when the entire window is loaded. For
this to work you need to pass in the id
of the "Notifier". So we'd like to say
"notifierId" and '.' like this. Let's run
again to see if it still works.
And just like we expect, our things work.
The next thing I want to show you is
that you can also wrap
the connection in the "Notifier" object
and not have to do it right here. The way
you can do that you can come to the
"Notifier" object and give it a property
of the target element that is going to
provide the slot. You can say "property"
the data type is going to be "Receiver".
And we are going to call it "target". And
it's going to be "null" by default because
we don't want to specify it. But we want
to be notified when the target is set.
And we are going to capture that in the
onTargetChanged signal. Because when
you set it, it changes and we want to do
the connection. Okay we want to say
notify.connect(target.receiveInfo),
just like this. Okay let's set this and
what you would need to do in the
"Notifier" object is take out this
connection here because you don't want
to do this twice. And specify a target.
Okay so you're going to say "target" and
it's going to be "receiverId". Okay just
like this you see that we don't have any
connection here. We did everything in the
"Notifier"
object by giving it a "Receiver". It is "null"
by default. But when we set it here the
onTargetChanged signal is fired and we
are doing the connection.
Okay the connection is made when we
define this "target" here. I hope this
makes sense.
If we run you're not going to see any
difference. Click and you see the signal
sent by the "Notifier" and received by our
"Receiver" component here. I really hope
this nails down the way you work with
signals and slots into amount because
it's really simple. You define your
signal, you fire it, and then you plug
it into a slot. And just like that you can
pass data back and forth between your
components. In the next chapter, we're
going to look at user Input elements. I'll
see you there.