In this lecture we're going to download
the tools were going to need in this
course. We're going to download the Qt
framework itself and we were also going
to download QT creator the IDE we're
going to be using. We're going to get our
tools from this link here so we're going
to go there in our browser. And here we
are. One might want to go directly to the
qt website and try to click on this
download button. But they do take you
through a number of steps that I'm not
willing to go through right now. So let's
go directly to the download page, click
on official releases here and we click
on the qt and we are shown the
versions that are available for a qt
here. We're going to choose the latest
version, which is at the moment 5.10 so
we go in there. And we choose 5.10.1.
In here we see a number of versions
we can choose from. We see QT versions
for Windows, we can choose a QT version
for Linux and a QT version for a Mac. I
am on a Windows machine right now I'm
going to choose this one:
QT-opensource-windows-x86-5.10.1.exe.
I'll click on it and I am
given this window to confirm that I want
to download it, so I click save file and
my download starts here. I already have
the file downloaded to save time so I'm
going to cancel out of this. You should
download it if you don't have qt
downloaded already. And I'm going to open
the folder where I have it downloaded.
I'm going to double click on it and they
tell you to open a qt account and
things like that. We're not going to go
through this click Next and right now we
don't want to open a QT account so skip.
Hit next and you are given an option to
choose where you want to install qt.
Mine is going to be installed in "C:\Qt\Qt5.10.1".
You can choose a location
you like or you can leave the
if that's okay with you. We're going to
click Next. So I have installed this
before but you're not going to have this
error, so I'm going to continue. On this
screen you can choose the tools that you
want to install we want to install QT
creator so we selected here under tools
and we're going to install the QT
pre-built components for mingw. I choose
mingw because it's a free compiler so
it's freely available anywhere on
Windows, Mac and Linux. And we're going to
be using it. On Windows you should also
know that you can use microsoft visual
studio compiler, we're not going to
choose it here but you can choose it if
you have this IDE from Microsoft
installed.
I also recommend checking the check
boxes for android x86 and android arm v7
because in this course we are going to
run our applications on Android. We
mainly need x86 because it makes it very
fast to run your applications on virtual
devices but if you happen to have a real
devices running this architecture it is
also going to be useful. So please make
sure these two check boxes are checked
android x86 and android arm v7. We're
going to hit next and we are given an
option to accept the license or deny it.
So we're going to accept
hit next and we're going to start our
installation. You can click on show
details here and they're going to show
you the progress of your install. Okay
our download is done right now and you
can see the result of our download. They
say that QT has been installed, they tell
us the location where it is installed
and where we can see the change log for
that. Okay so we hit next and we choose
to launch QT creator but let's not launch
it right now. We're going to close this. I
want you to see where it is installed
and how to start it just in case you
have some down.
So you click on start here and they
showed QT creator here but we're not
going to click that either. So you go
down we find QT 5.10.1 and we can click
on it. You can see that I have qt 5.5
installed, I have some projects that
are using it but you can have multiple
versions of qt installed so you should
know that. So we'd like to go in here
click on QT creator 4.5.1 and
open it. Ok here is QT creator opened
ready for you to use. If you look on the
left here we have a few tabs and you can
click around and see things. We're going
to explain the UI of QT creator in an
upcoming lecture. What we're going to do
is create one graphical user interface
project so that you see what QT creator
is capable of. So hit file - new project, we
choose QT widgets application. You have
to choose where you want to put your
project. In my case I want to put it in
D:\OnlineCourses\3.Qt gui\CourseCode and call it
1-2QtcreatorDemo. I hit next.
I choose widget application. You don't
have to don't worry if you don't
understand all of this I'm going to
explain this in upcoming lectures. For
now I just want you to be able to run
something for the first time
in qtcreator. hit next next again and finish.
Ok our project is generated and this is
what the QT C++ project looks like. For
now you don't need to look at the code
all you have to do is click on this
green button to run your project and
make sure it works. You can click on this
tab here down compiled output to see the
progress of how you
application is being worked. And you see
that they say that the process of
building our application exceeded
normally. So we can see our app here and
now this is not very exciting but for
now you know that your tools are working
and we can start building QT applications.
And we're going to learn the building
blocks of how you do that in the
reminder of this course. Okay that's all
I had to say in this lecture you have QT
creator installed you run your first
project. In the next lecture we're going
to look at the user interface of QT
creator and try to explain it a little
bit more. I'll see you there.