In this lecture we are going to build
our first qml application and run it in
Qt creator. And along the way we're going
to see some tips to go by when building
your Qt applications when using Qt quick.
Let's head to Qt creator and do that.
Okay here we are in Qt creator, we're
going to create a new project. We're
going to go to file - new file or project.
We're going to choose application. And we
are going to choose Qt quick application.
We want to start with this empty
template so we're going to click on it,
choose next we are going to call it QtQuickAppDemo.
We want to use this as
the default project location. We hit next
you want to use the latest version of
Qt you have installed. Mine is 5.11
right now. Hit next you are going to
choose the kit you are going to use for
your project. In our case we want to
develop for desktop. I am going to show
you how to run your Qt quick
applications on mobile devices on the
Android platform later. But for now we choose
was desktop because we just want to get
started. Hit next and hit finish. The
first thing I want to do is to go
through the files that are generated for
us. And go through them to show some of
the things they can help us with. The first
one is the project file if you have
worked with Qt before you know that
this is the file that ties all your
files in the project together.
It shows what files are in your project
for now you see that we have a source
file of main.cpp which is a C++ file. And
we have another file that contains our
resources which is called qml that Qt
assists. We're going to ignore this
things down below here for the moment.
And if you look at the files that we
have on the left here you see that we
have a sources folder, inside we have the
main CPP file. And if you open it you see
that it is a C++ file even if we are
going to be working with Qt quick, Qt
quick works
with C++ behind the scenes and it needs
a way to run. And we use this thing
called QmlApplicationEngine here to
load our qml file that we show when we
run the application. We're going to run
it in a moment but I just want you to
have a feel of what is available in your
project. If you look down here we have
another folder called resources, this is
the folder that is going to contain the
files that your application is going to
need. They are wrapped in resources here
because resources are bundled into the
executable of your application when you
distribute it to the user,
making sure that the files that are
critical for your application to run are
always available. Inside the resource
files we had this main.qml and this is
the main of the code and this is where
we're going to spend most of our time in
the course. Ok so this is what qml code
looks like. Ok now that we know what is
available in this project let's run the
application. And this is what we have a
boring window that called hello world in
the title. This is your minimal qml
application let's do something a little
bit interesting inside so that we don't
have an empty window. So we're going to
write Text and this creates a text
component inside our window here. So
we're going to give it the text to show
let's say: Hello World. We want it to be in
the middle the window so the way we do
that we say anchors.centerIn: parent. I
don't expect you to understand
everything right now I just want you to
have something to show in the window. And
I'm going to get a chance to explain all
these things in the course. Ok so we want
to set the color for the text. I want to
make it red for example. And I want to
make the font a little bit bigger so I'm
going to say font.pointSize let's make
it 20.
Let's run the application. And you see
that in the middle we have a text that
says Hello World. This is what qml code
looks like you have some imports on the
top here to import some components that
you're going to use. This is where all
these components are coming from, the
text is coming from, the Qt quick window
is coming from, Qt quick window here. And
if you don't believe me let's comment
this out. And you're going to see that
we're going to have errors. It doesn't
know what these things are windows, text.
We don't know what these things are so
we need to import this things so that
our compiler knows what they are. Okay by
now you have seen one way to run your Qt
quick application which is through the
qml application engine class. Let's go
back to Qt creator and analyze this a
little bit more. If you look in our main
CPP file you see that we have a main
function which is the entry point for
our application. When our application
runs it starts here in the main function.
We instantiate app GuiApplications like
that which is going to wrap around our
application. And inside we create a qml
application engine object which we use
here to load our qml file. This line here
is really loading our qml file and
showing it in the window as we saw when
we run the application. The second way is
to use some provided command line tools
that you can use to run your qml files
one by one. You obviously don't want to
start the Qt project whenever you have
some qml file you want to run just to
see how it looks. So we're going to use
some of these tools. The first thing you
might ask where do I find these tools.
Well you go where you installed your Qt
packages, in our case we are going to go
in C because that's where I have it
installed. You see I have a Qt folder Qt5.11.1.
I click on the mingw version of my
Qt installation. I go into the bin
directory. And if I scroll down you're
going to see that I am going to see one
tool called QML
and another tool called qmlscene. These
are our tools that we can use to run the
application. Okay so what I'm going to do,
I'm going to copy the path to these
tools and I am going to go where my qml
file is located. So I'm going to
show this in explorer. So if you are on a Mac
or on a Linux machine
you should find equivalent ways to do
the same thing. This just takes me where
my project is hosted. I'm going to hold
down the shift key and right-click and
it's going to give me an option to open
the command line window here. Okay and
you see that it is opened here. If I do a
dir I'm going to see the files that
make up my project and if you look
inside you see that I have a main.qml
file. So what I want to do is to paste in
the path where I have my QML tools in
the Qt installation directory and I'm
going to complete the path with the qml
tool. And I'm going to specify that I
want to run the main.qml file. Ok
when I hit enter notice what happens you
see that what hello world application is
shown. Okay this is one way you can run
your qml files. Let's use the qmlscene
tool and do the same thing. So I'm going
to say here now scene and I'm going to
specify main.qml as we did before.
And you're going to see that it is the
same thing we have our qml
application running the same way it ran
in Qt creator. If you like me you
probably think that typing all this thing
to run one qml file is really tedious
and it's hard to do. But there is a way
you can add the path to these qml tools
to your environment variables and all
you have to do is do something like qml main.qml
. And it is going
to run. Why is it running if you do this
it's probably not going to run. For me it
is working because I have added this
path to
environment variables and I'm going to
show you how to do it on Windows.
There are equivalent way to do the same
on a Linux machine in the Mac. All you
have to do is find ways to add
environment variables to your operating
system and Google should give you more
options than anybody can. So we are going
to go in my computer, click on properties,
click on advanced system settings, go
into environment variables. And you're
going to find the path variable like
this you click on it. And you are going
to add the path to the tools as I did
here. You can see the full path to there
and when you add it like this and
remember to put a column at the end.
Confirm, confirm, and close this. And if
you close your command line and open it
again just like this you're going to be
able to run your tool so let's clear. So
I want to kill this application because
there is hang in here. So I want to clear
and show you that I can do the same
thing using qmlscene main.qml. And
you see that the application is running.
There is another way you can run your
QML files if you really don't like these
command-line tools it really is a
wrapper around the qmlscene tool. You
create a prototype file in Qt creator
and run it. Let's go to Qt creator
and try this tune. The first thing I want
to do is to copy my files because I'm
going to paste it somewhere. Let's
collapse this, save everything and close
again. So I'm going to file - new other
project and on the right here you're
going to see a Qt quick UI prototype. I
want you to select this - hit next. We
call this PrototypeTest. You can choose
where you want to save it on your drives
going to hit next, choose
the latest version of Qt have
installed. And in the end you see that
you have a qml file that is called
PrototypeTest. It takes the name of the
project you specified. So I'm going to
take out everything and paste in the
code we had and I can run it directly.
Okay and you see that it is the same
thing we had before.
And what this is really doing it is
doing the calling to qmlscene for you.
And by now we have seen four ways you
can run your qml files: you can use
QmlApplicationEngine like we did here, you
can use the command line tools that are
provided, you can call kml scene to run
your application or you can even call
qml to run your qml file and the last
one is to create a prototype file that
you can run directly by clicking the
green button here if that's what you
find easy. Before we wrap up this video I
want to show you how you can show some
log messages because that's something
very important to know in whatever
technology of programming that you are
working on. We are going to load
something when our component here is
loaded. The way you do that you say
component.oncompleted. Again don't worry
if you don't understand all this I'm
going to have a chance to explain this. I
just want you to know that you can do a
console.log just like in JavaScript to
show some debug messages. So in here we
can say for example component loaded
and when you run the application you're
going to see that in the application
output pane. This covers all we set up to
do in this lecture. I hope you like the
introduction to Qt quick. And you had in
your arms on different ways you can run
your QML file. In the next section we're
going to start looking at some qml
syntax and shed some light on some of the
things we've been talking about in this
lecture. I'll see you in the next section.