I would like to welcome you again and
congratulate you on taking the step to
become a Qt quick user interface
developer. Qt quick is the latest user
interface design technology from the Qt
framework, it stands for user interface
creation kit. Qt quick uses Qml
language at the core and Qml stands for
Qt markup language.
Qt is a framework you can use to build
cross-platform applications. You can
basically use it to target all these
operating systems you see here: the
Android, iOS, Linux, Mac OS, Windows, Windows Phone
and many others. It was originally
designed by these two guys: Haayard and
Eirik and over the years it's got owned
by these companies you see here. Today it
is owned by the Qt company which is a
subsidiary of Digia, you can read more on
these companies by clicking these links
here. Qt is a very powerful framework, you
can see some of the companies that are
using it. From this you can have an idea
of how good it is. You can see AMD here
Microsoft, Samsung, CMS, Volvo and many other big
names here. Down here if you keep
scrolling you're going to see a few
applications that are using Qt.
You can see some Adobe products, Google Earth,
Krita, it's graphics editing and
digital painting software, Mathematica,
you are going to recognize this if you
are a scientist. Keep going down you're going
to see VirtualBox, a powerful piece of
virtualization software. You can see VLC
media player. From this I hope you can
see how useful and powerful Qt can be.
Now I am talking about Qt here
where does Qt quick fall in. Well Qt
quick is another application framebuild
that is built on top of Qt with a sole
goal of building fluid and dynamic user
interfaces that can run on touch devices,
mobile devices and literally it is being
pushed even to desktop platform. So you
can use it to build user interfaces that
can really run anywhere. And if you're
looking here you're going to see that
the Qml syntax allows using javascript
provide logic. And it is often used for
this purpose so you can use JavaScript
to add some interactivity to your Qml
code. Qml by itself is a declarative
language. And by now some of you might
ask what is the declarative language. Qml
is a declarative language in that it
allows you to describe how your user
interface is going to look without going
into the flow of the logic. And this is a
Wikipedia link on the declaritive
programming if you want to know more on
the subject. If you look here they say
many languages that apply declarative
programming attempt to minimize or
eliminate side effects by describing
what the program must accomplish in
terms of the problem domain. In Qt quick
the problem domain must be how you user
interface is going to look. So we try and
describe how the user interface is going
to look but we don't want to go into the
details of how that is accomplished. The
job of accomplishing that belongs to the
Qml engine that is built into your
Qt framebuild. This is what they are
trying to say here, you can read more on
this if you are interested. To give you
some context if you were trying to put a
few buttons in a layout in an imperative
language that is not declarative, you
would mix flow and program logic. You see
here we are adding widgets to the layout
inside the loop which is a control flow
structure in C++ or any C like language. So
if we do this declaratively like we do
in Qml you see we define a component.
This is a column layout it lays out
things from top to bottom and decide we
just stuff things we want to put in that
layout and we are done, we don't concern
ourselves with how this is accomplished
it is the job of the Qml engine to
make sure this works. Ok now you have an
idea about Qt you have an idea about Qt
quick how do they interact, how do you
put them together. Well there are mainly
two sides to building with Qt.
You can develop your application
completely in C++ and this is what we
were all doing before they came up with
Qt quick
but the problem with applications
developed with C++ is that they don't
build well when you run them on mobile
devices. It is really painful to look at
the widget application running on
android or iOS. Another side is using Qt quick
which is designed to work fluid and
dynamic user interfaces that can run on
Android iOS touch interfaces or embedded
devices or even desktop you can use it
to build the desktop applications. And
we're going to see that along the course.
Now Qt quick also comprises two parts
there is Qml the language that
allows you to build how your user
interface is going to look it allows you
to build still and static UI components.
And if you want to add some
interactivity to your application you're
going to use JavaScript to do that. If
you want to do things like responding to
a click on a button and things like that
you're going to use javascript. And we're
going to see exactly how that builds. Now
I want to bring to your attention that
it is possible to communicate between Qt
quick and C++. And the recommended
workflow to building with Qt to develop
cross-platform applications is to write
your user interface in Qt quick and do
resource heavy things in C++. For example
if you are doing an image processing
application you can do your user
interface in Qt quick and take advantage
of all the cool things that this
technology has to offer. And you can do
heavy things like doing operations on
your images on the c++ side and pass the
resort back to Qt quick to be displayed.
I have to say this course is solely on
Qt quick, we don't cover how you
communicate between C++ and Qt quick
because we wanted this course to be
equally useful to designers who are not
interested in C++ and C++ developers who
want to know how to work with Qt quick.
Now you are probably going to see the
terms Qml and Qt quick used
interchangeably.
Qt quick is the overall technology if you
go down the staff you're going to see
that it contains Qml itself, it also
contains a Qml API that we are going to
use in this course and it contains a C++
API that allows you to expand Qml with
new types using c++. Qml itself contains
the Qml engine and the Qml language.
It is also important to know the
difference between Qml and C++ in terms
of what is available to you what can you
use. Qml is declarative we just saw
that in a previous slide but it is also
imperative because you can use
JavaScript which is an imperative
language to add some interactivity to
your Qml applications. C++
is imperative you are going to see less
debug information in Qml. And C++ is
a beast when it comes to giving you the value
information. There are API is for most Qt
modules in C++ but Qml covers only a
few selected Qt modules. It is new
compared to the C++ side of Qt but it
is getting there. We should also note
that there are some api's that are only
available in Qml for example the Qt quick
API it is only available in Qml.
And that is one main reason why you need
to learn Qml because you're going
to take advantage of that. Qml supports
property bindings a very important
property that allows you to have your
changes propagated to other properties
we're going to look at that and C++
doesn't support that. And Qml can be
extended from C++. Okay and the big idea
is that Qt quick is used to build your
user interface and C++ takes care of the
heavy liftin, doing resource heavy things
and passing the results back to Qt
quick to be displayed to the user.
Qml has four main components really. It
has nested elements blocks you can see
here this is what Qml looks like. We are
going to look at this
but you see we have an item here and
these brackets here inside we have
another rectangle item inside the
rectangle item we have
another mouse area area. You see they are
nested this is what we mean here. Qml has
properties things like XY you see here
width, height, color our properties in
Qml. You can bind properties together.
We're going to see how this builds in
Qml. And we also have signals and handlers.
If you look here in the mouse area on
clicked here is a signal handler and you
can also emit or send signals in Qt
quick. Now I have been getting this
question a lot how do you know the Qt
quick version to import. The Qt quick
version you use comes with your
installed Qt version. For example right
now I am using Qt 5.11
and the Qt quick version that comes
with that is 2.11. Different modules that
you import in Qt quick are also going to
have versions attached to them. They are
usually different from the Qt quick
version you see. A good way to find out
the version that you might use is to
search for the element in the Qt
documentation and they are going to show
you the import that you can use. For
example you can search for rectangle in
the Qt documentation and they are going
to show what you need to import to be
able to use that component in your
Qml code. I want to talk about what you
need to bring in this course to be able
to take advantage of it. First off you
need to bring in an open mind and the
willingness to learn the stuff we talked
about in this course, it is really not
difficult. All you have to do is follow
up the demos do what I do and try to
bring in your own changes to try and
understand how things really work. It is
also going to help if you have an eye
for design because obviously we are
designing the visual stuff. Qml is a
completely new language so you don't
really need to bring in any other skill
but if you have very basic programming
skills if you have worked with things
like CSS and HTML. And if you have some
basic understanding of JavaScript things
like control flow if you know how to
work with IFS and ELSES if you know how
to work with loop you're probably going to be
fine in this course. But the most
important thing is to have an open mind
and be willing to spend sometime to
learn what is presented in the course.
Okay how to make the most out of this
course I just said it you just have to
follow up with what I do and try to
write the code yourself and see how
things work for you. This course is very
practical we are going to spend most of
the time in the IDE writing code and
trying to get things to work. If you get
stuck try to compare your code to mine,
the projects are going to be attached to
every lecture and you can easily
download that and look at what I tapped
or even trying to run my project and see
what is not working for you. If you still
can solve the problem you may search in
Google with the error that you are
saying in the IDE. And this is mostly
going to lead you to somebody who had
the same problem as you and you're going
to see their solution and apply it. If
after this you still can't solve the
question this is a good time to jump to
the community. Udemy itself have the QA
section where you can post your question
and I'm going to try to answer to the
best of my abilities. We have also set up
a Facebook group dedicated to helping
students learning about different Qt
development topics, we talked about C++
we'll also talk about Qt quick. So if you
have a question or anything you want to
share really please go there and post
and share with us. And by the way this is
a good time to post the video go to
Facebook and like that page so that you
have updates from other students to try
and learn from each other. Okay this is
all for the introduction in the next
lecture we're going to download and
install Qt & Qt creator and set up our
host development environment. I'll see
you there.