in this lecture, we're going to look at
repeaters. repeaters allow you to show
your data in a very similar way to the
way you display the data in the listview,
but you use it in cases where a
ListView is not usable. it also gives you
more control on how you display your
data. we're going to go to QT creator and
play with it. okay here we are in QT
creator, we create our project as usual.
it's going to be called repeaterdemo.
choose our Qt version, choose our kit,
and Finish. we want to say "repeater demo"
here, and inside we want to put a
flickable component. and now you are
wondering why do we put the flickable
if a repeater is like listview. well a
repeater doesn't have a bulletin
flickable like a ListView does. that's
because it wants to give you more
control on how you display your data, so
we are going to weld the flickable
ourselves. so inside we want to put a
column component, and this is how we are
going to display our data from top to
bottom. ID is going to be column, it's going
to fill the parent, and we want to give
it a spacing of two. we want to let the
flickable know how much content it has
to display, so we're going to say content
height. we have done this before, and it's
going to be the height that is to be
displayed in the column here, so we're
going to say implicit height for this,
but we also wanted to fill the parent, so
we go back to our column here. inside we
want to put a repeater, our component of
interest in this lecture. a repeater is
very similar to the ListView in that it
has a model property and a delegate
property to control how each element and
the repeater is going to look.
so for example if we say 10 for a model, we
haven't done this, so let's do this so
that you see we can specify our model
like this, you're going to see what is
going to happen when we run this, and for
our delegate, we want to put in an inline
one, which is going to be a rectangle
like this. okay so I just pasted this and
to save you some type in time, but it's
nothing you haven't seen before, we have
a width, a height, a color. we have a text
component inside the delegate. this is
what it is going to look like, and we
want to make it clickable. we also access
the current item for the delegate using
the model data role, which is the same
thing we have seen in the ListView, and
listmodel. if we run this application,
we're going to see numbers displayed
from 0 to 10, and the look of each item
is controlled in the delegate here. this
is really how you work with repeaters.
you see that we don't have complicated
stuff inside, and when we specify our
model like this, you see that we have
numbers from 0 to 9 so you can
understand it as displaying the number
of integer elements you are going to
show, starting from 0. so we go from 0 to
9, and total we have 10 elements. we can
also comment this, and put in the months
like we have been doing in a few
previous lectures, and if we run, it's
also going to work the same. ok this is
what we have, and this is really how you
work with a repeater. that's selected hit
f1 and go to see what the official
documentation has to say about it. the
repeater type is used to create a large
number of similar items. like other view
types a repeater has a model and a
delegate for each entry in the model. the
delegate is instantiated in a context
seeded with data from the model. so the
data is coming from the
model. a repeater is usually enclosed in
a position or types such as row and
column to visually position the multiple
delegate items created by the repeater. a
repeater
basically repeats data. we tell it three,
it's going to repeat numbers from zero
to two, and we need to specify how these
pieces of data are going to be displayed
using the delegate. hope this makes sense.
okay you can also give it a model, and
they give you tons and tons of things
you can look at, if you need to know more
about this repeater component, and if we
click we're going to see whatever
component would click that. let's run
again,
you click on that April, you see April. you
click on September, you see September. ok
this is all for this lecture. the next
one we're going to see how you can
dynamically add and remove data in your
models. I'll see you there.