in this lecture, we're going to look at
how you can add some decorations to your
ListView.
specifically we're going to look at how
you can work with headers footers and
highlights. let's go to QT create or and
do a demo about that. here we are in QT
creator we're going to start a new
project. it's a Qt quick 2 application.
we call it HeaderFooterHighlightDemo,
choose our Qt version, choose our kit
and finish. we want to change this title
here, and we want to go to the last
example, and copy the code we had in
there, because that's going to be our
start. so we're going to copy everything
in the window like this, bring it over in
our new piece of code here.
let's close this, we don't need it
anymore.
if you go to the documentation for list
view, you're going to see that we have a
few properties that we haven't seen
before. we have a property called footer
here, we have a header, and we have
another called highlight. the footer
holds the component to use as a footer,
you can specify a footer for your
ListView. the header is the same, you can
specify a header for your list view, and
highlight displays how the data changes
when you select the current item. it is a
visual representation that you see in
the listview when you select something.
we'd like to see how this works. we're
going to go back to our code here, and
specify our header component. we're going
to go down the list and, say "component".
it's going to be our header, so we're
going to say "headerID" for the ID, and
inside we want to put a rectangle
component. it really is the same thing we
did when we defined our delegate. we're
going to specify how our header is going
to look, and the data that is going to be
inside.
let's give it an ID. it's going to have
a width which is going to be the same as
for the parent. it's going to have the
height, we want this to be 50 in height.
we want him to have a color of yellow
green, and we want to specify a border.
our border is going to look like this.
it's going to have this color, and it's
going to be 2 in width inside, we want to
have a text component as usual. it's
going to be centered, the text is going
to say "months", and it's going to have a
point size of 20. let's do 20. so we can
go back to our list view here and
specify the header. so we're going to say
"header" and say "headerID". this is really
all we need. let's run the application,
and see what we have.
hmm we have a good header on top here.
and this is how you control how the
header of the ListView looks, if you
happen to need this. we can do the same
thing for the footer, but we're going to
do that in line, so we're going to say
"footer" and specify a rectangle component
like this. we want it to have the same
width as the parent, a height of 15 just
like the header, and the color is going
to be dodgerblue, if we run, we're going to
have a footer at the bottom of the list
view. and you can put in a piece of
content if you want really. you can put
in whatever you want. now we want to
highlight every element as you select it.
you see that if we click we see November
for example, but it would be better if we
had a visual representation of what is
the current element. that's what
highlights are for. so we can come back
to
listview and specify a highlight, so
we're going to say "highlight", it's going
to be a rectangle, the same thing really.
it's going to have the same width as the
parent, the color is going to be blue, and
it's going to have round edges, so we
want to specify a radius, let's put in 14,
and let's give it a border color of
yellow green. right now we need to set
the correct item to the list view when
we click on an item, and we do that in
the delegate if you remember, we click on
an item and we show what we click on
here, so what we can do is let's look
again at the ID of the ListView. we can
say in here "mListView", "currentIndex"
equals index, and this index property is
coming from the model, when it feeds us
the data to show in that particular
delegate text item. hope this makes sense.
when it gives us the data to show from
the model for example, when we grab the
model data here, we also receive a bunch
of other properties that we can use, and
one of them is the index that specifies
the index of the element that we
received in the model. okay so the index
is going to start from 0 in the model, so
January is 0, February is 1, and as you go
up, you increase until you get to
December which is index 11. I hope this
makes sense. ok we are setting the
current index when we click on the item.
let's run the application and see that
we are having this highlight work. our
app is here, but you see we have a
problem, where is it?
uh-huh we forgot to say width here. I
make this mistake a lot, so don't be like
me. let's run again. ok you see
it's clicked,
but you see that our rectangle is not
visible, and if you watch, you see that we
are seeing the highlight rectangle move
in the background, and this says that the
data is laid on top of that rectangle, so
what we can do, we can bring it up by
increasing its Z index, so we're going to
come back to the highlight, and specify a
Z of three, the Z property of your
element specifies how high it is if you
have two items stacked on top of each
other. let's run again. uh-huh
you see that our how light is on top now,
but it is covering the data so we're not
seeing anything. a hack that I have done
to make this work is set the opacity of
this thing to be a little bit low. so we
can come back to the highlight here, and
set opacity of 0.1. let's run again.
mm-hmm and you see that we have a visual
confirmation of whatever element that we
choose. this is good. isn't it. and I hope
this really gives you an introduction of
how you can work with header, footer and
highlight in your list views to make the
data more presentable. in the next
lecture, we see how you can
work with sections. I'll see you there.