in this lecture we're going to see how
you work with list view and list model
intuitive quick list view is going to
display our data list model is going to
control how we store our data. we're
going to go to QT creator and start
working with us, here we are in QT
creator we're going to create our
project.
it's a QT quick application as usual.
we're going to call it list view list
model demo. choose our QT version, choose
our kit, and finish. we're going to change
the title here to say a ListView, we want
to start by putting a ListView component
inside. we're going to give it an ID. it's
going to "fill the parent" and we need to
specify a model property, and the
delegate property for it. we're not going
to specify that right now, what we want
to do is come to the documentation, and
look at this. "ListView" in here. at this
place data from models created from
Wilton qml types like list model and XML
list model. we are going to look at XML
list model later, now we want to focus on
this model. a ListView has a model which
defines the data to be displayed, and the
delegate which defines how the data
should be displayed. items in a list you
are laid out horizontally or vertically.
list views are inherently Flickable
because ListView inherits flickable, so
you don't need to wrap your elements in
a flickable component to be able to
scroll through more content. a flickable
about is Boston by default. okay now that
you have a better idea on the ListView,
how do we specify the model or the
delegate. let's start by the model. we are
going to use the list model component.
want to give it an ID of model ID and
model ID, and we want to specify it here
so that we get rid of this error here. I
don't really like this, so a model ID
let's comment this delegate first, so
that we get rid of these errors. okay we
have our list model here. we need a way
to put in the data that should be
displayed by the ListView, and for that
to use a list element. let's look at that
in the documentation. "list element". let's
look at "more" list elements are defined
inside list model and represent items in
the list that will be displayed using
list view or repeater, you put in the
data like this, you wrap your data in
list element. what I am going to do is
come back to the code here, and put in a
bunch of list elements that I had
prepared. to save you some typing, but it
really is easy you have a list element
component, and you specify your
attributes and the values for your
attributes. in QML these are
called roles but you can call it
whatever you want. the important thing is
that you know how to use it. so we have
our model and it has a list of items
that should be displayed by the view
that we're going to attach to this model,
and the model has two data sets, one is
for the country that you specify like
this, and the other is the capital of the
country that you specify like this.
notice that your attributes here can
really be anything, a specified country
and capital here because that's what I
want to work with in this lecture, but as
you see in the lecture here, you can
really put in anything, they have name
and Coast depending on what you are
designing for. you're going to have
different things defined in here. okay
now we have our list model and you might
not believe it but this is all you need
to have a model that you can display in
a view. the next thing we want to define
is the delegate. how do you define this.
We go to the bottom of the
model, and say "component". so far we have
used components as external qml files,
but you can also define an inline
component like this, okay it is the same
thing. we want to give it an ID, it's
going to be delegateID, inside we want
to put the rectangle component. let's
give it an ID as well, rectangleID, we
give it a width that is equal to the
parent width, give it a height of 50, and
we give it a color of beige, we want the
border color of yellowgreen and the
radius of 10, on this rectangle here, so
we have the rectangle we want a way to
display some text inside, so we want to
put in a text component. give it an idea
of textID. we want it centered in the
parent, and we want it to have a pointsize
of 20 let's try this. okay now we
are going to see something important.
from the component here, that is our
delegate, by the way we can come back to
the top here and specify our delegate,
because we have it now. so we can say
"delegateID", when you try the model and
the delegate and if you like this in the
list view, something important happens.
you can access data in the model
directly without doing anything else, so
for example, what we can do we can access
the country and the capital attributes
from the current element that we are
displaying in the delegateID. so what I
want to do now I want to say "text" it is
going to be "country".
"+" let's put a column in the middle
and say "capital". notice that these are
the attributes in the model that we are
accessing. okay we didn't need to do
anything else, we are able to do this
because these things are tied together
in the ListView like this. right now we
can run the application and see what it
looks like. let's run it. okay.
you see that we have a list of elements
and we have countries and capitals, I
want to shrink the height of this then,
and you see that we aren't able to
scroll to see the data. okay so if you
have more data than can be displayed in
the available window, you can scroll to
see things. this is the effect of the
bolt inflickable component that is in the
ListView, and this is really how you work
with a ListView and a list model. you
define your ListView like this, and you
give it some positioning as you would do
for any component, in this case we wanted
to fill the parent, and you give it a
model by specifying the ID of the model.
our model is nothing special, it's a
bunch of list elements wrapped in a list
model component, and our delegate is a
custom component like this, and inside we
have a rectangle that contains a text
element. that is going to contain the
attributes of the list element in our
case. another thing you can do is make
the list element inside the ListView
clickable. the way you do that you can
put a mouse area in the delegate, so
let's say "Mousearea", we want it to fill
the parent, and the parent is going to be
this delegate rectangle here, so we're
going to say "onClicked"
"console.log("clicked on:")", we want to say the
"capital", remember that we are still in
the delegate so we can access distance
without a problem. put in a column, and
say "country"
let's run. we have our things here, and if I
click on Rwanda, here you see that I
clicked on Kigali Rwanda, let's click on
Paris Paris, France
Uganda Kampala Uganda, and ladies and
gentlemen this is how you work with the
list view and the list model. the list
view controls how you display your data,
and the list model controls how your
data is saved. and the delegate controls
how each data item is displayed in the
view. the delegate is this rectangle here
notice that the decoration that we put
on the delegate is here, this is the font
size that we specified here, this is the
color beige that is the background, this
is the yellow green border color that we
specified here. you can control all these
aspects of how your elements are
displayed in the delegate element that
you tied to your ListView. hope this
makes sense. ok I have used my delegate
as an external component just to show
you that you can do this, but we can also
make this inline and I also want you to
see that. so I am going to copy the
rectangle inside our component here.
selected copy and I'm going to comment
it challenge, ok so. we don't need it
anymore
in what we're going to do. and what we
can do is come here, comment this out
because I want you to keep this for
reference. we can say "delegate" and paste
in our rectangle in line like this, and
it's great to work the same. let's run.
mmm and you see that it is the same
thing, click on India New Delhi ,you see
that things are the same as they were
before, you can specify your delegate or
your model in line like this if you want
to. this is all hard to say in this
lecture. I hope you have a better idea of
how you work with list views and list
models to display your data. in the next
lecture, we're going to see how you work
with direct models.I'll see you there.