in this lecture, we're going to look in
detail at how you can manipulate your
models dynamically. we're going to go to
QT creator and play with it. here we are
in Qt creator.
we're going to create our new project.
it's a QT quick application as usual.
we're going to call it DynamicModelsDemo.
Save it in the usual location, hit Next.
choose our QT version, choose our kit and
finish. we want to change the title here,
because we are going to need a few
buttons, we're going to import Qt Quick Controls.
we want 2.4. and we want to
import QT quick layouts. let's use 1.4. we
want to put in a column layout. it is
going to fill the parent. and inside,
we're going to have a listview whose
ID is going to be mListView here as usual.
it's going to have a model assigned to
it, and the delegate, but we don't have
those defined yet. we're going to define
them in a while, but we want to make this
fillwidth, we're going to say
layout, fillwidth, set this to true and
layout, fillheight, set this to true. to
save on some typing, I'm going to put in
a model that I have prepared before. it's
nothing you haven't seen before. it is a
list model, and inside we have list
elements. we should go down in our list
view, and specify this model. let's look
at the ID, the ID is mListModel, so
this should be our model. the same as for
the model, the delegate is also prepared
before. control a control I to align,
and it is nothing you haven't seen
before also. inside we have a rectangle,
which has a bunch of properties. inside
we have a text element, and we have a
mouse area to make this delegate
clickable. so we're going to be able to
click on each row of our listview that
we have in this column layout here. okay
now we can specify "delegateID" to be
our delegate. it's not "delegated", it is
"delegate". this is good, and you see that
we are printing the first name and the
last name, which are the roles that we
have in our list element here. now we
want to put a few buttons below the list
view here. we are going to use these
buttons to dynamically manipulate this
model here. let's go down here, and put in
a button. the text is going to say "add
item", and we want to know when it is
clicked. that's where we're going to add
stuff to our model here. we want to copy
this button, and paste it a couple of
times.
I think we need four buttons here so I'm
going to paste this three times. the
second one is going to say clear. the
third one is going to say delete. we want
to delete that item. let's spell this
correctly, and the last one is going to
say set item at in its tool as well. okay
so how do we add items to our model here?
the first thing you need to remember is
that you're going to use the ID here to
manipulate the model. let's go back to
the documentation, look at list model.
let's go up and find the methods that we
have. we have a method that is called
Append, and you append things like this. okay
so what we can do is actually to take
this, because I like to learn from the
documentation. I'm going to copy this,
come back in our
handler for an odd item, we're going to
paste this, and I'm going to change fruitmodel
to mListModel. I can do that so
"cost" is going to be "first name" because
that's the role that we have here. I can
actually copy this and paste to reduce
the chance of having an error. last name,
I copy and paste in here, and let's say I
want to put in "Daniel", and "Gakwaya".
I want to add my name in here, and when
we click, we're going to see my name
added to the list here. let's run the
application. mm-hmm we are here, and you
see that these buttons are not filling
the available space. we're going to
correct this in a moment, but we should
click on add item and see my name added
here. this is cool, isnt it? let's go
back and make the buttons fill the
available width. we can do this by
copying what is here, and putting that in
every single button that we have in here.
let's do that for everyone, and we should
be fine by now. now we want to clear
everything in the model. the way you do
that you say mListModel, clear,
Easy, right? let's run. okay ready?
clear, everything is gone, and we can add
a bunch of other pieces of data, and
notice that we can still scroll because
this is a ListView that has the flickin
Bolton. we want to delete the item at
index - how do we do that?
so if you look here, the first item is
that index 0 1 2, and you keep going up
like that. so if we delete... let's close
the application and run it again, so that
you see
different pieces of data. Jones snow is at
zero,
Nikolai Itchenko is at one, Mitch Mathson
is at two. okay so if we delete at index
two, we're going to delete Mitch Matt's
on here. that's what we want to do. let's
go back to the documentation and see
what they have to say. we can go up to
find all these methods, and we find a
method that is called remove. you pass in
the index where you want to start
removing, and you pass in the number of
elements that you want to remove. this is
easy right? so we can go back to our
signal handler here, and say mListModel,
remove, the index is going to be two
because that's what we want to remove
and we want to remove one element. let's
run the application, okay we are here.
ready? delete.
you see Mitch Madson is gone, now index
two is occupied by a Vince Luvky j
here.
we can also remove him and we can keep
removing data. notice that the moment we
don't have an item at index two, and
we try to remove an item, you see that we
have an error here, so you should be
careful and check the index before you
remove an element. and the check is
really not that hard. you just have to
see that two is less than the number of
items that you have in the model. the way
you do that you can say if 2 is less
than mListView, the "model" that is
attached to that and "count", this is the
property that has the number of items in
that model. so if this is the case, we can
successfully remove the element because
it is available. if this is not the case,
you can "console.log"
"index is invalid", something like this.
let's run again. okay we delete all items.
Ken Kologorov, we remove this. we remove. if
we try to remove again, it says "index is
invalid", because the number of items is
two now, and two is not less than two.
that's why we failed. I hope this
makes sense. okay we want to do the last
operation, which is setting the item at
index two. notice that at index 2, we have
Mitch Matheson. we can change that
dynamically. let's look at the "set" method
in our documentation here. you pass the
index and you pass the JSON object
containing the data that you want to set
your thing with. so we are basically
going to use this syntax here, so we
should copy this to save some time, and
we are going to say "mListModel.set", we
passed the index that we want to modify.
it is index two and we pass in edges an
object like this. first name, last name, so
we can say John Doe in here. why not?
let's run. index two is Mitch Matson here,
and if you "set" that you see that it
becomes John Doe, and everything we had
before it works. okay we can keep setting
the item at index two as we want. and
this is really all I hard to show you in
this lecture. I hope you have a better
understanding of how you can modify your
model at run time. you have a bunch of
methods available to you that you can
play with if you happen to need that. in
the next lecture we're going to work
with grid view. I see you there.