In this lecture, we're going to look at
XmlListModel, the component that allows
you to parse data in an XML file and
feed it your views in Qt Quick.
This component has a few properties
that you need to be aware of.
This first property allows you to link to an XML file
that is going to provide the data.
The 'query' property allows you to specify the data
that you want to extract from the XML file.
The 'roles' property allows you to
specify the attributes that you want in the role
that you queried from the query property.
And the 'status' property updates
you on the status of loading your data.
So if there is an error, if the loading is successful,
you can note that from the
'status' property here.
And down here you see an example of how you can link to an XML file.
The XML file can be local,
living in a resource file and you can
link to act using qrc like this
or you can get the XML data from the internet
using some XML API's.
Here we have an example of an XML file
and the XmlListModel that is going to read data from this XML file.
Okay, we specify the
'source' to be an XML file that is located
in the resource file in our project.
The 'query' property allows you to specify
what you want,
what is going to be your role in your XML file.
In this case, we want to retrieve all the courses.
Ok, you see we have a tag for courses and
inside we have a bunch of courses and
each 'course' has child elements in structure
'year' and 'coursename' here.
So, we specify that we want to get courses
in this 'query' property that is in the XmlListModel.
Now that we have a course,
we may want to fetch further data from the course.
For example we may want to
get this 'hot' attribute here,
we may also want to read the elements
that are children to this course element here.
That's where these XmlRole come in.
The first one here is reading
this 'instructor' element.
You specify the role for whatever it is
you are trying to read and you pass in a
query that fetches what you want.
Okay, we want to get the instructor.
This 'instructor' here has to match the tag
that you have in your 'course' element here,
and you pass in a method that
denotes the data type that you want to
read that piece of data as.
We want to read this as a string in this case.
We also want to read year.
It really is the same thing but we want to read that as a number.
And in the third one we want to
read the course name here.
We want to read that as a string.
In the fourth XmlRole here, we want to read
this 'hot' attribute here and this @ symbol here
specifies that what you want to read is an attribute.
It is not an element.
And if you want to read an element,
you just pass it in like this.
All this gibberish that I am typing here to fetch data is
really specified in the standard
that is called XPath.
It is a standard that allows you
to parse an XML file to get
specific pieces of data that you are interested
in and that what we are exactly doing here.
Reading the XML files to fetch
these elements or attributes here
and in this case we want to feed that data to
an XML List model.
I hope this made sense.
If this is not clear yet, we wait to run an example in a moment
and you're going to understand how this works.
Okay, we just looked at an overall example of
how you read the data
from your XML file and feed it to the XML list model.
Now we want to focus on the syntax
that you can use to pass this query here.
The query that is in the XML list model.
Notice that we have two queries:
one is this one in the XmlListModel
and the other is this query
that is inside the XmlRole here.
We're going to focus on this one, the first one.
Okay, these are different things you can do to read the data.
You can specify that you
want to read a course by passing a slash
and passing the path that leads to the
tag that you want to read.
For example, here courses course.
We specify that we want to read the course
You can pass in double slashes here
and specify the tag name
for whatever it is you want to read.
This is also going to be equivalent to
the first syntax here. You can also pass
in the @ symbol to specify that you
want to read an attribute. You can also
specify that you want to read the first course.
Okay. Then we fetch courses here
we get all the courses that are in the XML file
but you can say that
you want to get the first course and you can do that like this.
If you are a C or C++ programmer,
or any language that is based on C,
you know that arrays start at 0.
This is going to tip you off because
this indexes start at 1 and you need to be careful about that.
Now we want to look at a few examples.
Okay, we have the example here.
It is the same file we had.
You can pass the query to read all the courses.
You can pass in another query
that is going to read all the courses.
The double slash notation here you can
pass this array notation to specify the element that you want.
You can fetch all the courses
that have the 'hot' attribute.
You can fetch the courses that have the
'hot' attribute and the 'required' attribute.
If you happen to have that,
you can also query the courses that have the
'hot' attribute or the 'required' attribute.
Okay, you can do all these operations.
The next thing we want to look at is
the syntax that you use in
your XmlRole to specify the data that
you want to get in each course.
Okay to repeat, you can get the attribute or you
0:06:06.240,0:06:12.870
can get the elements inside here.
To read the elements you pass in the name of the
element that you want to read.
Okay, so, if we want to read 'instructor' here, we just
pass an 'instructor' here and we specify
the datatype for whatever we want to read.
If you want to read an attribute,
you pass in the @ symbol here and you
also specify the data type that you want
to read this as and it is the same for the 'year'.
We want to read this as a number.
Now we want to go to Qt Creator
create a project and play with it.
Okay here we are in Qt Creator.
We're going to create our project.
It's Qt Quick Application.
We call it 'XMLListModelDemo',
choose our Qt Version,
choose our kit and finish.
We want to change the title here and specify what we are doing.
The first thing we want to do
we want to specify the XML file that we want to read.
So we're going to add
a resource file that is going to point to that XML file.
Hit 'resources' here, 'add new'
choose Qt resource file, I want to name this 'resource'.
We have done this quite a lot.
By now I want to add the prefix
take this out, hit enter.
Now we want to go where we have saved this 'main.qml' file.
You right click on it, choose 'Show in Explorer'.
It's going to open that location in a moment.
Here we are.
Add a new folder call it 'XML'.
I want to open this 'XML' folder and paste in a file
that I have prepared.
This is basically the same XML file you have seen in the slides.
I am going to go back to my project,
add files to my resource file,
choose this file here and I can save it
because it is now in my resource but qrc file.
I can double click it to show it in
Qt Creator and you see that it is the same file.
We have our courses inside
and you see that we have instructor, year, and course name.
Now we can go back to 'main.qml'.
I want to define my 'XmlListModel'
I give it an ID
I want to give it a 'source' property and
it is going to specify the location of my XML file.
I want to use a local file
so I'm going to say qrc, three slashes
say the folder where the file is located
and say the name of the file.
It's called 'employees.xml'.
You can also specify a remote file using HTTP
just like an API to fetch some XML data from the internet.
I flagged this here so
that you know we're not going to do that
in this lecture, but if you have an API
that gives you an XML file you can just
stuff in the HTTP URL to the XML file
and it is just going to work.
You just need to pass in the correct queries to
fetch your XML data.
Now we want to pass
in our 'query' property. So, we're going to
say 'query' here and we are going to say
'courses/course' because that's what we
want to get from the XML file here.
We want to read all these courses and you
pass in a query like this to get it.
This is one way to do it.
When we have run the application, I am going to show you
the other syntaxes so that you can play with them.
Okay, now, I want to pass in my 'XmlRole'
to parse the data that I want to
read in each item, that is returned by
this query here, that we did.
This query is going to return the list of all the courses
that we have in here and we need
to be able to read the data from each
course that we have. This is the purpose
of this XML role here. I want to pass in
the 'name' attribute and it's going to be
'instructor'
because this is what I want to read and
I'm going to pass in the 'query' property
and here, I am going to say 'instructor',
this and it's going to be a string.
This is what I want to read it as.
The first thing here specifies the role
that this is going to be available as.
So if I want to use this data in a delegate
,for example, I am going to use the name
that I have here as this. It doesn't have
to be like what we have here in the XML file.
But what we have here in the query
has to match exactly what we have in here
for us to be able to read the data.
So we have 'instructor' here, you should
copy this and come here and make sure
that we also have 'instructor' here.
This has to match the XML file. This has to
match what you have in the delegate.
Okay, we have read the 'instructor', we can also
read the 'year'. Let's do that. We can pass
in 'year' and 'year' here and we're going to
read this as in number. We also want to
read the course name. Let's look at how
it is spelled here, 'coursename', I can
copy this to improve on not getting the
error so course name is going to be a
string as well. I also want to read the
attribute whether or not it's hot.
So I'm going to copy this paste down here and
say 'hot' because that's the name of the
attribute if I'm correct. Yes it is.
And we want to specify '@hot' here and we
want to read that as a string.
And now we should have our model ready to be
linked to a list view or a grid view
whatever you say. But before we do that,
I want to look at this data.
I want to show you a way to see
what's going on when your model is
reading the data from the XML file.
We want to handle the 'onStatusChanged' signal handler
and decide we are going
to do something like this. Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to align.
We are basically
defining a 'pre' that says 'XmlListModel'
and we are saying if status equals
ready, we print ready and we showed the
count of the elements that we read from
the XML file. If it is loading, we say
that it is loading. If we have an error,
we say that and if it is 'null', they also
say that. This is a good way to debug and
see what is happening as your model is
reading the data from your XML file.
Now that we have the model, we can go down
here define a ListView. This is going to be a quick.
ID is going to be 'mListViewId',
model is going to be 'mXmlListModelId',
we want it to fill the parent
so we say 'anchors.fill: parent' and we
want to give it a nice delegate that we have prepared.
Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to align.
And our delegate is nothing new to you
as of now we have a row that has two
text components one is going to say the
instructor and notice that we are using
the same thing that we had in our XmlRole here.
So 'instructor' here should
match 'instructor' here and we have 'coursename'
that matches 'coursename' here. We
have 'year' that matches 'year' here and we
have 'hot'
that matches 'hot' that we have here and
we are reading 'hot' as an attribute
because we have the @ symbol here.
You should know that. And we are checking to
see if it is 'hot'. Okay if it is 'hot', it
is going to return true here. If it
returns true, the text is going to be
bold for the course name and the year
and if it is not 'hot', it's not going to
be bold here. And we have a 'MouseArea'
that shows whether we have a 'hot'
attribute and this value when we click
on the item in the ListView here.
Okay our application should be ready now but
there are a few things we forgot.
If you go to the documentation for XmlListModel,
you're going to see that to use
this element you need to import the
module with the following line. We need
to import that so we're going to copy
this and put that here to import this
component here, to be able to use it and
I notice that we made a mistake here by
putting this @ symbols here.
We shouldn't have them here. Okay so remove them.
Again I'm sorry for this. And we
should be able to run our application.
Make sure that you don't have any @ symbol here
and make sure that you have
this XML list model imported. Run the application.
Okay you see that we have
the names for the instructors, we have
the name of the course and the year and
you see that the course for Matt Kabwe
is bolded because it has a hot attribute on it.
Okay this is the course here and
this is the name, this is the year.
If you look down you see that we have another
course that has a hot attribute but
because it is not true, we are not making
it bold in what we have here.
Okay the course is by Lillian here and it is not bold.
And this is really how you read
your data from an XML file, put it in an
XML List Model and fit it to a List View.
Now I want to try a few syntaxes that
we have seen before. Another way you can
query the elements. You can comment this out
so that you have it. I'm going to say
'query' and passing double slashes and say
'course'
and if I run, I should see the same thing.
They are effectively the same thing and
you see that I have my data and I am
seeing my debug output. It is saying
loading and when it's ready I know that.
I have five elements and if you count
what we have in the XML file, we have
one course here, two courses, three courses,
four courses and five courses.
Okay this is what we are successfully reading.
Let's go back to the QML file and if I
wanted to only retrieve the first course,
we also saw this syntax, I can pass in
brackets like this and pass in the index
of the course that I want. If I run this,
I am only going to read one course from
the XML file. You see the number here, the
count and you see that it is only the
course by Matt Kabwe here. I can also
specify the other courses, for example
can pass in two and I am going to read
the second course. Okay we have the
course here. This is all I have to say in
this lecture. I hope you have a better idea
of how you work with XML list model
to read the data from the XML file.
It is really easy and the bulk of it is ready
to be able to work with these queries.
The first query is in the XmlListModel here
and the second one is in the XmlRole
that specifies whatever specific data
that you want to get from the items
that these first query returned.
And if you want to learn more on these queries
and the way you do that you can come to
the documentation. I think they have good examples
on how you work with these things.
You can go through these examples.
They have an XML file, they have the query here,
they have its role. You can look at this
and if you keep going down,
you going to see more examples of things
you can do with these things. If you come to
this location, they are going to tell you
to see xml role query, click on that and
if you keep going down, they're going to
show you a link where you can go and
read about the XPath specification which
is a standard that defines these things
we are doing here in the queries.
You are going to see everything about it.
If you are in the mode for tutorials, you can
come to this link here. This is one
tutorial found online that goes through
the standard of XPath and how it works.
If you need a refresher or an
introduction to it, this is a good thing to look at.
Ok this is all I have to say in this lecture
and the next lecture we're
going to look at how you work with
animations in Qt Quick. I'll see you there.