in this lecture we are looking at the
Model View architecture and QT quick the
model 2 architecture abbreviated MVC is
a design pattern that allows you to
separate the way data is stored and the
way data is displayed to the user. there
are three components the model which
stores your data that you which displays
your data, and the controller which maybe
is the exchange of data between the
model and the view. now tooth doesn't
implement the model view controller
pattern completely, it takes the
controller and strips it down to a
delegate and the delegate does part of
the job that a full-blown controller
would do. in qml specifically, the
delegate defines how each row in the
ListView is going to look. you have to
keep in mind that you have three
components in QT quick: the model the
view and the delegate. now that we have
an idea about the models you delegate
architecture in QT quick, what components
are available to us in Qt Quick so
that we can use them in qml. for
the view you have list view, grid view
and if you are the components that we're
not going to talk about in this chapter.
for the model there is a list model an
XML list model, we are going to look at
all these models, and the delegate is
really a chunk of qml code that
controls the look of each row in your
list view, as we going to see. okay and
one thing you need to understand is that
the data that goes in your model can
really come from anywhere. it can come
from the database the internet. it can
come from a file that you are storing on
your drive. it can come from static data
that you type in your QML code, and a
model gives you a common interface that
you can use to abstract the real source
of data away, so that it can be used by
many components. for example you can take
one list model and feed it to a list
view and the grid view, and there is a
common interface to pass the data back
and forth between these two components,
and you don't need to worry about the
detail
how the data is really stored. this is
the benefit of having the way you store
data abstracted away in a model like
list model and XML list model. okay now
we want to focus on list model a little
bit. the way you use the list model in
your qml code, you really give it a list
of elements that you are going to
display. you can put in these elements
statically when you define a list model,
and this is how it looks in code, you
have a list model component, and inside
you have a bunch of list elements that
contain attribute and value pieces of
data.we're going to look at this in a
moment. okay you can put static list
elements in your list model. that's one
way to put in the data, but you can also
use any of these methods that are
available to you to manipulate your
model at runtime. you can append data,
you can clear data, you can get an
element you can insert, move, remove, and
you can use all these functions, we are
going to have a chance to use some of
these in one of the upcoming lectures.
there are also two properties that are
available to you: count gives you the
number of elements in your model, and
dynamic roles is a property that allows
you to modify the nature of your model
at runtime. if you look at this append
method, it takes a parameter of j/s
object dictionary .I want to focus on
this a little bit. if you are familiar
with JS, you're going to recognize what
we have here. this is a just an object,
and this is how you pass data in your
model dynamically, you pass something
like this. we just looked at an example
of how you can build your list model, and
you see that it takes country and
capital here. if we were to put in a
piece of data like this dynamically, we
would pass in adjust an object that is
structured like this. okay when you pass
a list element dynamically, you pass it
as a JSobject, this is what we mean
here. in QML terminology these
attributes are called roles, okay so we
have two roles in our list model, here we
have a country role and we have
capital role, and we give values to these
roles. these roles can be named to be
anything really, but you need to remember
the name you gave them here, because
you're going to use them to refer to
this piece of data in your delegates
that we're about to see. we just looked
at one type of models that we have want
to look at XML list model. this is a
model that allows you to wrap around an
XML file that is either local or coming
from the internet, and it allows you to
automatically read the data from the XML
file, and fit it to your list view, or
other views that you might have in you
QML file. the source property allows you
to specify where the XML file is going
to come from, and you have a set of
queries that allow you to fetch the data
in your XML file. and you can use XPath,
this is a technology that allows you to
parse an XML file and take the data that
you want from that file. we're going to
see how this works. I take away from here
is that this model wraps around an XML
file and allows you to extract data from
there automatically, and fit that your
list view or grid view if you happen to
need that. and the last piece of the
puzzle that we're going to look at is
the ListView, which is going to tie all
the things we've talked about together.
the ListView has a model property which
lends to the model that you want to show
in the ListView, you have a delegate that
controls how each role in the ListView is
going to look, and we have highlight
header and footer that allows you to
decorate your ListView to make it look
better, and right here we have an example
for this view. this is how you define it,
and we're going to look at this in
detail in a few upcoming lectures. ok
this should be all to spice up your
appetite to work with models and views
in QT quick. in the next lecture we're
going to start looking at list view and
list model in detail, I'll see you then