in this lecture, we're going to look at
another aspects of decorations in your
list views, and that is using sections to
group your data in similar groups. we're
going to go to QT creator and play
with it. okay here we are, in Qt Creator.
we're going to create a new project.
it's a QT quick application, we call it
DecorationSectionDemo, save it in the
usual location. choose our Qt version.
choose our kit, and finish. we want to
change the title here. it is another kind
of decoration, so we say that here. I
want to have a mListView. it's going to
be the usual thing really. the idea is
going to be mListView. it's going to
fill the parent, and we are going to
specify a delegate which is going to be
an external component, so we're going to
say "delegateID" like this. I want to put
in a model that I have prepared to save
some typing. it is nothing special.
it is a ListModel with ListElement.
right now we have roles name and company.
what we want to do is to group these
people in all this view based on the
company where they work. so now we have a
model, let's check the ID mListModel.
mListModel. this is okay.
we want to specify our delegate. again I
am going to put in our delegate like
this. Press ctrl A ctrl I to align. it is
the same thing we've seen before. we have
an ID inside, it is a rectangle that
specifies how each element in the list
view is going to look. so it's a
rectangle with the background color of
beige, border color yellow green, it has
round edges, and inside we have a test
component that says the names of the
person. ok we don't want to display the
company, we only display
the name of the person in the delegate
here, and we have access to this because
the delegate has access to both the
model and the view. the data in there and
the functions that are inside. okay now
we have our model, we have our delegate,
and we have our listview, we want to
know how to group the elements together.
let's go back to the documentation, find
listview. if we look at the list of
properties that we have, we have one
called section. click on that and you're
going to see that this is a grouped
property. ok this property's determined
the expressions to be evaluated and
appearance of Deception levels, this is
what you use to group your elements
based on a criteria of the data that is
stored in the model. in this case, we want
to group the people based on the company
where they work at, and the company is
also stored in the model in all
listmodel here. so we want to put an A
section here. this is how you work with
it. you can do this separately like they
are doing it here in the examples. if you
scroll down you're going to see an
example of how you work with this. section,
property section, criteria section,
delegate like this, but I want to show
you another syntax, because you need to
see that too. you can specify it like
this directly, and you can specify the
properties inside like this. the first
thing we want to specify is the property
that we are going to group by. ok we want
to specify it in here, in quotes, it is
company in the model, criteria is going
to be usage and full strength.
if we go back in the documentation,
you're going to see that the criteria
holds the criteria for forming each
section based on section property. you
can make it a full string, which is
going to show the entire thing. this is
the default or you can group by first
character, so if you had something
like an address book, it's going to group
people by ABC and things like that. but
we are going to use full string in
this example here. so we specify full
string, so we are going to specify a
delegate. this is going to be the
delegate for the section headers. we want
to put in a rectangle like this, because
I don't really want to type this again,
I'm going to put in this rectangle
ctrl A ctrl I, and I'm going to
try and explain it, so the rectangle is
what we have in here. we have an ID for
this rectangle. we have a width and a
height, a color, a border, radius. this is
nothing new to you. right now inside we
have a text component. it has an ID. the
text is going to be the section header.
this property holds what you are
grouping by. in this case we are grouping
people by company, so we're going to see
a section for a company of Google. we are
going to see a section for a company of
10 cent, Apple, Baidu and things like that.
this is the data that you have in this
section property is art your section
here. ok we Center that and specify a
point size for the font. we also want to
make this clickable, and we display the
section here. by now we have our
components in place, and the meat of this
lecture is really this section, you see
here. we are trying to group the data in
our model based on company. the company
is the role that we have in our model, we
want to group by company. we are going to
show the criteria for group end in full
string, so we are going to show the
full names of the companies that we are
grouping by, and the way the section
header is going to look is specified in
this delegate component here. it's going
to be a rectangle, inside we're going to
have a text element, and the text
is going to be displayed is the section
header, and it's going to be the same
thing as the name of the company we are
grouping by. I hope this makes sense, and
if it's not clear,
maybe it's going to be more clear if we
run the application. so we run it. mm-hmm
you see that our people are grouped by
the companies they work at. if we look in
our model, you see that Seth Morris works
at Google. jack may works at Apple. Mary
beige works at 10cent. and you see what
data in here. so sometimes you need this,
when you do, this will come in handy.
but one thing you need to know is that
for your data to be displayed correctly,
you need to have your elements stored
contiuously. what do I mean? let's take
Seth Morris here, copy the element and
put it at the end of the list in the
model. let's run again. mm-hmm you see
that we have Google and we have Miriam,
but if we go to the bottom. you see that
we have another Google header, and we have
Seth Morris inside. and this is really
how the sectioning works. if you don't
have your elements continuously, you are
going to have the header on every piece
of element that comes after the other
element. in this case Google is coming
back after Baidu, and the ListView is
going to let you know that Seth Morris
works at Google by putting a header like
this. I hope this makes sense. if you want
to have only one header for each company,
you're going to have to store your
elements continuously in the model. and
put it back like it was before. let's put
this first again, run our application, and
this is what we had before. one thing you
need to know is that the look of the
section header is controlled by the
delegate property in your section. what
we have here is rectangle. this is all
had to say in this lecture. I hope you
know how you can group your elements in
your list view, and the next lecture
we're going to see how you work with
of repeaters. I see you there.