In this lecture, we're going to see
how you can work with the GridView component in the QML.
This is a component that
allows you to lay out your items
coming from a model in a grid like structure.
We're going to go to QT Creator and play with it.
Here we are in Qt Creator.
We're going to create our project
It's a QT quick application,
we call it 'GridViewDemo', store it in the usual location,
choose a QT version, choose your kit, and finish.
You want to change the title
to say 'GridView Demo'.
And if we go to the documentation and look for a GridView,
they're going to tell you
it displays data from models created from built-in QML types
like ListView and ListModel.
It is back to by model and
the delegate defines how data should be displayed
and your data is displayed in a grid like this.
Okay, this is a great.
So, we're going to go back to our code here,
put in a predefined model to save some time on typing.
This is a list model.
Nothing new here.
It contains list elements and we have two rows in each list element:
a number with this role and
the color with mColor as your role.
We can minimize this actually
to help things a little more readable and put in our grid view.
The ID is going to be 'mGridViewId'.
It's going to fill the parent
Model is going to be model ID and
it's going to have a delegate just like
we have for the ListView.
We have a nice delegate also prepared. Ctrl+A , Ctrl+I to align.
It is nothing special also
but we are using the roles in our model
to put data in our delegate here.
You can see the color is
coming from the list element here.
This is our role for the color
and we are displaying the number
that is coming from the model as well.
You can see this is the number role that we are using here.
The rest you have really all seen before.
We are centering the text,
they are sending the font here.
Let's run the application and see what we get
Mm-hmm. This is our grid view.
You see that it tries to fill the available width with these rectangles here
but if you reduce the width,
you see that it flows to the next lines
until we have the data filling the available width.
Okay this is the behavior
you have with the grid view.
There are a few settings you can apply
to your grid view here.
For example you can control the layout direction.
Right now, it is going from left to right but
we can make it go from right to left.
Okay, when we do that, we are going to
start counting from 1 to 3 from the right here and going to the left.
Let's do that.
We can come in our code here and
say layoutDirection and say Qt.RightToLeft just like this.
Let's run. Mm-hmm
1 2 3 from right to left and this is not out of the blue.
You can come back to the documentation,
find GridView,
and you're going to see a bunch of properties that you have
and one of them is layoutDirection
and they show you things
you can pass in here.
If you look here, we also have another property that is called 'flow'
and you can use this to hold the flow of the grid.
Okay, right now it is flowing
from left to right by default,
but we can also make it flow from top to bottom.
We can come back to the code,
put in a flow property and say
'GridView.FlowTopToBottom'
Let's run.
You see that it is saying
one two three from top to bottom.
Without the flow property setting, it was going from left to right
and wrapping to the next lines.
Now it is going from top to bottom
and wrapping to the columns as we go from right to left.
I hope this makes sense.
We can check this out to show you what we had before
because sometimes it is easy to forget.
And you can see that
one two three from left to right.
You can play with these properties and see what you get.
And if you happen to need these features,
they are available to you ready to be used.
And this is really all I have
to share about the GridView component.
It is very easy to use and it allows you to
layout the data that is coming from your model
in a grid like structure.
And you have a bunch of properties that you can play with
to achieve the design that you want.
In the next lecture, we're going to
visit the XmlListModel component and
see how you can fit it the data from an
XML file.
I'll see you there.