This is video of 4.3 of controlling multimedia which covers interacting with the open computer vision
library. In this video we're going to cover linking or including open computer vision in Qt projects,
cascade classifiers for facial detection and drawing on images.
So let's go ahead and get started.
The first thing that we need to do is go ahead and make sure that the opencv IncludePath and the
opencv libraries are linked correctly in our project file.
Now for Linux I've already done this or Unix in this case as the .pro file calls it, because for Linux
and Unix these paths are standard but for my Windows users you're going to have to actually get the
open computer vision library in and then add in the correct path.
So I've included like a nominal path but you need to actually add in the correct path for your setup.
And so we need to add in both the INCLUDEPATH which you can see here.
So Windows users need to uncomment this and add in the correct one. And you'll need to actually add in
the LIBS and you can see that all here.
So you need to find those three LIBS and make sure that they're all linked correctly in your project file.
So once we've got all that set up let's go ahead and take a look at the code.
Now this is very familiar.
This is basically the same code that we did last time using our custom video surface.
The only difference is we're switching back to using a QCamera. But if you look at our implementation
file you can see and scroll all the way to the bottom and look where we actually set the camera.
You can see instead of setting the Viewfinder to something else, we actually set this to be our custom
videosurface.
So again almost exactly like the last implementation.
And if you look at the VideoWidget.
Right?
Nothing has changed here, we reimplement the paintEvent and resizeEvent.
And if we look at the implementation file, we create the QPainter, set the RenderHint and actually
passed into our video_surface. And for a resizeEvent same thing, we call the parent implementation and
then call it on our video_surface.
So now if we look at our video_surface and scroll all the way to the bottom, you're going to find we
have a new private data member here.
This computer vision CascadeClassifier. So the Cascade Classifier is the actual technology that we're
going to be using to do our facial detection. Cascade Classifiers are very efficient object detectors
and the open computer vision library comes with pre-trained classifiers that can be used to detect faces.
Well
cascade classifiers are not the most accurate technology.
They are one of the faster methods available for finding faces, which is why we're going to use them
here.
Now you see that we've actually created an instance here. But if we don't actually load a pre-trained
data file our classifier won't work.
So we're going to start by loading a file and so we'll switch to our implementation method,
Scroll up the top here and you'll see there's a couple interesting things here.
So if we switch back to the .pro file and look at the bottom, this code right here is kind of interesting.
What it does is actually copies the haarcascade_frontalface_default.xml from the source code
directory into our executable directory.
And the reason we're doing that is because our cascade classifier has to take a C string,
so we need to actually pass that in manually.
So we're going to go ahead and do that now.
So since we copied that data we can actually use this QCoreApplication applicationDirPath to
get the executable directory out and then we know this is our file name.
So if we combine these two things we can get the full path out or we can get the full file path out.
So let's go ahead and do that right now.
Awesome.
So once we've got the file path out,
we'll call our load method on our face_classifier.
And again the only weird thing is we need to actually pass in this C string to this, to our load method
because that's what it's expecting.
And then you see we've got this red_pen which if we switch back to our data implementation it's just a
QPen.
All this is going to draw the boxes around so we set it to be red and we set the width to be 10.
Awesome.
So now that we've loaded up our face_classifier, the method that we need to use is the
detectMultiScale method and it's going to actually do the facial detection.
The only problem is that we need to pass in a computer vision mat to the method to make it happen, which
means we basically need to convert from a QImage to a CV mat.
Matt So let's scroll down to our paint method. And right after we create our QImage from our video frame
which is right here,
we just use the current_video_frame. Remember it's actually a video_frame that we've stored. And you can see we've
actually got a helper method here.
So we've got this variable here that we're creating is called cv Mat gray_mat_image.
And we call the get method to get that out.
So let's go ahead and look at that.
So if we scroll down you can see that we're actually iterating on the QImage Format. So we have the
switch statement here.
And we've got our format and a bunch of cases.
And basically if we scroll all the way to the bottom it actually passes us off to another method which
takes the qimage_to_matt basically takes the qimage and then it takes a computer vision enum.
And enum that it needs is just based on the actual image format that we have.
So all these cases here are the only thing that really truly only different thing in them if we're passing in
different enums to make sure that they get instantiated correctly.
And if you want the method for that it's actually at the top, it's this qimage_to_mat that we pass in the image
height, widht, the format and the actual data information right there.
And then we static cast the bytesPerLine. So very standard data manipulation.
You know we're not going to get into that too much because we want to do all the interesting stuff
instead. Awesome.
So let's go and scroll down.
So if we make it to the end,
we successfully created a CV Mat and the variable name is the actual mat_image.
Now the important thing to know about this mat_image.
We can't make changes to it because we'll actually make changes to our original image.
So that's one of the important things to know.
So because we don't want to make any changes to our original image, so let's go ahead and create a new instance
which we'll call cv Mat gray_mat_image, which will be the one that I actually do operations
on.
Awesome.
So our cascade classifier works best in gray scale.
So let's go ahead and change our original image to grayscale using the cvtColor method. And we need
to specify the original mat which is where the data is coming from,
the result mat
which is where the data is going and the color change that is going to occur.
So we're using our mat_image which is mapped to our original documents that we don't want to change.
And that's our input, our output is this gray_mat_image.
And then we're actually changing it from BGR, which is a color scheme that openCV uses, to gray scale.
So once we have got our gray image, the next thing that we want to do is actually equalize the histograms.
This is going to help increase the contrast in our image so that our features are more exaggerated.
Now since we've finally got our gray_mat_image, we'll go ahead and just make the changes to that.
So we're going to call the cv equalizeHist method. And then the last thing that we need to do is go
ahead and return this gray_mat_image, and that's it.
That's how we successfully go from a QImage to a cv Mat, is we use this qimage_to_mat helper
and we base it on exactly which QImage Format's coming in.
And then we've got our helper method up at the top that just takes our height width, the format that we
passed in and the actual data information.
And then lastly the bytesPerLine. And once we've got that image out we scroll down to the bottom.
We go ahead and change the color into gray scale because our cascade classifier works better on that. We
use this equalize histogram function to sharpen the features to make them more contrasting.
And then we go ahead and return that gray image which brings us right here.
So now that we've got our gray_mat_image, let's go ahead and use the detectMultiScale method.
So the two big things that need to be passed in include the mat_image and something to record where
the method detects face is, which in this case will be this standard vector here, which is just a vector
of cv rectangles and we've called that faces.
We're also going to say that in order for a face to be detected it needs to be a certain size.
So in this case what we're using is the image size columns divided by four and the rows divided by four.
So basically an image a face has to be at least take up a quarter of the screen in order to actually
be detected.
So passing in this min_face_size will help speed up the actual computation.
So let's go ahead and actually figure out where our faces are
by using the detectMultiScale method.
So there's a couple other data members in here that we pass in.
Basically these help us tweak the detection.
And that's a little outside the scope of this tutorial.
But feel free to explore the detectMultiScale documentation and tweak the variables based on your
specific use case.
But this is a pretty good general use case right here. And if you need something more fancy than that and
go ahead and tweak those.
So basically once we've done this method detectMultiScale, we pass in our gray_mat_images and it's
actually going to push all that information into our cv rect vector here of faces.
So the last thing that we want to do is go ahead and create a painter and draw directly on our images.
So we want to get back into the Qt way of doing things.
Perfect.
So once we've got this painter created and we've told that we're going to draw directly on this image
by passing it in, let's go ahead and actually draw rectangles for each of our faces.
So we need to convert from the cv rect into a QRect.
And I've already done the first two steps here by getting the top_left point and the bottom_right point.
So we'll just go ahead and take those,
the top_left point and the bottom_right point and create a QRectangle out of that and then pass that
into our image_painter to draw. Awesome.
So with that we've actually successfully created image. So everything else, all the code here is exactly
like it was before.
Right so we check to make sure the scanLine, if it's the bottom to top then we'll go ahead and do that.
And we've got a little Debug here to see how many faces we detect.
And at the very end of that, once we've actually drawn our actual QImage we make sure that we unmap
the data.
So let's go ahead and run this.
And you can see if I get close enough to the camera,
we're drawing the rectangle and actually seeing our face.
So we successfully used our computer vision library in order to detect faces.
So with that we successfully learned how to detect faces,
draw a rectangle around the detected face and link open computer vision to a project. Join us next time
where we'll cover working with Qt 3D.