This is Section 4 of mastering Qt programming which covers controlling multimedia. So let's go ahead
and get started with the multimedia capture. In this video
we're going to cover how to capture images, how to capture videos and finally how to configure our settings
for capture.
So let's go ahead and start with our image capture.
Now in this example we want our users to be able to select the cameras dynamically
in the case that our users have multiple cameras. Now we haven't gotten into memory management very much
since we've been leaning on Qt's parent child ownership model to do this for us.
But in this case since we're dynamically allocating the camera, we're going to have a couple of members
that are going to fall outside of the parent child ownership model.
So we're going to use a scope pointer to automatically delete objects for us whenever they go out of
scope. And the class we are going to be using to do this is QScopedPointer. Specifically will be managing
the QCamera and the QImageCapture this way.
So let's go ahead and create those member instances real quick.
So our QCamera instance right here controls the camera, the QImageCamera, the QImageCapture class
or instance is actually the high level image recording class which translates from the camera into an
actual file and the QCameraViewfinder here is going to go ahead and display whatever our QCamera
sees for us so that we know what we're taking a picture of.
So let's go ahead and switch into the implementation file.
And the first thing that we want to do is go ahead and create our views so that our users know what
we're taking a picture of.
Awesome.
So our UI is going to be this actual view which is going to show what we're taking a picture of and
a push button which will be used to go ahead and tell when to take the image.
So we create this blank QWidget.
And if you look at this set up UI function you can see that we create a layout and add both our camera_view
and our QPushButton to this layout before sending it to this widget.
So now that we've got the user interface set up, let's go ahead and grab all of the cameras so that our
users can select them dynamically.
So we'll do this using a static method available cameras.
Now the easiest way to give our users an option is to add all of this information up to a menu bar. So
our QMainWindow already has a menu bar built in so let's grab a reference to it. And then let's go
ahead and add a specific menu which will call devices to our menu bar. Perfect.
So we want to go ahead and iterate through each one of our QCameraInfos that we created as part of
this QList right here.
And I'm not going to get too much in the code to do this but basically we go ahead and create a
QAction.
We set this action to be checkable.
We set it to be the actual QCameraInfo so that every time a user selects this, this is the actual value
that will get passed whenever our user triggers something new.
And then we check to see if the camera info that we're iterating through is the default camera.
And if it is we go ahead and set that to be checked.
So we set it to be checkable here and then set to be checked here and then we go ahead and add each
action that we've created as part of this first line to the device menu that we created up here.
So the only thing that we're missing from all of this code right now is an action group. An action
group will help manage all of our actions for us though we have a single interface that we can use to
actually change things.
Let's go ahead and create that now.
Perfect.
So now that we've got this camera_group which is a QActionGroup, what we want is every time our user
selects a new camera_action here we want that to be passed to our
set_camera_action slot.
So let's go ahead and connect the QActionGroup's triggered signal up to the set_camera_action slot.
Awesome.
So we've successfully added the ability for our user to change which camera that we want to use with
only a couple of lines of code.
So let's go ahead and scroll back up.
Now the one thing that we didn't do is we haven't actually set any of the cameras.
So let's go ahead and set the camera to be the default camera and our CameraInfo class has a static
method called defaultCamera which we can use to go ahead and set the default camera.
So we haven't implemented these cameras slots.
Let's go ahead and scroll down and implement that.
So the first thing that we're going to want to do in here is actually create a new instance of our camera.
Now remember that these are the QScopedPointer that QCamera and the QCameraImageCapture are
all wrapped in this QScopedPointer so the interface is going to look a little bit different.
But let's go ahead and create our instance here.
And then once we've actually created our instance, let's go ahead and set our new image capture.
And what the QImageCapture class actually needs a reference to the specific camera.
So we're going to pass that in as well.
Perfect.
So let's make sure that our camera is set for actual image capture real quick and we can do this using
the setCaptureMode method.
And we'll change it to CaptureStillimages.
And the last thing that we need to do as part of this method is set our viewfinder or reset our viewfinder
so that it's capturing the data from this class specifically.
So we'll go ahead and do that now using the setViewfinder method.
Perfect.
So the last thing that we need to do as part of this application is go ahead and wire up our PushButton.
So we've set the camera and we've set up all the camera devices we've set up the UI.
So now whenever we push our QPushButton let's make sure we actually take an image.
Now since we're dynamically resetting the image capture which is the class that uses to actually save
a file here, we're going to use a functor rather than connecting directly to the instance that's part
of this class.
Cool. So let's go ahead and run this and take a picture.
Looks like I missed a semi colon here.
So now let's go ahead and run this and take a picture.
Awesome.
So you can see we've got our actual viewfinder here and we've got our push button and if we click this
and then change in here
and look at the most recent one you can see that we've successfully managed to capture an image. Awesome.
So now that we've got pictures working, let's go ahead and record some video.
So we'll open the record project here and we'll take a look.
Now all the code should look very similar but the one thing is that instead of using a QCameraImageCapture
we're going to use a QMediaRecorder instead, so let's go ahead and create that. Perfect and
then we'll switch to implementation file and we'll go down to the set_camera function or slot here.
We need to actually initialize this QMediaRecorder just like we did our QImageCapture by passing
in a reference to the camera.
Awesome.
Now that the QMediaRecorder is initialized, let's set up the record and stop recording slots as part
of the MainWindow.
Remember we're not going to connect our signals directly to the instance member which in this case is
media_recorder.
Since we're replacing it every time we change the device so we're going to put the slots on the parent
widget instead which in this case is the MainWindow.
So in order to record the function that we want to call is just record in order to stop recording the
function that we want to call is
Stop.
Cool.
So let's go ahead and scroll up to the top.
You can see that we're creating 2 QPushButtons.
One is called the record_button which has the words record in it and the other is the stop_record. And
you see at the bottom of this class we're actually connecting those to the slots that we just created
server, the clicked signal gets connected to the record slot and the stop_record_button and clicked signal gets
connected to the stop_recording slot.
The only thing that we don't have implemented here that's different is we actually want to dynamically
change these buttons so that the only ones that are unable are things you can do.
So example while we're recording we don't want our users to be able to hit the record button anymore.
And similarly when we're not recording we don't want our users to be able to hit the stop recording
button and the slot that we've set up to do this is the update_recorder_state slot.
And scroll down you can see the implementation here.
We've got two cases here, the RecordingState and the StoppedState. And whenever we are actually recording
we make sure that our users can't select our record button.
And similarly whenever we are not recording we make sure that our users can't select our stop recording.
So let's go ahead and connect up the signal which is on the QMediaRecorder instance and the signal
that we want is the actual stateChanged signal. I'll go and connect that to our slot. Perfect. So we've
successfully connected that up, so now every time our QMediaRecorder state gets changed,
we'll be able to update the recorder state in our actual function which is just going to change the
buttons here, and we're just iterating through or switching on an enum which is the actual
QMediaRecorderState.
So the very last thing that we need to do here is we need to check to make sure that we can actually
record video on our default camera.
So if we can we want to go ahead and set the capture mode to be CaptureVideo. And if we can actually
do this we want to let our users know. Perfect.
So let's go ahead and run this and capture some video.
So you can see our 2 buttons here, down the bottom, and if we hit record we can see that the record actually
fades out and if we hit stop recording we successfully created that and we can show this is the case
by go ahead and opening up this clip, which you can actually see we have managed to successfully record
video there.
So the one thing that you might not know is you might want to actually change the file format that you're
recording in.
So right now it's just recording in whatever the default is.
So the way to check to see what we've got is there's actually a function on our media recorder. And that's
the supportedAudioCodecs.
So this would actually get you out a StringList of everything and then you could you know display
that to your users and whatever you could have them pick it and have them actually set it as well.
And you could either use you know supported_audio, you've got a ContainerFormat and the EncodingSettings
too, you've got default methods to select each of these and the set methods that actually set
those.
So I would encourage you to play around with those on your own to see what's available on your system.
But with that we've successfully learned how to capture images, how to capture videos and briefly touched
on how to configure images and videos.
Please join us next time where we cover multimedia playback.