This is video 4.2 of controlling multimedia which covers multimedia playback. And in this video we're going
to cover how to play videos using playlists and advanced video playback.
So let's go ahead and get started.
If we open our Play project and look at some of the data members in this media scroll all the way down
to the bottom you can see that we've got a QMediaPlayer, a QMediaPlaylists and a QVideoWidget.
Our QMediaPlayer can play songs, movies, or internet radio.
Our playlist holds a list of everything that we want to play and our video widget will actually play
the content.
So let's go ahead and switch to our implementation file and initialize some of these classes.
And the last thing that we need to do is go ahead and set our media player to have the VideoOutput
of our video_widget. Awesome.
So now that we got all this stuff initialized, let's go ahead and set up some of the interactivity. So
you can see that we've got a bunch of PushButtons, we've got play, pause, stop, next and previous video.
Let's go and connect some of those up.
So the play_button will go ahead and get connected up to the MediaPlayer Play slot.
The pause_button will get connected to the QMediaPlayer Pause slot.
And similarly the stop_button will connect to to the MediaPlayer Stop slot.
Now the next video and previous video, the clicked signals for these are actually going to get connected
to our MediaPlaylist.
And the MmediaPlaylist has a Next slot and a Previous slot, so we'll go and connect those right up.
Now we want to update our buttons dynamically to let our users know what they can do or what makes sense
to use.
So we'll use the update_button slot.
That's part of this MainWindow class. To selectively enable and disable buttons based on
the media_player_state,
The QMediaPlayer has a stateChanged signal, so let's wire that up.
And the last thing is to go ahead and update our state using the StoppedState since that'll be the default
for it.
Now we want our users to be able to load files into our playlists.
So let's add this ability into our menu bar. And once we've got that
QAction, let's go ahead and connect the triggered signal to the trigger_media_file_ slot that's part
of this
MainWindow.
Awesome.
So let's scroll down to the slot and let's implement this using the FileName method from QFileDialog
to allow users to select which files they want. Cool.
So this will basically our QFileDialog will open up, our users can select files and the names, the
StringList of those files that we've pushed here.
So we will iterate over each of these and get the filepath out. And what we want to do is go ahead and add these
to our media playlist. And we will do that using the addMedia method.
Now the addMedia method expects a Url, so we'll use the QUrl class to convert from a QString to the
Url expects. Lastly we want to see if the currentIndex is on set. And if it is we'll use the setCurrentIndex
function to change it from the first index
if it is. So if the media_playlist's currentIndex is equal to -1 we'll just set it equal
to 0. 0 will always be the first index in an array.
Awesome.
So we set up our simple MediaPlayer.
Let's go ahead and run it.
And if we click open file here and we navigate to a file and hit play.
You can see that we've got a simple video going. Awesome.
Now we need to go a little bit deeper than this in order to set up working directly with video for the
next section.
So how do we get lower access to the actual data?
Well in order to do this we'll need to subclass and implement a QAbstractVideoSurface.
So if we open up our complex_playback project and look at the MainWindow and scroll down the code, looks
very similar.
The only difference is instead of creating a QVideoWidget we create our own specific implementation
of VideoWidget.
And if you look at the implementation file, instead of setting the VideoOutput to be our QWidget
we call this get_videosurface helper method.
So if we go ahead and change over to our VideoWidget
you can see that we have re-implemented the paintEvent and the resizeEvent.
So for this example we'll be using Qt painting engine so that we can focus more on the data manipulation
and less on explaining graphics library calls.
But this doesn't mean that we'll take a performance hit for this example.
So we switch over to the implementation file or a VideoWidget.
You can see for our paintEvent, it's very simple.
We create a QPainter.
We set the RenderHint to be Antialiasing and then we pass it off to our custom class which is the VideoSurface.
And we basically do the same thing for a resizeEvent. We call the parent class and then we pass
it off to our custom implementation.
So now if we look at the header file for our VideoSurface class there is kind of a lot of code here
and I'm not going to get into all of it.
What I want to do is just follow the data because what we're interested in is how the video data gets
here and how it gets displayed.
So we're going to leave out some of these bottom classes which include these supportedPixelFormat and
nearestFormat methods.
Instead we're going to go ahead and start with our start function.
That's where I actually enter into the usage of this class.
So if we open up our implementation file and scroll to the start, you can see that we had passed in a
QVideoSurfaceFormat in the form of format. And the first thing that we want to do is go ahead and get
the size and an actual QImage image_format, because we will be using the QImage class to kind of help
us out.
We want to translate from the VideoSurfaceFormat to the ImageFormat so let's go and do that first.
And you can see for our getting the QImage format out
we actually use a static method ImageFormatFromPixelFormat, that's included in QVideoFrame.
Awesome.
So the first thing we want to do is go ahead and put a check in here, and we want check to see if the
image format that we got out is actually valid
and if there is actually data in our size. And if there's not we want to go ahead and punch out of this
start function to tell our user that we can actually do what they need them to do.
Perfect. So if we make it pass this first statement then we are good to go.
We are in business.
So the first thing we want to do is store our image_format that we just created there and store the
size as part of the class.
And then you can see here we've got a bunch of stuff that has to deal with the actual size.
So we create get this source_rectangle and we actually call our parent class.
The next thing that we do is actually update the video_widget geometry and then resize it.
So let's go ahead and look at this resize function.
So there's a couple of things that we need to know.
First how big is the actual video coming in.
And we get that from our surfaceFormat sizeHint.
Next thing we want to know is how big is our parent widget which we can get from the size method.
And then what we do is we basically scale the video size using the widget_size that we got out. And there's
couple of helper methods that we use, which is the boundedTo method. And we tell Qt that we want to
go ahead and keep that aspect ratio going. But once we've got our actual video sized, according to what
our parent widget is, then we'll go ahead and create this target_rectangle which is just the point 0
0 to the video size and we move the target_rectangle to the center of our video widget.
So that's the resize function in a show.
So let's go on to the next one.
So this is where we're actually starting to touch the actual QVideoFrames as part of the present
method.
So we get, as part of a method call, we get our frames in and the first thing that we do is go ahead and
check to make sure that the start method was called with the actual frame that we're getting passed
in.
And if it's not we'll go ahead and set an error and stop and return false because this is a boolean.
But if everything is valid then we'll go ahead and store the current frame that we got passed in and
then we're going to do something different. We're going to actually trigger a repaint.
So we're just going to store the frame information and then trigger a repaint.
So let's go ahead and look at the paint method.
Because if you remember our parent widget, this paint class is the next thing that we're pretty much
the only thing that we're going to call in a paintEvent.
So the repaint that we just call will trigger that.
And then we'll drop right into here.
So the first thing we want to do as part of our paint class is actually make sure that our video frame
is set to ReadOnly. And then we're going to go ahead and create a QImage.
Remember that the video frame data is stored in the data member current_video_frame.
So we're going to use that to go ahead and create our QImage.
And once we've actually created our image let's just go ahead and draw. And our image needs to know
how big the information came in on and how small the surface that we're actually going to paint on as
well as our actual image information.
And then when we have actually successfully drawn our image, we'll go ahead and release the video data.
Now there is one weird thing here and that is sometimes our video data will come in upside down from
our normal convention.
So we actually need to check for that.
And I'm not going to be into this too much but we're just going to tell QPainter to paint upside down in this case
and we'll be using the translate method to do that for us and that will make it a little bit easier.
So let's go ahead and run this now real quick.
That should be everything that we need.
And if we click Open File, go to our clip here and hit play,
you can see that we've successfully implemented our abstract video surface completely.
And that's going to set us up for success because now we actually know how to get out our QVideoFrame
and how to actually work with our data directly.
Right?
And we do that with this current_video_frame, the bits, width, heighth and bytesPerLine.
So with that we successfully learned how to work with more advanced video by handling the video data
directly, added in some media player playlists handling and learn how to play videos. So join us next
time we'll work with interacting with open computer vision.