And this is the video 3.3 of interacting with the web which covers the Qt WebChannel. In this video we're
going to cover how QWebChannel works.
The C++ WebChannel API.
And lastly the Javascript WebChannel API.
So first let's talk about how Qt WebChannel works. WebChannel works by publishing a QObject through
an instance of QWebChannel on the application side. On the web site side,
there's a corresponding QWebChannel.JS, which translates the published
QObject into javascript.
QWebChannels on both the application and the website side are responsible for translating objects
between C++ and Javascript so that they both have the same data members and methods which include signals,
slots, and published
QProperties. QWebChannel does not implement any method to actually send the ones and zeros between
the two platforms.
So we'll have to implement that ourselves. Part of implementing this transportation method means that
we have to implement our transportation in both C++ and javascript which is the reason we will be using
web sockets.
So now that we have a basic idea of how Qt WebChannel works, lets get into the nitty gritty of this
example.
Now as I mentioned before, we're going to be using web sockets. Web sockets are nice because the javascript
implementation is in Chromium and launching a Web socket server in Qt is really easy, which means
the only thing that were on the hook for is providing the interface between QWebChannel and the web
socket.
Now since this example is already pretty involved we're going to leverage some of the open source code
from the other QWebChannel examples and go ahead and skip that implementation.
Feel free to read the source code if you'd like.
So let's go ahead and get into the code.
So if you look at our header and source files, the code that we're not going to cover is this
websocketclientwrapper and websockettransport. So all that code is just straight from other QWebChannel examples.
You can go ahead and read through it if you'd like them.
The other code that we're not going to cover if you open up the resources and then go to the QWebChannel.JS
This is how Qt actually implements the QWebChannel for the javascript API.
So we're more interested in how we're going to use QWebChannel than how Qt provides it, so we won't be
looking at this code either.
But if we go to our MainWindow, we can start looking at some of the code that we are going to be looking
at.
So if we scroll down to our data members you'll see we have the Web browser, the Web Channel, a Web Socket
Server a Web Socket to QWebChannel interface, which is again something we won't be covering.
And our object which we're going to publish over QWebChannel.
Cool.
So let's go ahead and open up this .cpp file and if we scroll up to our constructor you can see that we create
our browser, load a web page and set the browser as the central widget in the MainWindow.
The next thing that we want to do is go ahead and start our web socket servers.
Let's go down to this method.
We need to create an instance of QWebSocket server and then call the listen method onto port 1 2 3
4 5. The Listen method returns a boolean which lets us know if it was successfully attached to the requested
port or not.
Now please note as part of the implementation we're using a NonSecureMode on this WebSocketServer
which we're only doing because we're putting it over the LocalHost, so please make sure that if you
put this over the web that you use something other than a NonSecureMode.
Awesome.
So now that we've got our web socket server up and running,
let's go ahead and create our QWebChannel. Sweet.
So let's go ahead and register the object that we're going to be playing with on the javascript side.
We'll be using the register method and we'll need to pass in a string that we use to identify the object
on the javascript side and pass in a reference to the object itself.
Now we need to set up the transportation or communication between our two key web channels.
So if we look at the setup_webchannel_transport method, remember that we're just taking this code from
other Qt WebChannel tutorials, but basically we need to wrap the incoming web socket clients so that
whenever one comes in, it emits a WebSocketTransport class. A WebSocketTransport class is a concrete
implementation of the base class.
QWebChannelAbstractTransport. Again
don't get too wrapped up in this code.
It's purely an implementation thing.
And if I was doing another example like this I would simply reuse this code.
But with that we'll have successfully set up our web channel, we'll have set up the transportation and published
an object.
So we're pretty much ready from the application side.
So the next thing that we need to do is go ahead and focus on the website side.
Now we've already loaded our webpage in line 17.
The only other thing that we need to do is go ahead and inject our Javascript.
So let's go ahead and scroll down to this method.
So in order to inject javascript we first need to grab the page out of our WebView first, we'll then load
our custom javascript from the files with a helper method before finally inserting the javascript into
the page.
Awesome.
So if we go ahead and look at this custom method get_custom_javascript or you can see we're actually creating
this QByteArray which we're calling javascript. And then we're just basically opening up these
files here and dumping those into our javascript QByteArray. Eventually we create a
QWebEngineScript which we'll just call script and we go ahead and pass in the source code of
QByteArray in on that line and then go ahead and set the name and set a couple of other variables here before
returning that javascript back out.
Awesome.
So that's how we go ahead and inject the javascript, but what are we actually doing in the javascript?
Well let's go ahead and open it up.
So we're going to do all of this on the onload function and you see the first thing that we're going
to go ahead and do is create a WebSocket and we're going to be listening on the localhost port
12345 just like our WebSocketServer is. Whenever our socket gets open, we go ahead
and create a callback where we immediately create our javascript QWebChannel and that will take
in our socket and then we create another callback which will actually get our channel passed in.
And now we can actually start coding.
So the first thing that we want to do is get access to the interactive objects that we registered or
published.
So as part of this channel object, it's actually going to have a data member called objects which we
can use to access our interactive object that we published. Awesome.
So let's go ahead and look at the Class of that object that we just got access to.
So if we go back and we look at the interactor.h we see a pretty complicated class.
So QWebChannel will only publish signals, slots, and Qt properties.
You can see in this class header file, we've got several slots, a signal and one QProperty. We'll get
in the QProperties more as we start working with QML.
But for now just understand that if we want to access data members we need to tell Qt what the
type of the data member is, what the name will be in, the name will be in this case who_changed_this_string.
The method to read which is get_string, the method to write which is set_string, and the signal that will
notify of us of changes which in this case is the string_changed signal.
Again we'll get lots more practice with writing and understanding how
Q properties working when we get into QML.
So let's go ahead and look at our slots.
So we've got a method that launches a new window.
We've got a method that returns a string and a method that just tells us to call it.
So let's switch back to the javascripts. And now that we've got access to the actual object,
let's go ahead and use all of these signals, slots, and Q properties.
So the first thing we want to do is go ahead and invoke a C++ slot. And we'll invoke the slot that the
code told us to call. Very easy.
So how do we handle a slot if it returns a value, like our method that returns a string?
Well since the communication is asynchronous, we'll need to use a callback.
So now that we've called a slot, how do we connect a signal?
Well it's remarkably similar.
We need to use a callback as well.
And I guess one thing to note is we don't have to use a callback here but we do need to set this equal
to something.
So if we look at this code real quick, notice how we were able to call this who_changed_this_string
data member directly.
So if we look back at our interactor, right.
This is basically happens because of this Q property because we actually set this read method here as
get_string, that enables us to call who_change_this_string exactly like this and get a return value like
we expect.
So guess what we can do if we've defined this write function with the set_string.
Well if you guess that we'd be able to assign the value using the assignment operator,
you guessed correctly.
So let's go ahead and demonstrate that. Awesome.
So if we look at the Html real quick that we're doing all these operations on, you're going to see a very
sparse example.
It basically only includes the instructions to "press F12 to bring up the javascript debugger" which we've
included is the getfirebug script right here. And then we've also got a button.
So far we haven't really included our user in any of this interactivity that we've been doing.
So let's go ahead and fix this by adding an event listener which listens for a click on the button and
launches a new window in response.
Right.
And so if you would just note "Add an event listener to HTML buttons 'click' method which calls the C++ method
launch_new_window".
Awesome.
So with that we were able to successfully use connect to a signal, we called two different types of slots,
one without a return value and one with the return value. We were able to read our Q property.
We were able to write to our Q property and we actually hooked up an HTML element in the form of a button
to our launch_new_window.
So let's go ahead and run this and see if it works.
Awesome.
So looks like everything is working
so far so well. So let's go ahead and press F12, and we can see here if we look back at our javascript
code and we look at the output from our application output, we can actually see some of the results of
our activity. And if we clicked this button you can see that a dialog pops open for us.
So we've got we've been successfully able to call signals and slots using javascript and see the results
in the console here.
And we've been able to successfully interact and call and change stuff from our actual javascript and
you can play around more with this example on your own.
So we successfully integrated our gooey and our Website elements, where would we actually use this?
Well one of the biggest things would be if your company that is in the middle of transitioning from
desktop to the web or maybe vice versa.
A lot of times we've got to make that transition very slowly as developer time is really expensive.
So we don't want to rewrite all our services at once.
So leveraging QWebChannel like this can be a good way to actually ease that transition
If you're transitioning from the web to the desktop or from the desktop to the Web.
But with that we've successfully learned how QWebChannel works, including both the C++ and Javascript
APIs. So join us in the next section where we go over how to control multimedia.