And this is the video 3.2 of interacting with the web which covers web engine widgets. In this video we're
going to cover the Qt web engine widgets, application programmer interface, build a simple web browser
using widgets and a couple custom browser ideas.
So let's start with the easy question.
Why would we cover the API or application programmer interface?
We want to see where the majority of the functionality for this module is.
Additionally an API review helps us understand how the code is supposed to work so that we can leverage
the pre-made code rather than fight against it.
So let's take a look.
Remember that this is the top level architecture that we showed from the last time.
And here's how this breaks down into actual class names.
The top level widget is QWebEngineView.
Now I've outlined some of what I saw to be most of the important functions on the right.
So you can see here that we can set either a Url, Page or Html document on our top level view,
which is super convenient as we'll see in a second.
Below the QWebEngineView is the QWebEnginePage.
This is where the meat of the module is, it's in the page itself.
Now I didn't outline it here but the page also has some of the same functions as the view does.
So for example you can set the Url or the Html on the page itself, just like you can with a top level view.
The way to think that page can be seen if you open a normal web browser, which you'll typically see in
the web browser, is the actual tabbed interface.
Each tab represents another page, and any one time only one page is showing.
But if you click on a tab it will switch to the relevant page.
Now whether you choose to implement a web browser as a tabbed interface is up to you.
You could use for example a drop down list to change between your different pages, or whatever other
interesting interfaces you can think of. Some of the interesting functions I saw on the page included
the icon and title functions, which will return you the icon and title for the page.
Additional functions for this class include download, run javascript, and print.
So all in all QWebEnginePage is a very very powerful class and you'll be seeing a lot of it.
The enum WebAction is also part of this class and very important.
We'll review it once we finished up with this diagram.
So below the page are some other classes that we won't get into too much here.
The profile is very interesting.
If you wanted to implement like incognito mode the profile is how you would do it.
You can also implement your own settings, script, and cookie handling from that profile as well.
So if your web browser needs to dive into any of these areas they each have their own distinct classes
and functions to go along with them.
Now that we're done with that diagram, Let's talk about some of the actions. A lot of the user actions
are tracked in a single enum in QWebEnginePage.
I've copied a couple up here just to illustrate where to go to find some functionality.
So for example some of the actions that are owned by the page include back, forward, stop, cut, copy, and
paste.
But if you look at the actual documentation which we'll see here WebEnginePage WebAction, you can see there
actually like 44 different enums here.
So this is super important if you're implementing a more fully featured web browser to make sure that
you correctly handle each of these actions.
But that's a quick crash course in the API.
So now that we have an understanding of how the code works together, let's go ahead and create a quick
web browser.
So if you open up the web engine project and open up the MainWindow_H you can see here we've
got a very streamlined class. Looking at the private section
there's only three private widgets here,
a QWidget, a QWebEngineView and a QLineEdit.
We use the QLineEdit to input and view our current Urls, and we use the central_widget to
help navigate some of the layout.
Basically what we need to do is put our Url above our web_view.
So let's go ahead and switch to our implementation of our mainwindow and the first thing that we'll
do is go ahead and create these three widgets.
We also want to call this set_up_central_widget_ui function which if we look at this all this does is we
create a VerticalBoxLayout.
We add the QLineEdit which is called edit_bar first so that it's above our web_view.
So we also add in our web view. And then we actually set this layout that we've just created on our
central_widget.
And you see as part of this constructor we actually call a central_widget on the mainwindow and pass it
in our central_widget.
So the next thing that we want to do is actually load a Url.
Let's load Wikipedia's Url as example.
We'll go ahead and make a temporary QString and set it on the edit_bar class.
Now in order to call the load function on our web_view, we need to actually wrap the QString with the
Url constructor to make sure that our web_view can load it. The last thing we want to do is make sure that whenever
we change the Url in our LineEdit
the web_view gets changed.
Luckily QLineEdit has a signal that signifies when editing is finished, the editing finished signal.
We'll connect this to the
setUrl function in our Main_Window.
So now if we scroll down to the setUrl function
we'll go ahead and grab the text out of our QLineEdit and use a static function to let our
QUrl class
know that's coming from our users before finally loading it into the WebView.
so let's go ahead and run this and see how it goes.
Yep that looks like a web browser. So you might be asking yourself "Is that it"?
And the truth is
"Well yeah kind of".
The interesting thing about web browsers is browsing the internet.
If you pull open Chrome you can see that we've got a tab widget, couple of icons, but that's about it.
The user interface for the browser itself tends to be pretty limited.
I challenge you to make a similar tab browser using Qt.
It should take you less than a day to get a simple tab widget working.
Now if you're looking for some examples there's a few on Qt's website which you can find at this
Url.
The cookie browser, stylesheet, Html2PDF and Spellchecker are all interesting examples. With what
we've learned so far,
they might inspire you to help create your own unique web browser that scratches at personal itch.
So I encourage you to look at some of these examples and understand exactly what itch they were trying to
scratch because it might help you realize your own unique use case.
But with that we've hopefully successfully inspired you to create your own personal web browser, build
our own simple web browser and review the widget application programmer interface.
Now the one thing that we're missing is the ability to interact directly with the web from our desktop
app.
We'll cover this in our next video when we look at the Qt WebChannel.