This is video 4.4 of controlling multimedia which covers Qt 3D. In this video we're going to cover
that Qt 3-D FrameGraph, Entity-Component-System before finishing up with lighting and camera control.
So what is the Qt3D module? Qt does 3D graphics programming for a long time.
But up until Qt 5.7 it didn't have any high level means for controlling open GL. With a Qt
3D module
there is now a high level module that can be used to provide a more data driven approach for 3D rendering.
Now there's two important concepts in the Qt3D module that we need to understand in order to navigate
it.
The first is the framegraph and the second is the entity-component-system.
So let's go ahead and get started with the framegraph. The framegraph defines how the rendering will
take place. By default
Qt3D uses forward rendering. In forward rendering, everything gets rendered to the back buffer,
one object at a time, shading each object as it is rendered without any interaction.
The other common rendering scheme is deferred rendering. In deferred rendering
each object is rendered to an intermediate buffer before the shading is actually applied.
You can see an example of deferred rendering here, and the difference between deferred rendering and immediate
is in deferred rendering with these nice shadows because we can see our objects here are interacting
with the four objects here whereas intermediate we wouldn't get shadows at all.
We would just get the components themselves.
So the reason that is important to understand what the framegraph is is because if you need to switch
to a deferred rendering that is where you actually have to do it, it's in the framegraph definition.
Now we're just going to be using the default framegraph for this example.
So let's go ahead and get started and access that now.
And the first thing we're going to do is we're going to open up our main.cpp and we're going to go ahead
and create the window and grab a reference to the QForwardRenderer.
Awesome.
So now that we've got access to our default ForwardRenderer, let's go ahead and set the ClearColor which
for us will be the background color.
Perfect.
Note that we can always set our own renderer if we don't want to use the default one, and the method to do that is
just the setActiveFrameGraph method.
So you go ahead and add your own framegraph definition in here if you wanted to do a different one.
Cool so we've got the window created.
We've got forward_renderer, we set the ClearColor.
Let's go ahead and embed our window into a QWidget.
So the QWidget can control the geometry and the visibility for us.
And if we look at the very end of this code, we'll scroll down to the bottom, and you see we're actually calling
the show method right there when we call the container.show. Awesome. So now that we understand how
to access and set our framegraph, let's go ahead and talk about the second important aspect of Qt3D, the
entity-component-system. Entity-component-system
is an architectural pattern that addresses some of the shortfalls of inheritance overuse. Specifically
the entity-component-system fixes issues with deep and wide inheritance and helps tamp down on the tendency
for shared codes to rise up the object hierarchy.
It stresses composition over inheritance.
Now to go ahead and define each of these pieces of the entity-component-system, entities are general
purpose objects.
They are the tag for every object. Components represent the raw data for an aspect of the object and
show how it interacts with the world, and system perform global actions on every entity that possess
a component of the same aspect of that system.
Now I realize this is slightly confusing but it's important to remember that as you dig through the
Qt3D module, now I realize slightly confusing but it's important to remember this concept, because as you
dig through the Qt3D module it'll help you figure out what classes are supposed to do.
If you're looking at some of the documentation you can see that a class that you're looking at inherits from
QComponent. Then that should be a hint that you need to graph this class onto an entity,
the two provided aspects or systems because it's interesting Qt actually change it from the entity-component-system
into the component aspects, but the two provided aspects to the module are the Qt 3DRender and
the Qt 3DInput.
Now let's go ahead and look at this. This is an abstract example of how this would fit into the Qt sense.
We've got our QEntity.
We've got various QComponents, a mesh which provides us some volume and material which provides kind of how
it looks, a transform which should go ahead and move our object around, and a couple other aspects that we won't
get into, but you can see like you could have audio, you could have a rigid body, you could have collision volume and
AI tagged on here. And on the far right hand column here
these are all our aspects, or this kind of shows how the groups in each aspect so we have a QEntity.
In our case it's going to be a sphere where we're going to attach a mesh, so the mesh is going to describe
the actual sphere volume, attach material which defines how it's going to get rendered, and then
we will go ahead and put a transform on one of them to get them to rotate around each other.
So let's go ahead and take this and apply it.
So like I said we'll create a sphere entity and we're going to add three components to our sphere,
a mesh, a transform, and a material.
There are several sets of steps that we need to do between now and then.
So first thing we need to do is go ahead and create a RootEntity. And we're going to go ahead and set
this to be the root on our window.
Now that we've got the RootEntity set, let's go ahead and grab our camera out.
And we're going to go ahead and set a bunch of defaults on here which include the PerspectiveProjection
of the UpVectors and of the ViewCenter.
Perfect.
So let's go ahead and create a light.
You know we're going to tag our light at the same position that our camera is. And the important thing
whenever we're creating new entities, they are going to be parented back to the RootEntity somehow so we're creating this
new light_entity.
But it is the child of our RootEntity.
Now QPointLight our light_entity is just an entity, doesn't have any functionality, so if we want this
to actually act as a light, we need to go ahead and add that component. So we'll do that using the
QPointLight.
So go ahead and create that now.
And once we created that we'll go ahead and set some variables on here.
So the variables that I've got set is going to set the color to be white and we're going to set the
intensity to be 1.
And once we've set everything up for our component, which is the point_light_component, let's go ahead and add it
back to our entity. Again our entities are just descriptions, so the description is usually
just an integer. In order for us to get actual functionality
we need to actually create components and add them back onto our entities. That's very important step for
the Qt3D module. Awesome.
So let's go ahead and create a transform and position it with our camera position and then go ahead
and add that up into our light_entity as well.
So now our light_entity that we've created has a PointLine and a Transform that had been associated with
the addComponent. The last bit of setup stuff that we need to do before we add our spheres in is to
go ahead and set up our first person camera controller.
So go ahead and create that here.
And again we're going to make sure that this inherits from the RootEntity. And once we've got that
instantiated we're just going to go ahead and call the setCamera method and pass in our camera entity.
Perfect. So we got all these set up done.
Now let's go ahead and create some of our objects so we're going to create two spheres.
One's going to sit in the center and the other is going to rotate around the center sphere.
So let's create the first sphere that sits in the center.
So we'll create an entity.
Now again the entity isn't going to give us anything to look at.
We need to add some components to it.
So let's start with our mesh.
We're going to use a QSphereMesh class from the Qt3DExtras module to give it some volume. And
then we're going to set the number of rings, slices and radius on our QSphereMesh.
Perfect.
So that's fully instantiated. So let's go ahead and add that back up into our sphere_entity by using
the addComponent method.
Next let's give it a way to combine and diffuse and specialize using the QPhongMaterial class.
So go ahead and create our instance here.
And then we're going to go ahead and set the Diffuse.
So this is going to go ahead and set the color, and it's just a semi pleasing color that I've come up with.
That's the only two things we need to do to set this up.
So the only other thing that we can do is go ahead and add this back to our sphere_entity using the
addComponent. Awesome. Now that we've got one sphere, let's go ahead and create our second one which we're
going to have rotate around. So we're going to create a new QEntity. And let's go ahead and add the same material
and mesh that we just created for our last shpere
to this one. Awesome.
So right now our spheres are identical.
They're sitting at the origin and they have the same mesh and the same material.
So let's go ahead and add in a transform.
So we need to have this rotate over time.
We're going to combine a QTransform with a QPropertyAnimation, the transform
I've already included.
So it's this RotateTransform. And if you see the header file here, and the big thing about this is we needed
to expose a user_angle property.
So this directly gets subclass from the QTransform.
And the only thing that's really different is it exposes this user_angle property which we're going
to use to vary, with our QPropertyAnimation, so we can change the user_angle from 0 to 360 to
get it rotate in a full circle around our original object.
And if you look at this class, it's basically the implementation ,is this private slot right here which
is called rotate which we create a matrix. We rotate it based on the emule we translated, you
know, 20 units and then we set the matrix on our actual instance here to be the matrix that we just created
there.
So that's kind of how that works behind the scenes.
The biggest thing that we need to do is just go ahead and set up this QPropertyAnimation. So let's
go ahead and create this real quick.
There are two things that we need as part of this constructor.
The first will be the target and the second will be the property name.
So our target is going to be the rotate_transform and then the property name is going to be user_angle.
So let's go ahead and create this QPropertyAnimation now.
Perfect. So let's go ahead and set the duration to be 10 seconds and have it vary from 0 to 360 degrees.
And then we use the setLoopCount to -1 to go ahead and enable us to loop infinite times and
then go ahead and start it. And the last thing that we need to do
now we've got that set up is go ahead and add our transform, our rotate_transform up to our rotating_sphere
entity. Perfect. So let's go ahead and run this.
Looks like I've been in business to my name. So let's rename this widget_container to be a window_container.
And now let's run this.
Perfect. So you can see we've got our two spheres. They're the same color, same size since they both have
the same mesh and material.
And then we've got one that's actually rotating around. And if you click and hold you can actually track
it as it moves.
And that is our second sphere which has the rotation_animation applied to it.
So with that we've covered a quick example showing some simple lighting and camera controls.
We've covered the entity-component-system and covered why the Qt3D framegraph is important.
So join us in the next section where we'll cover communicating with Qt.