In this lecture, we're looking at how you
can import some an external javascript
code in your QML file and use it
directly. Let's go to QT creator and
play with us. Okay, here we are in QT
creator. We are going to create a new
project. We're going to call it
JavaScript import demo. Hit "Next", choose
your QT version, choose your desktop kit
here, and finish. What we're going to do
is to change the title here. We are going
to put a rectangle inside. Width is going
to be 300, height is going to be 100. It's
great to be blue. And it's going to be
centered in the parent. In start, we are
going to have a text element. This text
is going to say "Click Me". It's going to
be in the center as well. And the parent
of the text is this rectangle here, so
the text is going to be in the middle of
this rectangle here. We also want to put
a MouseArea that is going to fill this
rectangle. I should put this inside the
rectangle. It's going to fill the
rectangle. And when it's clicked, we want
to do something. For now, we can
console.log "Hello there". If you run the
application, there's nothing special.
You're going to see a rectangle in the
middle. It's going to have some text
inside and when you click, it's going to
say "hello there" in the console. The color
is really not good. So I think I should
change this to green. Let's see how it
looks. Or yellow green. We've used this
before.
Yellow-green. It looks like this. I think
it's going to be better. Okay, this is
better. If you click it says "hello there".
So what we want to do is to add a new
javascript file and call a method inside
there and let it say "hello there". We
don't want to say "hello there" directly.
We want this to come from a piece of
code that is stored in an external
javascript file. That's all go. We want to
come to the QML that qrc file
here, and add the new file. So we're going
to click add new Qt, JS file and call
it utilities, one, because it's going to
contain somethings that we want to use.
And you're going to see that under the
main QML file, we have a new javascript
file. Its extension is JS. We're going
to get rid of the content and put in our
function. It's going to be called "greeting".
And inside, it is going to say the
same thing we had. In the onClicked,
handler, okay, just like this we have a
function in the external javascript file.
We are going to save it. Come back to the
QML file, and now we need a way to import
our JavaScript code. The way you do that,
we're going to say import "utilities1.js".
And you're going to say as and you
specify a name that you're going to use
to call methods from this file. We call
this utilities 1, starting with capital.
And down here, we can say utilities one
greetin. You see that the method is even
recognized in the autocomplete feature
of QT creator. If you run the
application, click here. You see that it
says "hello there",
but the message here is coming from an
external javascript file. Let's prove it
by adding something here. Save this. Run
again. And you see that it says "hello
there" from external javascript file. And
it really is this easy to call methods
from an external javascript file. You
just added to your resources just like
you add QML files. You put your methods
in there.
When you import it in QML, take note of
this syntax here, you specify your file
in quartz. And you specify a name, you're
going to use to call your methods and
then you call it. And everything is going
to be fine. And this is really all I had
to say in this lecture in showing you
how you can call javascript from an
external file in your QML file. In the
next lecture, we're going to see ways you
can import your JavaScript indirectly.
I see you in the next lecture.