In this lecture, we are looking at ways
you can use JavaScript in your QML code.
We are specifically going to look at how
you can use JavaScript in property
bindings, custom functions and signal
handlers. Let's go to Qt creator and look
at that. Okay. here we are in Qt creator.
We are going to create a new project
as usual. It's going to be a Qt quick
application. We are going to call it
JavaScript usage demo. save it in a
location on our drive. Use this as the
default location for our project for now.
Choose your Qt version and choose your
camp. We are going to change the title to
JavaScript users demo. And to have
something to work on, we are going to put
a rectangle inside. This is what we
always do. Its width is going to depend
on the height, so it is going to be
height multiplied by 2. And its height
is going to be 100 for now. We are going to
give it a color of green, and it's going
to be in the center of its parent which
is this window element here. so we're
going to say anchors. Let's run and
see what we have. Okay. This is our
rectangle. It is in the middle of the
window object here. I don't know if you
noticed already but this is JavaScript
used in property binding. We are binding
the width of this rectangle to its
height. And this is one usage that we
just saw of using javascript in QML
files. You've already seen me do this a
lot and you are probably going to do it
yourself to make your properties depend
on each other. To play with this a little
more, I am going to put the MouseArea
inside. It's going to feel the parent. And
we are going to allow this mousearea to
drag this rectangle here. We are going to
say drag.target: container. You already
know how to do this, we've done this
before. The Axis is going to be the
XAxis. The minimum is going to be zero.
And the maximum is going to be parent
width minus the width of this containerRecId.
So we're going to do.
Because we are dragging this rectangle,
we don't really need to anchor it in the
parent. These properties would be
conflicting, so we're going to comment
this out. Run the application. It's going
to be in the top left of the window, and
we can drag it from left to right, can
increase the size of the window and you
see that it still works. So what we want
is, for the rectangle here, to change the
color when it goes past the X location
of 300. And the way we do that, we make
its color depend on the x coordinate of
it. So we're going to say if X is greater
than 300, the color is going to be red;
otherwise, it's going to be green. This is
a ternary operator. So if you don't know
about it you should check it in
JavaScript documentation or any other,
like programming language. This is really
common and you're going to see it a lot
in QML examples. Let's run the
application. And if we drag past
some location on X, the rectangle should
turn red. And you see that it turns red
right here. So we should do something to
show the x-coordinate as it changes and
we should capture one signal for, when X
is changed, we are going to say
onXChanged, console.log of X. Run again.
Okay. Let's drag to the right. You see
that we are passing 100, 200 and when we
get close to 300, notice that the color
is going to turn red. Ready, red. So our
code is working. But what I really want
you to focus on is this thing here. okay.
This is JavaScript used in here and that
this is also another case of using
javascript in property binding. okay. Now
that you send this, I'd like to show you
how you can use custom functions. So what
we can do, for example, we can move this
property binding here in a function. The
way you do that, you can define a
function down here, inside this rectangle.
And I call it getHeight. And it is going
to return what we just did here, this
expression. I realize this is a very
basic and trivial example, but I just
want you to see that you can do this. If
you want to do more complex things,
you're free to do so. So we can press getHeight
here. okay. This is a function we
defined inside this rectangle and we are
calling it here. Let's run the
application to see that things still
work the same way. You see that the width
is 2 times the height and our code still
works. Let's flood this function as a
custom function so that you have this as
a reference. And again you might have
noticed that in this place here,
onExchange,
we have used javascript in a signal
handler. Okay. So let's flat this champ.
and this really covers all I wanted to
show you in this lecture, which is where
you can use JavaScript in your QML files.
To recap, you can use javascript in
property binding just like we did here.
I think this turns to function so we
should say in Function. You can use
javascript in property bindings. You can
use javascript in functions, we defined a
custom function here, and we called it's
here, on the width property, to make it
depend on the height. That we define here.
We have also used it here in a signal
handler where we simply did a console.log
to show the current value of x. Okay.
Discovers all we set up to do in this
lecture, I hope you have a better idea of
where you can use javascript in QML
files. And the next lecture, we're going
to take a little bit more on functions
and see the scope of where you can use
them. I see you in the next lecture