In this lecture, we are going to continue
on top of the previous lecture and show
you how you can use JavaScript
indirectly in your QML files. Let's go to
Qt creator and do that. To show you how
you can use Js indirectly, we're going
to add a new javascript file. Click on
the qrc file here. Right, click. Add a new.
Choose Qt and choose JavaScript
file. We're going to call this "utilities2".
Hit "Next", and "Finish". And this utility
is too far, we want to define a new
function that is called "add" and it is
going to add two numbers. We're going to
return (a + b) and save the file. So
what we want to do is to import
utilities2 inside utilities1, so
that we can use it. The way you do that,
it basically is like what we did in
main.qml file but we put a dot in front
of our import. So we're going to say
import utilities2.js, 2 like this. If
we define another function here, for
example, call it "combineAges" and it's
going to take age1 and age2. And it's going
to return utilities2 add these two
ages. ok, age1 and age2. And we want to flag
here, that we are indirectly calling add method
from utilities2.
We can now call this function from
main.qml file. Let's go there, comment
this out, what we did in the previous
lecture. And we can say console.log our
ages combined yield, okay. we concatenate
that here say utilities1 combine
ages and say, for example, 33 and 17. If
we run this application and click on the
rectangle here, you see that we are
indirectly calling add from utilities
here. This is the code coming from here.
You see that this method is being called
and the result is what we expected. If we
go back into utilities2 and put the
console.log message to prove things and
say "method from utilities2 called". Let's
run again, click here and you see that...ok
our changes are not being picked up, you
don't see the message here. Let's go back
to the QML file, add a space, and run
again. Click here and you see that what
message is being shown. Sometimes, Qt
creator doesn't pick the changes from
the external files that you use. So if
you don't see the expected result, try
coming back to the QML file add a space
or something, and then run again. You're
probably going to see your changes. Ok.
this is how you can import the
javascript file inside another
javascript file. And when you import this,
you can only use these methods from this
file. this method is not available from
the main QML file. So for example, if we
come in the main QML file and
try to call "add" directly like this and
run the application, see that add should
be imported by important utilities2,
but we cannot use it directly in
main QML. It is only available in
the scope of utilities1 because we
use this import here. To prove our case,
we're going to run and it's going to
show an error, showing that the add
method is not recognized. Let's run the
application. Click here and you see TypeError:
property 'add' of object. It's not a
function. It is not being recognized. You
cannot use this function here. You have
to use it in this call of these
utilities1.Js file. So if you want to
import another JavaScript file and use
it as if it was defined in here, there is
another kind of import that you can
do and that's what we're going to see. So
we are going to add another utilities
file. Add a new Qt JavaScript file. It's
going to be utilities3. And inside
we are going to define a function, call
it "substract". It's going to take a
and b as parameters. And it's going to
return (a minus b). This is what we want. To
import this function in utilities1
and make it available here so that we
can use it directly like we used "greeting",
there is another kind of import that you can do.
What you can do is called Qt.import
and passing the name of the file that
you want to import, so you're going to
use utilities3.js. And from
now on, it is like you took this function
here and defined it right here. You got
you can call it here or you can call it
in the QML file. To prove our case, we're
going to
go back to the QML file, and say console.log,
the difference of fifty and thirty
three. We are going to call this method
from the scope of utilities1, so we
are going to use utilities1 here,
substract. It's not available in
autocomplete, but it's going to work. Okay,
fifteen and thirty three. Let's run the
application. Fingers crossed.
Okay. What is wrong here.
Oh, we say the Qt.import. We should have
said "Qt.include". Sorry for that. Here
you say "include". Run again. And if you
click here, it's going to say the
difference is seventeen. We are able to
call a method that is defined in
utilities3 from the scope of
utilities1. Ok. These are two different
ways you can indirectly import
JavaScript in your QML. One is to use
this import with a dot to make the code
available under a different name space
and to call that code, you're going to
you have to use this namespace here, and
we have used that here. Another way is to
import a JavaScript file and make it
available directly in the scope so that
you can call it in the scope of the file
where you define it. We have used that
here, in the main QML file where we call
the function in utilities3 as if it
was in utilities1. And you do that by
using this Qt.include thing here and
you pass in the file that you want to
import. And this closes our journey of
visiting ways you can use JavaScript in
QML file. In the next chapter, we're going
to start and look and
you can position different elements in
your QML, and we're going to shed
some light on row and column components
that we've been using without having
explained them in detail.
I'll see you in the next chapter.