In this lecture, we're going to look at
the flow qml component. According to the
documentation, the flow item positions
its child items like words on a page,
wrapping them to create rows or columns
of items. This is really all this
component does. We're going to create a
new project and play with this thing. File,
new project,
It's a QT Quick Application. We're going
to call it "flow demo", stir it in the
usual location, hit "next", choose your
latest version of Qt, and choose your
kit. And we have our project here. We want
to change the title here and make it say
"flow demo". And inside, we want to put a
flow component. Inside, ID is going to be
container. Width is going to be, let's
spell width correctly, and the height is
going to be the height of the parent. To
speed things up, I'm going to put in a
few rectangles that I have prepared
before. This one is a regular rectangle
with an ID, width and the height, a color and
inside we have a text element that is
centered in the rectangle. And it has a
black color, a font.pointSize of 30 and
the text inside, the text element, is
going to be 1. Let's hit control + A and
control + I to align things nicely. And we
want to add more rectangles like this. We
want to do a grid structure like we've
been doing in the last few lectures. We
put in the top center rectangle looks
like this.
The color is beige, the size is 100 100
width and height, and his text is saying 2.
Control + A, Control + I to align things.
We put in the top right rectangle, we put
in the left center rectangle, we put in
our Center rectangle, right center
rectangle, bottom left rectangle, bottom
Center rectangle, and finally bottom
right rectangle. We need to hit Control + A,
Control + I to align these things. And I
want to collapse this rectangle so that
we see what we have in here, very easily,
to basically have a flow component and
rectangles inside and it is nine
rectangles, and we can run to see what
our application looks like. mm-hmm.
You see that our rectangles are laid out
from left to right. And when the width is
not enough to contain them, they wrap to
the next line just like text flows in a
page. And I think that's a really good
comparison to help people understand how
the flow component works. Okay, if we try
and extend the width, you see that they
try and fill the available width. As the
width decreases, we start wrapping to the
next lines. And if we keep decreasing the
size of the width enough, we're going to
have a grid structure like we've had
before. And you see that it flows from
left to right and from top to bottom.
Okay, a property we can set inside the
flow component is the flow property,
which can be flow left to right. Okay,
which is what we have by default. We're
not going to see any difference, left to
right, but it can also be ToptoBottom.
Okay, something like this. We run and we
should see one, two, three from top to
bottom and it's going to wrap to the
columns as we run out of height to
contain our items. This is how you use
the flow property if you happen to need
this behavior. We're going to comment
this out. We can also do a layout
direction, like we did for the grid
layout component.
It can be Qt.RightToLeft. Let's run
and we should have one, two, three
starting from the right. Okay, you see
this is the behavior we have. It can also
be left to right. Run again, which is the
default behavior. And you might think
what could happen if we try and combine
flow and layout direction. So let's do
flow.TopToBottom and the layout
direction of right to left. What do we
have?
Let's run. mm-hmm, so it flows from top to
bottom, but it starts from the right
rather than starting to the left as we
had in the default behavior. And you can
try and match different values for flow
and layout direction and see the result
of what you have. Another property we
have seen in positioners and QT quick
layout is the spacing property which we
also have in the flow component. So we
can say "spacing", let's say 20, and if we
run, we're going to have some spacing
between the elements. Okay, what we just
saw is a section of what is really
available from the flow component. If you
need to have more information, you can
read on all these properties and see how
you can use them in your real
application. And as this is the last
lecture in positioners, I think this is a
good time to wrap up what we just saw. So
this is the documentation entry for Qt
Quick layouts. We just saw that they
allow you to world resizable pieces of
user interfaces. This is what you most
likely to use them for. All these layouts
are available to you. We used column
layout, grid layout and row layout, but
feel free to try stack layout. We also
saw positioners which are row, column and
grid. We use this and we saw how you can
blow the structures
like this. You use them when resizing is
not really your concern and they work
pretty well. And if you scroll down, you
can see more information about these
components. You see the column. This is
how your word done. You see the row. This
is how your world. You see
here, down here, we have a grid, we have a
flow component. These are different ways
to use positioners. They also say that
there are several other ways to position
items in a user interface. You can use
the basic technique of specifying their
x and y coordinates directly. We saw that.
You can also position elements relative
to other items with anchors and we also
looked at that. So when you need to
position elements in your user interface,
you have all these things in your
astronaut to really build what you want
and use the most flexible way. These
covers all I have to say in this chapter.
In the next chapter, we're going to keep
exploring more concepts on QT quick
development.
I'll see you in the next chapter.