Now I want to introduce a concept of
margins.
You can specify top margin to your
element, a left margin, right margin and a
bottom margin, and you use this syntax
here. So for example, we can come to our
grid here and look at the centerCenterRec,
which is here. It is positioned
to the bottom side of the top right
rectangle. So for example, if we wanted to
add the margin to the top of it, we could
say "anchors.topMargin" and say for
example, 10, why not? If we run it, mm-hmm,
you see that it moves down by 10 on the
top side here. Okay, one thing I want you
to see is that if you don't have an
anchor property on that anchor line, it is
not going to be possible to set the
margin. Margin here worked because we had
a top anchor set. Okay. Let's try to do a
right margin. What we want is to add the
margin to the right here, but notice that
we don't have it right anchor, so it's
not going to work. But let's try it so
that you can see that. So let's say
"anchors.rightMargin" and say 10 as usual.
Run the application. You see that our
margin is not being applied. And this is
a source of confusion for many students,
so I am going to note that here: To have...
okay, this is crucial. Let's comment this
out and do a margin that actually works.
So say anchors.topMargin and do it 10,
and say that: ...top margin set. Okay. I
want this to be clear to you. Let's run
again. Top margin is working. And I want
you to see that the green rectangle
moved to the bottom and any other
rectangle that was positioned in
relation to that moves too. So we applied
the margin to the green rectangle here,
but you see that all the bottom
rectangle, bottom left, bottom Center,
bottom right,
they also moved to the bottom. So I want
you to know this. Your margin properties
are going to affect all the other
elements that are anchored to the
element where you apply your margins. I
hope this makes sense. Another thing you
can do is use offsets and they allow the
position of your element to be
manipulated using center anchor lines.
Let's come back to our green rectangle
here and comment this out, and say
anchors.horizontalCenterOffset, say 10.
Let's run. You see that nothing
happens. But if we comment these out and
position our elements using the
horizontal and vertical center lines, the
way we do that, we say
anchors.horizontalCenter: parent.horizontalCenter,
and say anchors.verticalCenter.
It's going to be "parent.verticalCenter", and
run again. Okay, you see that this works.
This is the same as for anchor
properties, we try to set an anchor for
horizontal center offset, but we didn't
have an anchor to the horizontalCenter
and it didn't work. I really want you to
understand this because this is critical.
You can see that if you don't pay
attention, you can see your elements not
working as you wish, and don't know the
reason. This is the reason to set a
margin or enough set and have it work.
You have to have an anchor property on
that line where you are trying to set a
margin or an offset. Okay, so the offset
property also can work in vertical
direction. We can say "anchors.verticalCenterOffset",
and do it 10. And it's
going to work. Okay, it's going to go to
the bottom a little bit. This is what I
mean. Okay, it moves to the right and push
the blue rectangle here. It moved to the
bottom and pushed the bottom rectangles
because they all depend on it. And if you
look to the blue rectangle here, the
centre-right rectangle, its left side
must be anchored to the right side of
the green rectangle here. Let's prove
this. You can see, its left side is
anchored to the right side of the centerCenterRec,
The last point I want
to make is that you can only use these
anchors properties that we've been
talking about between siblings or
between parent and child. Let me show you
what I mean. I'm going to come to the
bottom here, to the bottom of the
containerRec. I am going to define
another rectangle. Width is going to be
200, height is going to be 200 also. Color
is going to be black. Its ID is going to
be "siblingRecId"
and it is going to be positioned to the
left side of the container, right. So
we're going to say "anchors.right", the
right side of it is going to be pinned
to the ContainerRec...left. If we run,
we're going to see our black rectangle
here. And as you move, you see that our
anchors are respected. The right side of
it is pinned to this container rectangle
here. So what I want to show you is that
you cannot anchor one rectangle inside
this containerRec to this black
rectangle because it's not a parent or a
sibling. Anchoring can only work between
siblings or between parent and child.
Okay, for example, if we try and take
these top left rectangle, the magento on
and try to anchor it to the bottom of
the black rectangle. It's not going to
work. Let's try this. We're going to say
"anchors.top" It goes to siblingRec
...bottom.
If we try to run this, hmm, you see that
cannot anchor to an item that isn't
parent or sibling. Anchoring can only be
done between siblings or between parent
and child.
Okay, discovers all we have to say in
this lecture. And the next one, we're
going to talk about position also like a
row column and grid. I'll see you in the
next lecture.