In this lecture, we are exploring anchors
in a little bit more detail. To play with
anchors, we are going to build something
like this. We are going to have a breed
of elements, and some elements are going
to be positioned in relation to the
position of other elements. And now we're
going to start the QT creator project.
I'll show you how you can do this using
anchors. File, new project, Qt quick
application. We call it "anchors demo" and
save it in location on our drive. I
actually want to use this as the default
project location. Hit "Next", choose the Qt
version - the latest one you have
installed, and choose our kit. We are
going to change this title to "anchors
demo". We are going to start by putting a
rectangle inside. This is the rectangle
that is going to contain other
rectangles, so we call it container..
containerRecID. Its width is going
to be 300. Height is going to be the same
as width. And this is property binding in
action here, the height depends on the
width. We wanted to have a border that is
visible in black. And it should be
centered in the parent. If you come here
in the documentation and search for a
positioning with anchors, you're going to
see the entry here, click on it, and they
say Qt Quick provides a way to layout
items using the concept of anchors. Each
item can be thought of as having a set
of seven invisible "anchor lines", and you
can see them here. You can position items
following this lines. For example, these
two rectangles from left to right are
aligned using this piece of code here.
You define the first rectangle like this
and then you define rectangle 2, and then
you define the left side of rectangle 2
to be anchored to the right side of
rectangle 1. This is how you say what is
happening here. Down here, we have another
slightly more interesting example.
Rectangle 1 and rectangle 2 are
positioned using this piece of code here.
The left side of rectangle 2 is aligned
to the right side of rectangle 1, and the
top side of rectangle 2 is aligned to
the bottom of rectangle 1. And this is
how you say this. We are actually going
to go back to Qt creator and position
our rectangles using this technique.
Define your first rectangle. Remember, we
want to position our nine rectangles in
a grid. This one is going to be topLeftRecId.
It's width is going to be 100.
Its height is going to be the same at
the width. It's going to have a color of
magenta. We are going to copy this, paste
it down here. This is going to be the topCenter.
It's going to be yellow-green.
Let's spell this correct. And we want to
position it to the right of the top left
rectangle, so we are going to take its
left side and anchor it to the right
side of the top left rectangle. We are
going to say "anchors.left" and set this
to be get the right side of the top left
rectangle. Let's run and see what we have
so far. mm-hmm.
we have two rectangles. The left side of
the second rectangle is aligned to the
right side of the first one. I hope this
makes sense. We are going to keep moving
forward. We are going to copy this and
define our third rectangle the same way.
This going to be topRight. It's going to be dodgerblue.
Why not? And it's going to be to the
right of the top center rectangle, so
we're going to replace this with
top center rectangle. Run. We're going to have
the third rectangle, okay, position to the
right of the second one. We are going to
copy this, paste it here. We are going to
call this rectangle "centerLeft",
something like this. And it needs to be
to the bottom of the top left rectangle.
so we are going to say "anchors". We are
going to anchor a top side to the
bottom side of the top left rectangle. So
anchors.top: top...bottom, okay. It's going
to be to the bottom of the top left
rectangle. What is going to be the color?
Why not
red? Let's run. mm-hmm. The red rectangle
is here. It is to the bottom of this one.
So when you add your element and not
give it an even position, it's going to
be positioned in the top left corner of
its parent rectangle. Let's show you what
I mean. I'm going to add this rectangle
here and not give it an anchor property.
It is going to be to the top of the top
left rectangle, basically at zero zero
position. So you need to move it for it
to be visible, and not wrap around the
other rectangle. And this is what we did
here with this property. And if we run
again, things are going to be normal. I
want you to know this. We need to add a
few other rectangles to complete our
grid. We're going to copy this, paste it
again here. Let's do "centerCenter.." Let's
make it green.
We can choose to align it in position to
the top center rectangle where we put it
to the bottom of it or to the right of
this rectangle that we just defined here.
It's going to work the quality the same,
effectively putting it in the middle of
the grid. Okay. So let's try the first one.
we're going to align its left side, okay.
It's going to be to the right of this
rectangle here. But we also need to move
it to the bottom. So to move it to the
bottom, we have to align it in relation
to any rectangle here on the top. For
example, let's do that in relation to
this top right rectangle here, so we're
going to say anchors...top...topRight
rectangle...bottom. Let's run the
application ,and this is what we want. The
green rectangle is in the middle. Let's
copy this, do "centerRight", it's going to
be blue. The left side of it is going to
be to the right of the green rectangle,
we can do that. Okay.
Effectively putting it here on x
coordinate, and we need to position it
vertically too, so we can do the same
thing we did here. You can do that, so
we're going to say anchor (stop), equals top
right rectangle...bottom. Let's copy this.
Put this here. Okay. We have our blue
rectangle. And obviously, there are
different ways you can do this. You can
just look at the position of your anchor
lines and decide how you want to
position your elements in the grid. We
are going to do the bottom line of our
grid very quick. I am going to paste in
the rectangle here and say "bottomLeftRecId".
Okay, positioning is very easy as
usual. We're going to put it to the bottom
of the centerCenterRecId. Let's do
that, so we are going to say anchor.right
center to the left. Okay. This is
what you want. Okay, its right side is
going to be anchored to the left side of
the green rectangle. Putting it on this
line here, horizontally and  anchor.top
is going to be "center...RecId.bottom".
We are going to give it a color of royal.
And if you hover over this color, you're
going to see what it looks like. Let's
run the application. This is our
rectangle. The bottom line of this grid
is going to be all positioned in
relation to the centerCenterRecId.
Let's see how we can do that,
so "bottomCenter", we are going to put it
to the bottom of the centerRecId,
this is not changing but the left side
of it is going to be anchored to the
left side of centerCenterRec, so we are
going to say "anchors.left..centerCenterRecId,left".
What color do we put in
here? why not do yellow?
Let's run. mm-hmm. Yellow rectangle. We
have one left.
Copy this, paste here, say "bottomRightRecId".
Let's make this pink. The bottom
side of it is going to be to the bottom
of the centerRec, but the left side
of that is going to be aligned to the
right side of the center rectangle. I
don't know if this makes sense. Let's run
to see that our grid is complete. Okay.
Now hopefully, you know how to use
anchors to position your elements
wherever you want to put it in this
structure. Okay. You basically have these
lines to anchor against and if you need
more examples of how you can do this
things, you can come on these examples and
try to run them.