In this lecture, we're going to look at
positioners like row/column and grid. We
are going to try to use them and bloat
the structure that we had in the last
lecture using anchors. Let's go to QT
creator and do this. Here we are in QT
creator and we are going to create a new
project.
It's a QT quick application as usual.
It's going to be called "positioners demo",
stored in the usual location, hit "Next",
choose the QT version you have installed,
we choose our kit and finish. Let's
change the title here and call it
"positioners demo" and we need to put a
rectangle inside because we need to do
the same structure as we did before.
ID is going to be containerRecId.
Width is going to be 300, I think that's
what it was.
Height is going to be the same as with.
Border, it's going to be black. And it's
going to be centered in the parent. And
by the way I don't think I mentioned
this in the last lecture. anchors.centerIn: parent
is equivalent to setting the
horizontal Center and the vertical
Center, so it basically is the same as
saying. anchors.horizontalCenter
parent.horizontalCenter and
anchors.verticalCenter: parent.verticalCenter. Okay, let's give
it a color so that you see this working.
I'm going to take it out after so I'm
going to give it a color red. Let's run
the application. And if all works, it
should be in the center of this window
here. Okay, it's in the center. And if you
resize it's going to work the same.
Okay, to show you that it is equivalent,
I'm going to comment this out and
uncomment "anchors.CenterIn: parent". And
it's going to be the same. I wanted to
make this point here. I'm sorry I didn't
mention that in the anchors lecture. Okay,
so what we want to do is to put
a grid component inside here. We want to
specify the number of columns that we're
going to have inside. I want to have
three. It is four columns by default, and
if you want to know more about the grid
component, you can come to the help here
and type "grid". It is this easy. And they're
going to show you all you need to know
about it.
so what we want to do is to actually
copy the rectangles that we did in the
last lecture. I am going to open that
project. You can go where you save it.
Let's go there. Here, okay. You can go
where you saved it, open the file with
whatever editor you see fat, and copy the
rectangles inside the containerRectID
here. so I have the project opened in Qt
creator so no need to do it like that,
but it is the same. I'm going to copy
from here to here okay.
Double check to make sure that it is the
rectangles that you want. I'm going to
copy them, come back to our project and
place them inside. Of course, I'm going to
have to do some modifications. Because we
are using the grid positioning system, we
don't need to do anchors ourselves, so
I'm going to take them out. One is gone
two is gone, three is gone. Let's take all
this garbage out. Four is gone. This
also should go.
This also should go.
Go, okay, I'm just taking these
anchors out, so we have six rectangles
inside: top left, top center, top right,
center left, center Center, center right,
bottom left, bottom center, and bottom
right. They are positioned in a green
component and the number of columns is
three. Why is it four? I set it to three,
okay. If you run the application, let's
see what we get.
Seems like I've forgot some anchor here.
Okay, and this is a good time to learn
that you cannot specify our anchors for
items inside the grid. Grid do not work if
you do that. Okay, we forgot this one.
Let's double check again. And while I am
here, I should take out this red color
because I used it to show you this
stands here. Now you know it, there's no
need. Let's run, mm-hmm, we have our
rectangles but the center-left rectangle
is missing. What is happening here? It
doesn't have a color, so we took it out.
Let's make it beige.
I love beige. Run again, mm-hmm,
these are our elements positioned in
a grid. I hope you can appreciate how
simple the code became for this thing.
Okay, you basically put your rectangles
inside and the grid positioner takes
care of positioning them for you in a
grid. All you have to do is specify the
number of columns here you want. Let's
see what happens if you specify two
columns. Run again.
Okay, two columns. And you see that the
system forces, thanks to be layout, in two
columns. Let's turn this back to three.
Run again. And boom, this is our thing
here. Another thing I want you to see is
that you can comment out the columns
here and change the element to a row and
have things displayed from left to right.
This is that. Okay, nine rectangles from
left to right. You can also do the same
in a vertical fashion. So you can do
"column" to help them lay down from top to
bottom. It is this easy, top to bottom. I
don't think we have enough space to show
all of this but they are here 1 2 3 4 5
6 7. Two are not visible because we don't
have enough vertical space. We centered
this. Let's take out this CenterIn parent
thing so that it is aligned to the
top of the parent. And you see our things
here. Let's turn this back to the grid and
specify our columns here. Another thing I
want you to see is that you can specify
the spacing between your elements. So you
can say spacing 10. Run again and there
is going to be a distance of 10 between
your elements. You can also do row
spacing to have your rows separated by a
distance that you specify here.
Rowspacing, say 10.
Let's do that. Okay, they are separated.
you can do "columnspacing". Let's do 10 as
well. The space is going to be between
the columns. Okay. And by now, I hope you
see that specifying the spacing here is
like
specifying both the row and column
spacing. It's going to be the same thing.
Let's run, same thing. Let's comment this out.
Okay, so far we have only rectangles with
colors, but I want to do something more
interesting for now. I'm going to put an
image inside this top left rectangle, so
I'm going to say "Image". I'm going to give
it a width of 15, a height of 15. And I
need to specify the source image.
Okay, I'm going to select the resources
folder here. Right, click, add new, Qt
resource file. I'm going to call it
"resources". Hit "next". we have worked with
the resources before, so this is not new
to you. I want to add a prefix because I
don't want to have any specific
preference, so I'm going to take this out
and hit "enter". I am going to go where my
main.qml file is created, showing
Explorer right here, and I'm going to
fall into the folder for our project
here. I want to add an image folder. Let's
call it "images", and I am going to paste
in an image that I have prepared on my
drive. Let's come back to our project, add
files to the resources file that we just
created, go in images, choose this LearnQt
image and save. So I can come back
to our qml file and say "images/learnQt.png"
I need to anchor
this image into its parent which is top
left rec, so I'm going to say
anchors.CenterIn: parent. Run again, mm-hmm,
and you see that our image is showing up
in the top left
rectangle here. Another thing I want you to
see is that you can specify the
alignment for the cells in your grid. Let
me show you what I mean. If I take the
size of this top left rectangle and turn
it to 60 and run again, it's not going to
fill the available width, so it's going
to be aligned to the top left by default.
You can control this alignment by using
the properties on your grid, and one of
them is horizontalItemAlignment and
you can specify different properties. You
can say Grid.AlignBottom horizontal
center left, right, top or verticalCenter.
For now, we want to do to the right. Let's
run this and you see that it is aligned
to the right. You can try passing in
other properties to see the effect of
your things here. You can also do
verticalItemAlignment. Let's do
Grid.AlignVerticalCenter and you can see
that it is in the center vertically.
Before we wrap up this lecture, I want
you to know that you can also do mirroring
on your grid. The way you do that,
you come to your grid here and say
"LayoutMirroring.enabled", set this to
true and we want the children to inherit
this property to have them mirrored
correctly, so we're going to say
"LayoutMirroring.ChildrenInherit" and set this
to true. And you can find all these
properties by looking in the
documentation. We have this selected
within F1. You're going to see all about
this attached property. Let's run the
application and you can see that the
order of things is reversed. This
to the left here and it's to the right
now. Okay, discovers all I had to say in
this lecture, I hope you know how you can
work with row, column and grid. In the
next lecture, we're going to look at a
much more powerful positioning technique
that is layout. I'll see you in the next
lecture.