In this lecture, we are going to talk
about the JavaScript environment in QML.
javascript is the first class citizen in
ER qml cool. It has a lot of similarities
with the JavaScript environment you see
and things like browsers and nodejs, but
it also has some fans that are special
to the qml environment. It does implement
ECMA-Script ES55 which is a standard of
JavaScript that is implemented in most
modern browsers like Firefox, Chrome,
Safari and this gives you access to
familiar JavaScript objects like math
and many others as we are about to see.
We also have QML global object which
contains the Qt global object we have
already seen. And we also have tons and
tons of JavaScript objects and functions
that we can use to make our job easier
when adding some interactivity to our
QML code. And the main job of JavaScript
is ready to add a layer of interactivity
to QML, just like it does the same thing
for HTML and CSS environments. Although
the JavaScript environment in QML is
very similar to what we see in
environments like the browser, there are
many differences you should be aware of.
For example, the JavaScript engine in QML
doesn't implement the DOM API. Its
implementation of ES5 gives us access
to objects like math, array and many
others as we going to see. And one thing
you should really be aware of is that
javascript is not really documented in
the Qt documentation. So if you try to
search for things like date in the Qt
documentation, you're going to have very
limited information and you're going to
have to go to JavaScript focus
documentation online, and I'm going to
show you one right now. That is very
useful. Ok. Here we are. This is the
developer mozilla.org javascript
reference. It is very good. So if you are
looking for the date documentation, for
example, you can come here to built-in
objects, and you get a list of objects
that you can really look at.
Inside, we have boolean, date and many
others. And you're going to have to come
here to search for whatever it is you
are looking for. If we click on date here,
we're going to have different ways we
can use this so they give us an example,
we can run, you can run this example by
clicking the Run button.
It basically is very good to test your
JavaScript. To show you what I mean by a
limited documentation, if we go to the
documentation here and search for date,
so this is a date QML type. They give you
a few things and how you can use it in
QML call. But for more information, you're
going to have to check the date object
in the JavaScript documentation that we
just found here. The QML global object is
the default object you fall and when you
start to write your QML code. Remember
when we are in our QML file, we can type
things like console, print. That's the
global object we are in QML file. It
contains things like the Qt global
object that we have seen, we have tried
it out, we have used Qt.quit method and
many others. It also contains things like
print that we can use to output debug
messages. It contains the console object
we have also been using that quite a lot
when we typed console out to output some
messages. It contains translation related
methods, but we're not going to explore
this in this course, but it is very
important when you want your application
to run in multiple languages. The
QML global objects also contains an
object we call XMLHttpRequest which
we're going to use later in the course
to fetch some HTTP data from the
internet. The QML global object is your
home environment when writing some QML
code. We also have a list of JavaScript
functions and objects that we can use. I
think this is explained better if you
see for yourself, so we are going to go
to this length. This is basically a list
of objects and functions that are
available to you in the
javascript engine of QML. There is the
global object that contains things like
NaN, infinity, undefined. There are
functions and properties that you can
use. There are constructor properties
that you can use. You can use this, for
example, to create a date object, a
boolean object, a number object. You can
use this if you happen to need them in
your QML code. There is the object object,
which is the parent of all the objects
in your JavaScript code. These are the
functions you can use on that object.
This is an exhaustive list of things you
can do. So if you are working with arrays,
these are the functions that are
available to you. One thing we have used
before is this for each method and we
used it to look through an array and it
was very convenient, so if you are
interested in this, you can actually come
to the documentation of JavaScript, go
back, go to built-in objects, look at
array. And if you go down here, you're
going to find array prototype for each.
If you click on this, they're going to give
you an example of how you can use this.
So the documentation is really good. Down
here they show you things you can pass
in and I think they have some cool
examples if you keep scrolling. So please
check this out if you happen to be rusty
on your JavaScript. I know I drove
through at you a lot of information, but
what you really need to know is that the
QML JavaScript engine implements ECMA-Script
standard 5, which is the standard
that is implemented in most browsers.
It contains the QML object which is your
home environment in your QML file and it
gives you a list of javascript objects
and functions that you can use to really
make your job easier. okay. I don't like
to throw information at you
without giving you references. So we're
going to go to the online documentation,
I'll show you where you can read more
stuff about this. Here you can learn more
about the JavaScript environment in QML.
They say that it implements standard 5
of the ECMA script standard. You see the
QML global object, the list of
functions that are available to you. You
can read on this. If you need to read
more about the QML global object, you can
see this here. They tell you that it
contains the Qt global object we just
looked at in a previous venture. You see
the print function, the console object,
the XMLHttpRequest object. And you can
look at this if you need more
information about this. Okay. Now that you
know a little bit more about the
JavaScript environment that is available
to you in QML, where can you type
JavaScript code in you QML file? Well, you
can do that in property bindings, signal
handlers, standalone JavaScript functions
and imported JavaScript code. In property
bindings, we have already actually used
it when you did something like height
equals width, multiplied by an even
number. This is some JavaScript you are
writing in your rectangle object, so you
can use it like this. You can also use
javascript in signal handlers. In your
MouseArea, in the on click method, this
is JavaScript you are write in here.
There are two other use cases of
JavaScript we haven't talked about yet,
but this is the topic of this chapter
and we are going to look at how you
can use JavaScript in standalone
functions and imported JavaScript code.
For now, I hope this gives you a good
introduction to what is available to you
in terms of JavaScript features in your
QML code. And in the next few lectures, we
are going to explore more earnest and
actually open Qt creator and start
playing with us. Starting in the next
lecture, I'll see you there