In this lecture, we are looking at
different ways that Qt Quick gives you to
lay out your components in the user
interface. We have actually looked at
some of these ways. One is to use direct
positioning where you specify the x
coordinate and the y coordinate for your
element. And this is called direct
positioning we have seen this. You can
also position your elements, depending on
other elements position. For example, here
you see rectangle 2 is positioned
depending on the location of rectangle 1.
The top side of rectangle 2 is aligned
with the bottom side of rectangle 1. And
the left side of rectangle 2 is aligned
with the right side of rectangle 1. And
you use anchors to do this. We have been
using anchors a lot so far, but this time
we are going to try to explain them a
little bit more. QML also makes row,
column and grid components available to
you and you can use them to position
your elements from left to right, top to
bottom or in a grid like structure like
this. The layout components respectively
row layout, to column layout and grid
layout, provide the same features as row,
column and grid, but they provide more
convenience features like resizing your
windows when the parent window changes
its size. We're going to see how this
works. In the next few lectures, we are
going to talk about these subjects in a
little bit more detail. Starting in the
next one. I'll see you in the next
lecture.