In this lecture, we are looking at
functions and scope in JavaScript used
in QML. Here we are in QT creator. We're
going to do the usual and create our
project. We're going to call it functions
and scope demo. Hit "Next", choose our
desktop kit and finish. Let's change this
to functions. We are going to do the
usual, create a rectangle inside, give it
an ID. Give it a width of 300, give it a
height of 100, put it in the center and
give it a color of blue this time. On the
root level, I want to define a function
that computes the minimum of two numbers.
And it's going to return. There is a math
object that is available to you globally
in JavaScript and we can use it to
compute the minimum of two numbers and
we are just going to pass in a and b
here. It's going to return the minimum.
Okay. So what we can do now is use this
function to compute, for example, the
width of this rectangle. We can say
minimum, for example, 300 and 400. This is
just a silly example of showing you how
you can use a function. It's really not
that useful here, but the point is to
show you how you can use functions in QML.
Run the application. Nothing
is going to change. It's going to be 300,
but if, for example, you pass in 500 here
let's do a component on completed signal
handler and console.log the width of
this rectangle so that we can improve
this.
we use its ID. Let's run the application.
It should show 400 and it's 400 here. So
our function here is working correctly.
one thing I want you to know is that the
function that you define on the root
level is callable anywhere in that
element. Okay, for example, we can call
this function here in rectangle, we can
call this function here in component
onCompleted. To prove that to you, we're
going to take out this here and say
min. The same thing we did there, 500, 400.
Run the application. It works the same.
Okay, you can call this function anywhere.
But if we put a MouseArea, for example,
here, I'm going to show you something.
That is not very obvious. Let's make it
fill the parent and onClicked,
we're going to do something that's usual.
We want to give this an ID and define a
function down here. So going to say
function and it's going to say something
to the console, for example, "hello world" or
"hello there". This is better. When we click
here, we're going to say sayMessage. Okay,
we define a function in this MouseArea
and then we call it when we click on the
MouseArea. If we run the application, it
is going to work as usual. Click here
"hello there". This is a message that is
coming from this function here. But one
thing I want to show you is that you
cannot call this same message function
anywhere outside without using the ID of
this MouseArea. So for example, in the
component.onCompleted method, we cannot
say sayMessage.
Okay, you see that it's not even
recognized. But even if we run, because
sometimes QT creator doesn't recognize
if invalid stuff, mm-hmm
sayMessage is not defined. To be able to
call this method that is nested in and
never sibling element, you have to use
the ID. So if we use the ID of this MouseArea,
let's copy and put it here and I
put a dot, you're going to see that it is
recognized
I think QT creator is going to
recognize that. Okay, you see that it
recognizes it and we have autocomplete
available. Okay. If we run when the
component is loaded, we're going to see
the message here "hello there" even if we
didn't click on this blue rectangle. It
is coming from this place when the
component is loaded successfully.
I hope this drives home the point that
to call a method it either has to be
defined in that element, for example, here
in the MouseArea, we define this method
and we called it. Okay. And any other
child items of MouseArea here are going
to see this function. But you cannot call
this method outside this MouseArea. To
be able to call a method, it has to be
defined in the root level of the parent
item or inside that particular element
where you are calling the method.
Otherwise, you're not going to be able to
call it and you're going to have to use
IDs to target the element where the
method is defined. This is what we mean
when we say function and scope. It really
means where we can use this function
without having an error.
Okay. This covers all we set out to do in
this lecture. In the next one, we're going
to see how we can import some external
javascript code and use it in our QML
file here. I'll see you in the next
lecture.