In this lecture, we're going to talk
about QT quick layouts. These layouts
work like row, column and grid - the
0:00:08.220,0:00:13.290
components we've seen before, but they
add the capability to resize your user
interface when the parent window is
resized. We're going to go to QT creator
and play with this. Here we are in QT
creator. We're going to create a new
project.
It's a QT quick application, we're going
to call it "layouts demo", hit "Next", choose
the latest version of QT have installed
here and choose your kit. We are going to
change the title here. It's going to say
"layouts demo". To use QT quick layouts, you
have to import them first, okay, they are
not part of QT quick. We're going to say
import QTQuick.Layouts, and we're going
to select 1.3 here. And if we look
in the documentation and search for,
we're going to find an entry that says
QT quick layouts...Let's select this one,
and they say that it is a set of qml
types that you used to arrange items in
a user interface. And unlike regular
positioners that we have seen row,
column and grid, QT quick layouts can
also resize their items.
This makes them well-suited for
resizable user interfaces. This is really
one of their strengths. They resize the
user interface when the parent window
resizes, so there are different layouts
that you can use in here. We're going to
look at rowlayout, columnlayout and
gridlayout. You can click on this list
to learn more on this UI components.
We're going to start with a GridLayout.
We're going to give it an ID. We are
going to make it fill the parent. We
wanted to have three columns, so we're
going to choose the columns property and
specify that we want three of them. And
we are going to put some contents inside.
We are going to put in a few rectangles.
This is going to be the top left
rectangle. Its width is going to be 70.
Its height is going to be equal to its
width. It's going to have a color of
green. We are going to copy this a few
times. Let's do the first row first. This
is topCenter, this is topRight. The
colors will change, so we're going to put
the second row, then we're going to call
this centerLeft. I am taking you through
the process of typing this because I
don't want you to be lost. Sometimes,
students don't see where things are
coming from. So if this is lengthy for
you, please be patient. Here we're going
to say Center and this is going to say
centerRight.
Okay, we are trying to build the great
structure we have closed before with
nine rectangles inside. This should bring
us to the third row and we put our three
rectangles here. We say bottomLeft,
bottomCenter and bottomRight. We should change the
colors, so green, red, blue, beige, pink, for
example, say yellow, say magenta, say
yellow-green, and say dodger. Okay, this
should do it. And the other thing I want
to do is to change the width and height
for the other rectangles except the
first one. You're going to see why. Okay, we
change this to 100. Copy this and paste
in all the other places: 100, 100, okay.
By now, we have a grid layout inside our
window here, and inside we have nine
rectangles.
The first one is 70, 70 in width and
height. And all the others are 100 in
width and height, and they have different
colors as you see here. Before we run, we
want to adjust the width and height of
this window to adjust through the
contents of this grid layout, so we're
going to say its width equals
mGridLayoutId.implicitWidth and its height
should be... And you should notice that we
also set this to have three columns. Now
we should run our thing and see how it looks.
Mm-hmm, you see that we have nine
rectangles inside. When we resize the
window, the layout is trying to resize
with this window here. This is a behavior
you don't have with row and column
components. You can also turn this into a
row or column layout. We're going to try
that actually. Let's say RowLayout and
you automatically see that the row
doesn't have these columns property, so
we should comment it out if we want to
run our code. It's going to be on one row
from left to right. Okay, you've seen this.
We can also do ColumnLayout, mm-hmm, it
is in one column. Let's turn this to a
grid component so that you can see the
difference. Let's uncomment the column
here and run, and hopefully you see the
difference between a grid component and
a grid layout component. The grid layout
allows you to resize the contents of the
cells when the parent window resizes,
okay. This is the behavior we have here.
Another thing I want you to see is that
you can set how the contents of the cell
behave when the current window resizes.
Okay, for example, we can instruct this
green rectangle to fill the available
width and height. And the way you do that,
you come into this rectangle because it
is an element of this grid layout now,
and you use an attached property of
layout, so you say "Layout.fillWidth", set
this to "true", say "Layout.fillHeight", set
this "true". Run again, mm-hmm, you see
that the grid is now filling the
available width and height even if it
was 70 in width and height while others
will 100 in width and high. And notice what
happens when we resize our window. Okay,
you see that the green rectangle is
doing its best to fill the available
width and height. Okay, so these are
properties you want in all of your
rectangles if you want to have a uniform
look and grid layout. So we're going to
paste them in every place in here. Okay,
let's run, and we shouldn't see a
difference in what we see when we run
the application, but if you resize, all
the windows now are resizing to the some
width and height because they all are
instructed to fill the available width and
high. Another thing you can do is specify
the maximum width or height that a cell
can have. And we're going to try this on
the yellow rectangle here, so we can say
Layout.maximumWidth. Let's say that we
own the yellow it to be 200 in width
and Layout.maximumHeight and I want to
be only 150 high. Let's run again and
watch the yellow rectangle, which is here.
If we resize in this direction, you see
that it goes at some distance
and stops growing, and you see that
the blue rectangle here is now trying to
occupied space. If you try to expand in
height, it's going to get to 150, and it's
not going to grow anymore. And you see
that there is space around it because it
can't go beyond 150 in height. Another
thing you might specify is the alignment
of your components in the grid layout.
Let me show you what I mean. I am going
to turn off the filling of the available
width and height, and run again. You see
the green rectangle is 70 in width and
height and it is aligned to the left,
okay. If you want it to be to the right
here, the way you could do that, you could
say Layout.alignment and say Qt.AlignRight,
okay. If you run, you can specify
the top bottom left horizontal Center or
vertical Center. If you want to see all
the possible options, you can actually
come here, click on Qt and say Align
and you're going to see different
options you can use. You can use AlignBottom,
AlignCenter, AlignHorizontalCenter,
AlignLeft, AlignRight, AlignTop,
AlignVerticalCenter. You can use all
this things if you are in the mood for
that. For example, if we say AlignCenter,
it is going to be in the center and here it
is in the center. Another thing you can
specify is the row span or column span
for a contained item in the grid layout.
For example, if we took out this blue
rectangle here, we could instruct the red
rectangle here to fill these two cells.
And the way we do that, we go back to
our code, find the blue rectangle, comment
it down. You don't want to delete it
because you might want to use it later.
And we come to the red rectangle and say
layout
Layout.columnSpan and say 2, okay. We want
this red rectangle to go across two
columns, this column and this column.
Let's run the application, mm-hmm, two
columns. You can do the same thing, for
example, we can take out this pink
rectangle and instruct the beige
rectangle here to span two rows. We're
going to do that. Center left red, we want
to say Layout.rowSpan and say 2, and
take out the bottom left rectangle which
is magenta. It's not that. I'm sorry for
that.
If we run, the beige rectangle should be
going down and fill in the available
space. Now you know how to use row span
and column span to suit your needs.
The other property we want to look at is
layout direction. What is the layout
direction?
It holds the layout direction of the
grid layout. It controls whether items
are laid out from left to right or right
to left. If we were starting from right
to left, the green rectangle should be up
to the right here. So let's try this.
We're going to go back to our code and
on top here, add layoutDirection and say
Qt.RightToLeft. Let's run the
application. The green rectangle should
be to the right now because the layout
direction is reversed. Things are
starting from the right, and you see that
our beige rectangle here also goes to
the right. I hope this makes sense.
Okay, this covers all I had to say in
this lecture, I hope you have a better
idea of how you can use QT quick layouts
to your advantage. And they really
provide resizing capabilities for your
contained
items. In the next lecture, we're going to
look at the last component of this
chapter and that one is flow. I see you
there.