All right. So we're going to talk about
qml and C++ and how they can work
together. As I mentioned, these notes are
actually reduction of about a three-day
course and how to write applications in
qml and Qt. So a lot of things have been
compressed condensed and something's
dropped. I was looking through the notes
and one thing I actually got dropped is
a nice quick and dirty way of exporting
C++ instanced objects into the qml
environments. So if everyone doesn't mind
I'm actually gonna switch gears for a
second, then jump into the notes for my
presentation tomorrow and we're gonna go
over the little short section about how
if you make an object in C++, like you
make a new something pointer, you can
export that something pointer into qml.
These notes are really geared toward
creating an item that you know you make
a pie chart or a bar chart item in qml.
And the back end of that item it
actually does is drawing in C++ which is
also very useful. So let's go ahead and
if people want to give me a business
card
after the notes after the class I can
send you these notes as well. I know, I
think you already have, these notes have
been going over on those USB sticks. If
you don't have the notes likewise I can
send them to you as well.
They're actually an open source Nokia
thing. So you can take objects that you
instantiate in C++ and export them into
the qml execution environments where
they will just appear has well magic
variables. So you can make an abstract
item model pointer and export it, you can
make a QObject pointer and just
export it, and the other way is you can
actually export types that are in stance
to your ball in qml. So
there's a slight difference there so
things that you can make in C++. Say you
make them in main you and then you can
export them into qml is you can make any
QObject pointer. You can create it in
C++ and export it into the qml
environment. Properties simply become
variables. Slots are functions now.
Sometimes when you're designing your C++
so it can be used in C++ and QML. There
are some things like functions with
return types that you generally don't
want to be slots, but you want them to be
INVOKABLE from qml. So you can use the
Q_INVOKABLE macro in front of the
signature rather than putting it in a
slots section. You can export a QList
of QObject, and this can be used as a
quick and dirty data model. However you
can insert or append on to the list. It's
just a quick and dirty list of items and
the most powerful thing that you can
make and export from c++ is an abstract
item model pointer. You can create that
create all your data in C++, create the
interface to your data in c++ and simply
export it into qml and use it there. You
can also export any QVariant instance,
which is a wrapper
basically a glorified void* and it
becomes a simple value type in qml. This
is probably the rarest thing to export.
Yes?
Yes. Yeah, well, it turns out the
converting the problem with variance is
that you can only convert them to and
from your particular item. And if since
in qml, you can't do a conversion to like
from a custom item to a strain. You could
really only pass it in and then pass it
back the c++ to have it processed. If you
want to have an item a struct exported
where you have, like myVariable.name
myVariable.title it needs to be a
QObject pointer. So we. Yeah. But
that's the trick and even in C++, QT,
there is no you can't override two
strengths for the photo complex types.
Yes, so what you're gonna do is and
there's actually example few slides away.
If you need to wrap something like
a something that works in variant in c++
and you convert back and forth, it's a
deep data structure you can wrap that in
a QObject and pass it out. So, but
we're going to be concentrating on
QObject pointer through an abstract item
model. So, so here we have a binding. We
were binding our rotation to some value,
a minute and a max. These could be
variables that are instance. Their
properties and qml or the bigger things
that have been pushed from C++, so qml
can call back the c++ by simply calling
the functions that are slots or use
Q_INVOKABLE. So you can say
backEnd.doSomething. So here's how you
would make say a Car object. And a Car
object has a list of sensors can get a
sensorValue units, a min and a max. So
the key here is we have the QObject,
Q_OBJECT macro, we use Q_ENUMS and we
have a Sensor.
And this is good C++ so far. Now the
problem with good C++ and qml is there
can be some clashes. One is qml does not
like enum at all, especially when you're
exporting the instance without the type.
There's a way to use enum when you
export the type. But when you're
exporting an instance, it's, it's a lot
harder but you can use a wrapper object.
Such as here what I'm really going to
export into qml is this CarSensorProxy
who has a bunch of Q_PROPERTY.
This is a flyweight object. It
is going to in its constructor take in a
pointer to a car and the sensor.
It's going to watch and then our interface is
going to be a simple property value min
and max in C++. We are going to create
our declarative view which is going to
give us the engine that the QML is going
to run inside of as well as the window
it's going to run in, and we setSource.
Here, I've got a project called
MegaDash which is gonna be a dashboard
for my car. And we can show it, and we can
extract it. Now what happens here in this
comment where it says:" Export C++"
"instances here."
"See next slide". Well, between creating
your view and setting the source, you can
export as many objects as you want.
Such as in a giant for loop export a hundred
sensors. So here I'm iterating over the
cars enum for its car sensor, and
I'm making car sensor proxy pointers and we
give it the car in the sensor. And then
we are exporting into the view. You get
the view.rootContext and you export
context property. Probably one of the
most ambiguously named functions and
Q. But this will export a C++
instance to objects into the execution engine.
The first parameter is a string
which
the name of the variable that's gonna be
used in QML. Since I use a for-loop here
my car is smart enough to return me a
string that represents the name for that
particular sensor. And we export a name
and a the actual pointer. So now
magically in my application, I have RPM,
speed, fuel pressure oil pressure.
Not only that but we can get
oilPressure.minimum, oilPressure.maximum,
oilPressure.value. Okay, so I'm basically
using a way of just taking things that I
allocate in C++. I control the life cycle
of and pushing them into the QML
execution engine. The only rule is that
for the lifetime of the view, these
objects need to exist or you're gonna
get seg faults. It makes sense, right?
So that is a nice quick and dirty way of
taking. And even appropriate in some
cases where you're going to take data.
Especially data models that you have in
C++. And you're just going to export them
into the QML runtime environments.
Maybe this is you know some tabular data that
you have, it's gonna run like a pie chart.
Or something we are reading things off
of a serial port or off of a network.
Any questions?
So we'll go back into the regular notes
even though I also talked about. It is
how to export types so rather than
having instances that we push into QML,
I want to say I'm gonna make my own type
of item, maybe call a car. And we're gonna
let QML programmers make an instance of
car where car's implementation is in C++.
And we're gonna do that, and we're
actually gonna do that with an ellipse item.
I mentioned that there's no ellipse
or circle item in QML. But we could make
our own and we could have it drawn and
managed in C++.
So anytime you want to write C++ code
that is going to know about the
declarative environment. There is a
separate Qt module called
QtDeclarative. So in your project file you
need to have QT += declarative.
And you need to pound
include things from the QtDeclarative module.
Oftentimes is there's so few
header files you can just use the magic
pound include QtDeclarative and get
them all. So here's an example where we
are including the QDeclarativeView. And
just like in the example we saw we make
a Declarative View and we set the source
on it. We show our window and we exec so
every view that you make is a new
runtime environment. So you probably want
to make as few of these as possible.
Inside of your project file, you want to
use QT += declarative. Now
from when it comes to RESOURCES, your QML
can actually be stored in the Qt
RESOURCES. So that when you say you know
setSource here is "qrc:files/animation.qml",
this is coming from the RESOURCES.
And remember that everything is relative
to the location of the qml file that you
are running.
So the contents of file/animation
that QML is going to use all relative
pathing. And that's going to be relative
into the resource file. So you're going
to include all of your QML source code
into the resource and then you can have
just distribute the executable and not
have to worry about this whole pile of
QML files to distribute along with you
executable. Yes. Yes.
Yeah, that's true. So there is a there is
a way to break the rule for main.qml.
The root item you could call it does
not need to start with a capital letter.
And sometimes you'll see it and some
people's projects start with just
main.qml, has the entry points with a
lowercase m. But for all other files that
that need to be loaded by QML, they need
to start with capital letter.
So to create a new instance your type,
you can either inherit from directly
QObject, or you can use QDeclarativeItem.
If you want to draw on through the
screen, you need to use QDeclarativeItem
which maps pretty much directly to
the Item in QML. If you just want to be a
hunk of data that people are going to
instance and pass around, then you can be
just fine inheriting straight from QObject,
and skipping the overhead. So
basically what's going to happen is
you're going to register this type to be
valid in QML, and we'll see what that
means in a minute. Stay for example.
First this ellipse1.qml file now
there is no ellipse item in QML. We're
going to make that in C++ and let users
use it. So here we have an import Shapes 1.0.
We have this new module called
Shapes, and inside of Shapes happens to
be the ellipse item and we create it
just like any other QML item. From the
point of view of this file the user does
not know if the ellipse is another QML file
or whether it's one of these C++ plugins.
So it's very clean from an API
standpoint. And the ellipse is just going
to draw the little ellipse on the right.
It's pretty basic. So how do we make this
item that can have a width and a height,
and be drawn in QML. Well, we simply
include QDeclarativeItem and inherit
from it. We use the Q_OBJECT the macro
that's going to be required and we
implement the constructor that takes in
a QDeclarativeItem *parent. This is
going to be used by QML to assign you
parent
just like you do for Q_OBJECT and QWidget.
There's gonna be parent-child
hierarchy we've already used that. Then
you need to implement the paint function.
So this is actually maps one to one and
actually up above of QDeclarativeItem
inherits QGraphicsItem. And
QGraphicsItem has the paint method
that takes in a painter a
QStyleOptionGraphicsItem and a widget
pointer which is the widget you're being
drawn on. So the implementation is
actually pretty easy, we have a simple
constructor, we pass our parents up to
our superclass, and we need to have this
setFlag. By default items are not drawn.
If you want to be drawn on the screen,
you need to set this flag graphics item
ItemHasNoContents to false. Why it's
not the default to be drawing on the
screen, I'm not sure, but it's what you
have to do in its paint function. We do
something super basic. We take that
QPainter pointer that we've been passed.
And painter as you might know from
the C++ API has a drawEllipse function
which takes in a rectangle. And we're
going to take in our option rect which
specifies the rectangle of the screen
that we take up. So whatever space we've
been allocated, we're going to try to
draw an ellipse that is going to
inscribe that rectangle.
Yeah. Well, you can imagine if you're a
root item maybe somebody starts a QML
file with ellipse open bracket, you have
no, you have no parent. Now your parents is
another QDeclarativeItem. The widget
that you get passed in the paint function
is pretty much useless. It's really there
because it's useful when you're doing
Qt graphics view programming, and
you're inheriting from QGraphicsView here.
Here be a little forward declaration in
QML 2.0. This particular API is changing.
But if you use QDeclarativeItem, you
can actually get the same the same
function names and syntax by using
Qt quick painted item. So there is a
upgrade path but there will be no
QDeclarativeItem anymore. And that will
change in Qt five. So, yeah, what we have
in main instead of exporting a
C++ instance of something, we're actually
using this macro function qmlRegisterType
to register a type into the QML
runtime. And we are exporting the
EllipseItem class and we're putting it in the
Shapes module, major version, one, minor
version, zero, and the name of this item
is going to be Ellipse. Notice that the
names don't have to match. We then go
ahead and make our view. We may, we
set our source and now the code that uses
the EllipseItem is going to work.
Because now Ellipse is a valid type. When
you make an instance of Ellipse, it's
actually going to make an instance of
your EllipseItem.
Yeah, it's kind of a beaut part of it.
Well, since, yeah, since you are basically
by inheriting QDeclarativeItem,
you're inheriting item. Remember that
item that is the generic in base class
for everything that's basically what
you're inheriting. So you get x and y,
invisible and opacity and all of those
properties of item you inherit, just like
when you inherit from C++, from a
Q_OBJECT with properties, you inherit all
their properties too. So from the client
side's perspective whoever makes
whoever's writing that QML never
knows what's implemented in C++, and
what's implemented in QML. And that's a
good thing. It's not any different. So if
you. Even if you wrote some QML and you
had this fancy game board object. And you
found that it wasn't fast enough doing
it in JavaScript. Well, you could make
game board in C++ and export it as game
board. And your game board code would
still work. So, do note here that we are
registering these with the fully
qualified imports. So, this is import
Shapes, 1, 0. There's no way to do this
without having the module and the
version.
And we are effectively a sub type of
item. So here for example we have the
ellipse item, and we want to add a
property. We want to add a property to
our ellipse to have a color. So we want
to fill it here with the color blue. The
x, y, width and height we got from
inheriting item easy, but we need to add
color.
Luckily adding color is as simple as I'm
adding the Q_PROPERTY macro. We need a
read function a write function and a
notify signal. So you would make your C++
as usual. Meaning that you're gonna have
a member for your color. You're gonna
have a setColor and a color getter. And
you're gonna have a signal for colorChanged.
This is as normal as Qt as you
can get. Then, at your header file you
simply use the Q_PROPERTY macro. You
specify the type of this property which
is QColor, a name which is simply color.
A read function called color a write
function called setColor and a notify signal
called colorChanged. This is a an
opportunity that you don't have in
straight QML, is that you can make
read-only properties by manipulating the
Q_PROPERTY macro. So if you didn't
have a write function then you would be
read-only. And if someone tried to set
your value the QML runtime would
complain, and say that is a right own,
that is a read-only property. Also, some
properties don't have a dynamic. So
there's no reason to have a notification signal.
In that case, you can replace
NOTIFY with constants. And you don't need
to specify a signal that tells the QML
environment never to expect a signal
when this changes often useful when you
want to have read-only constants exposed
as properties.
So it's pretty simple when you in C++.
Just like if you were writing graphicsItem
were you writing widgets in your
sets? You should always make sure that
what you're being set to is different
than what you already are. That will keep
you from getting infinite recursion. If
you have signals and slots crossed up
and you set your color. You call update
to repaint yourself and you emits the
correct signal and here we have the
signal colorChanged. And now, all of this
code basically equates to the color
property in QML and likewise since it's
a real property. There's an
colorChanged signal handler that you could
implement.
That's a good question. I guess no reason
in particular it could have been called
ellipse. Good question!
So the main when we exported it we did
this qmlRegisterType which takes in a
string name to use for the type name. It
which does not have to be the same as
the class name. Is that? It is a template.
It is a template. Now, the nice thing
about Qt in general is that Qt uses
templates. You know, here, there, and all
over the place. But does it really force
you to write template classes which is
nice? But this is an example it's a
template function. It takes in a type and
it does it's magic.
Yeah so then in your paint method which
is going to be called just like in
widgets or in graphics, you is gonna be
called any time you call update. now it
gets a little more complicated because
we can't simply draw the ellipse, we're
going to save our painter state. We're
gonna set the pen, we're gonna draw set the brush,
we're gonna draw the ellipse,
and restore the painter state. It is
always polite to save and restore the
painter States any time somebody passes
you a QPainter pointer. We'd be rather
rude if you change the contents of
somebody else's pointer when your
function returns. So in summary we've
seen that we can create a new type with
qmlRegisterType, we can make a new
visual item with QDeclarativeItem,
and we can add some Qt properties. Does
anybody have any questions on this is?
We're gonna move on the functions and
slots and fun things like enum. Yes? Yeah,
in fact you can have a parameter most
times in C++. You would have as a
parameter, the, the newColor. QML will
always ignore the parameter. So it's like
one of those things in QT. You can always
drop parameters from signal to slot. So
when, when that signal. When the on
property changed it's going to be a
signal with no parameters. It just wants
to know that needs to rerun all of the
evaluations.
Oh. No. But what you can do and you know
this. This will get you a little further
is that you could inherit from
QDeclarativeItem. Okay, and you can
actually you could inherit from
QProxy widget, and you can actually wrap
your QT widget in QProxy widgets,
which is a, which is a QGraphicsItem.
And you can find examples of that online.
Be warned.
Just like when doing graphics view
programming QProxy widget has
performance problems. So if you try to
take that QML screen that has an
embedded Q table in it. And you try to
animate it, it's probably going to drop
in performance. But you can do it.
In fact, we've done that at ICS for some
projects that one use like QWT chart to
do some line graphing. Yep
Yep. It is better to use multiple signals.
Because unless they are intrinsically
related. Because it is going to when that
signal fires QML is going to rerun all
bindings that include that property. So
if you change one property, but you just
have this uber everything change signal,
that's attached to four different,
properties then QML is going to seek out
those four properties and rerun all the
expressions in the bindings. As opposed
to have one really change you can get,
you know, just maybe two of the lines
instead of ,you know, 20 lines to be
recalculated. So that's the downside
there.
So now we want to add functions. Oh,
actually we want to add signals to our
Qt class that we are exporting into QML.
So basically what we want to have, so
wouldn't have the ellipse, have an on,
have a onReady signal. And so we can use
the onReady signal handler. Ready in this
context doesn't really mean anything.
There's no, it's not like QML and QT are
running in separate threads and there's
a some synchronization that needs to go
on. This is just an example, just some
state that's changing. So and what we
want to do is when something's ready we
want to change some text label to say
Ready. Very simple. And all you need to do
in QT is do what you'd normally do. Just
declare a signal Ready just like you did
color changed. The meta-objects will take
everything from there. You just recompile
your program and of course you need to
emit the signal. But after you implement
a signal this code will run whenever the
your emit ready. So for example we have a
QTimer signal single-shot just for
giggles after two seconds we're going to
emit the signal ready. So at some point
the signal is going to get emitted
onReady is going to be called and we have
stuff happening in QML because we have
emitted signals. So when people ask me
how do I manipulate the QML items from
C++ what you really want to do from a
design perspective is not find the items
and manipulate them but you want to
design your back-end to emit the right
signals that state has changed and let
the user interface decide what that
change, in state means for the user
interface.
So if you want to add callbacks
basically we want slots that we can call
from QML. It is just as easy as making
slots in C++. You have your option so
here when the mouse areas clicked we
want to actually call setColor on our
object with the strain of a color. So
what we can do is we can have this new
slot called setColor and you'll notice
that it takes in a QColor. Now, the
nice thing about QColor is that it
has an implicit conversion from strings.
So we can pass it darker green and when
it gets called in C++ a darker green
will be passed to the implicit copy constructor
for QColor, and we will
make a color from quote darkgreen. So
you have your option of specifying
public slots or using the Q_INVOKABLE macro.
20y prefer. Yeah, so first things
like a things that should be slots. Like
has an experience Qt programer, you
just you'll know what needs what should
be slots like things like setColor is a
good candidate for a slot. Something
where you're doing like a function,
that's going to return a value is not a
good candidate for a slot, but it might
be a good candidate for something to be
called from QML like it getMeSomeValue.
In that case, I would use getMeSomeValue
with Q_INVOKABLE in front
of it before someone thinks that they
can connect a regular C++ signal to this
thing and being like what the does the
deal with this function.
So we can also, we can also add methods
using the Q_INVOKABLE such as the
randomColor method here, where we are
setting our parent.color to parent.randomColor,
parent is an ellipse. So the
storage for QColor is in C++ and we're
using a function that returns a type. So
here bringing them color is not really
something that's useful as a slot. We use
the Q_INVOKABLE macro and we say return
a QColor and randomColor. Done. Now the
meta-object system is going to find that
macro, add it to the list of callable
functions and it now appears in QML. So
this line will run on click,
parent.color randomColor. And randomColor
here is implemented as some random color
actually. It's nothing to really say
about that. So we figured out that we can
define signals just like we do in C++,
and they were usable by QML. We can
define slots just like we do in C++,
usable by QML. And we can define
functions and give them the
Q_INVOKABLE macro and they're usable from QML.
Any questions so far?
So defining custom property types. So you
can guess that things like floats and
boolean and string and colors work. But
what if we wanted something more
complicated like another item or another
QObject that's deep it has many
properties or maybe we want to use enums
from C++. For example, we want to make our
ellipse taken style property where style
isn't enum such as Outline. So you'll see
these sprinkled all over the QtQuick,
stuff where you can say text.something.
You can make your own ellipse.something
which is an enum and this
is actually pretty easy because all you
need to use is a Q_PROPERTY macro and
the Q_ENUMS macro. This is actually an
old macro goes back, you know, decade
maybe longer. It was actually used in
designer plugins. It's how a designer
would know that when you had in your
property tree that this is a, you know,
what style do I want my frame to be
drawn in. It actually got it strings to
display from this Q_ENUMS macro. What it
does is the meta-object compiler is
going to read your header file and go
looking for an enum called Style.
It then going to make a map of the
string name of the, the string name of
the enum to the const, integer and
keep that map. So you can convert to and
from string and that's the same exact
functionality that the QML uses to
convert your Outline and Filled to
ellipse.Outline and ellipse.Filled.
These aren't 0 and 1 they're
actual strengths. So once you use the
Q_ENUMS macro you can use Q_ENUMS. You
can use Qt style
has a type in a Q_PROPERTY macro and this
just works. You just need to have a style
and a setStyle, some storage and a
signal.
And just like in C++, just like we
set the color all you need is a getter and
setter. And make sure your set or calls
updates and emits the right signal very
similar to the way we did the color
Except now we have an enum. So maybe enum
isn't specific enough. Maybe we want to
trade in other declarative items. We want
to set our style by passing an instance
of a style class which is another class
that we're going to export. So like you
can make instances of ellipse. You can
make an instance of a style where style
is a non visual item. It's just a
collection of data. So how could we do
this? Well, it's a little more complicated.
We're apparently also up to Shapes 7.0,
but what you can do is we declare
another QDeclarativeItem. And this time
it's gonna we're gonna leave the default
to not draw itself. Because this is just
data and we're going to implement two
properties Color and Filled, and we
implement that just like the ellipse. So
we're making a style class and an
ellipse class. And then we are going to
have a style and a setStyle. Now, what
makes this more, which makes this
interesting and different from C++
programming is that we are passing
pointers here and we're taking pointers.
So generally, in C++ you would return a
copy and you take a constant reference.
This is going to deal in pointers and
our Q_PROPERTY is going to be of type
style pointer and the name is going to
be style, READ is style, WRITE is setStyle,
and NOTIFY is styleChanged.
So when we do this we can actually
modify our paints actually use the style
and decide whether you're going to be
filled. And what color you're going to be
based on the contents of that style object.
So what we need to do is we need
to register in main not one type but two
types the style type and the ellipse item.
and once we do that amount of work
this code is actually going to work. Yes?
I think it could be. Yeah, yeah, could be.
Yeah. Yep.
Good question. Now you're getting into
religious wars. So according to purists
the, the point, the, the type is the type
and the fact that it is a pointer
actually belongs to the name of the
variable. Because if you use the common notation,
you know, this is a, I know, this
is a function declaration. But if you
were making variables and you said
style star name comma something else
so you made two instances in one line,
then where that would actually make is
not two pointers but one thing that's a
pointer and another thing that's an
actual stack instance. So some people
like to put the star after you know type
space star then the the object it's
really a style thing. I prefer to have
the star after the type and I don't put
two things in one line.
Hmm, good question. I'm not actually sure
on that. What's that?
Oh, is it required that the star go to
the, on the star, on style. Yeah, and I'm
not sure on that. Actually was a good
question. Yeah, or if we would take it
either way I'll have to look into that.
Yeah.
So another question is okay. Maybe I want
to have a property that is actually a
list. So just like we had an array of
styles and an array of transitions. Maybe
I want to have a chart object and that
chart object has a list of bars. So how
would we do this from C++? Well, it's
pretty easy because we have a special
type of property that is going to be a
QDeclarativeListProperty. So here
we are going to use the Q_PROPERTY,
syntax where our type is actually going
to be a template which is QDeclarativeListProperty
and we give it the type of
which this list will contain. And it's,
you know, going to be called bars. It's
read functions bars and it has a
NOTIFY barsChanged. And what we're going to
find out here is that in reality our
bars is going to be read rights
even though we don't have a write
function. And the reason for that is that
the read function returns the list not
the contents of the list. So we can
manipulate the list after we get the
reference from the read function.
Yeah, okay.
Yeah, I don't, I don't think so. Because
the, because the items themselves need to
be destroyed by QML. Because, imagine if
you, the situation where you set three
styles in a row
or you keep changing the style because
you keep clicking on it like you can't
let them just sit out on the heap
waiting for their parent to die. That
would be at the end of the application.
So that, suggests that, it's doing the
management on after you said it, it would
delete, it. Yeah, and yeah. And that's gonna
be required for grabs. Yeah.
So we make this ChartItem which is
going to use our BarItem and we have
this QList of BarItem pointers. And
we are going to have a static append_bar
function which is going to take into the
list to append to and the BarItem to
append. So and then in our function bars
which is our read function, we are simply
going to go ahead and return a
QDeclarativeListProperty. And the
QDeclarativeListProperty is a little
complicated because it is a templates. So
it takes in the type of which it
contains. It, it takes in a pointer to the
as a parent and it takes in a function
pointer to append to. So that's how it's
going to know that when you call BAR, BAR,
BAR. how it's going to append, append,
append on to the list.
So in append_bar what we do is we set
the parents correctly so that we're
going to take possession of this item. So
we can arrange it correctly. We're going
to append on to our bars object and
we're going to omit barsChanged.
So what we've seen is a way to make a
QDeclarativeItem that can be
instance and seen on the screen like the ellipse.
We've seen how we can export
properties in enums. We've seen how we
can, we can export sub items, so our
ellipse had a style item. We've also seen
how we can have our visual item, have
other visual items and manage them in a
list like our chart had a list of bars
using the QDeclarativeListProperty,
which is a fairly complicated thing and
you know needs the function pointer to
append onto. But is generally using the
same Q_PROPERTY syntax as everything
else. So the final thing that we're going
to talk about is how to take your C++
items and put them into a module so just
like we had the line item module. We're
going to make our Shapes module. We're
instead of exporting the types from main
we're gonna let some shared objects take
care of that. And just like Qt scans
certain directories and gets all the
sequel drivers and all the image drivers
It is going to scan certain directories
and finds your QML C++ plugins. So what
you can do much like every other plug-in
in Qt.
You can simply inherit from
QDeclarativeExtensionPlugin same idea
as, you know, QImageFormatPlugin or a
QSequelDriverPlugin. And it needs to
use the Q_OBJECT macro and needs to
implement one function called registerTypes.
and what happens in registerTypes
is, well what you used to have in main. So
you'll have a qmlRegisterType.
You are going to be pass your uri.
The reason why this is
passed is because the Q, the QML manifest
is going to define that and
where you located in the file system is
going to define what the name of your
package is. You specify the version here.
We're up to 9.0 and we have the name of
the item is going to be ellipse. Now to
be entirely accurate we should really
have two registers. We, we should registry
ellipse item and register our style item.
And we have to use the magic export
plugin, too. Just like every other plugin,
this is going to expand to some see
symbols that Qt is going to use to go
fishing in the shared object to get your
entry points to call registerTypes. So
you want to build this as a shared
library so you can use something along
the lines of this project file. We have a
template of library we need to tell the
CONFIG variable that were a qt plugin.
We need to use HEADERS and SOURCES of
course and possibly a DESTDIR to drop
our shared object somewhere that's
useful. So we get back to this thing
where we have a plugins directory and
maybe a standalone directory and we have
this qmldir. So this qmldir is a
manifest and we saw that qmldir can
specify QML files. We can also specify
shared object plugins to load when you
load this import. And the way you do that
is you specify an extra line in your QML
jar that says plug-in ellipse. Plug-in,
that's the name of the shared object
without the dot so at the end and the
directory to find that shared object in
which is a relative path. So it could be
in, in this case, ../plugins. It
could be in
relative path plugins so in one qmldir
file you can have a bunch of QML files,
and one or more C++ plugins. And to the
user who imports that package, you know,
they're never quite sure if what's
implemented in QML and what's in C++. It
looks all the same to them. So, you know,
here's an example here of using the
ellipse. And if the qmldir and ellipse9s
are in the same directory then there's
no need to em, you don't need to import
your own module is pretty much the point
of this slide because ellipse9s is
actually a QML file that's being
distributed with our plugin.
so you can either let load these plugins
yourself using the QPluginLoader or
you can simply manipulate the QML import
path by manipulating static functions on
QApplication or setting the
QML import path environment variable.
So the extensions that you write in C++
can be compiled into plugins. They can be
bundled with other QML files and they
can be imported as one gigantic package
if you manipulate the QML import path or
use the - i flag to QML viewer. Thank You.
You will find these items so you don't
need to have a C++ wrapper. If you use
plugins you can actually get C++ code to
be run from QML viewer which is kind of
cool. You can load the plugins directly
using QPluginLoader or you can let
Qt automatically load the plugins using
QML import path that brings us to the
end of my presentation.