In this lecture, we're going to look at
states and transitions. A state is a
group of properties that can be applied
to your element. For example, if you look
at the scene here, this can be a summer state.
The Sun is this color, the sky is
this color, the tree is this color and
the ground is this color. And when we
change to spring, we have another set of
properties that are grouped in a state
that we call spring. I hope this makes sense.
A state is a group of properties.
A transition is how you go from one state
to another fluidly. Okay if you look, the
changes are fluid. We are not jumping
from color to color. There is some kind
of fluidity and the way we change from
one state to another. This is basically
what we are going to look at in this
lecture. And we are going to work a
project like this, to explore this. So, we
are going to start our project. File, New,
Application, it's a Qt Quick Application project.
We call it 'StatesAndTransitionsDemo',
hit next, choose your Qt Version, choose your kit,
and we are done. We should say 'States and Transitions Demo'.
And we are going to put our components.
We need a sky, a ground,
a tree and a sun. We are going to start
by putting in a 'Rectangle'. Its 'id' is going
to be 'containerRectId'. It is going to 'fill' the 'parent'.
We are going to put in our sky.
Let's align things correctly.
Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I. It really is nothing fancy.
It's just a 'Rectangle' with an ID, a width,
a height and a color. We put in our ground.
Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to align.
Our ground is also the same but it is
anchored to the bottom of the sky and it
stretches up to the bottom of the window.
It has a width,
the same as the parent and it
has this color. Next, we want to put in our
tree. All trees really, because we are
going to implement this as two trees and
depending on the state, we are in, we are
going to hide one and show the other.
We have a spring tree and a summer tree and
we should add them in our resource file.
So we are going to 'Add new', 'Qt', 'Qt Resource File',
we call this 'resource' as usual.
We are going to go where this link
is stored, Show in Explorer. Ok our folder
is here. We want to create an 'images'
folder. Open it and put in our images. You
see that there are two images: one is for
spring, the other is for summer. You can
use these images in your project. No
problem. We're going to come back to our
project here. We're going to add a
'Prefix', we take it out, hit enter. We
add files and we select our folder and
select our images. We save this and our
images should now be recognisable. The
last component is the Sun. So we should
put it in here. Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to align. It
has a width and height of 100. It is at
this position by default. So it is in the
right side of the canvas and it is on Y 50.
It is yellow, it is a circle. That's
why we made the radius very big. Right
now we can run our application and see
how it looks.
We haven't applied any states so it
should look like this.
You see that we are seeing the summer
tree. Why is that? We are seeing the
summer tree because we put it last and
it is being staffed on top of the spring tree.
So what we want to do is to define
our states. So the way you define your
states, you say 'states'
like this and you put in an array that
is going to be your state. Okay inside,
you can say 'State' and it's going to be
your state here and you like to separate
them by a comma like this and say 'State'
again. We want to have two states so we
put in two here, summer and spring. So we
should give them names like this, so we
can give your state a name: the first one
is going to be "summer", the second one is
going to be "spring" and we should specify
how our set of properties are going to
change to go in this state. For that we
use a PropertyChange component,
the 'target' is going to be the 'sky',
we are going to start by the sky and
the color is going to change to deep sky
blue. No, in summer the sky should be
light blue. The summer tree should be
visible and the spring tree should be
invisible. So we make the opacity for the
summer tree 1 and the opacity for the
spring tree 0. This is how we show one
and hide the other. This is a trick you
should learn. It comes in handy many
times. The ground is going to change to be
dark khaki and the Sun should turn
yellow. Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to align. So we
have our properties in place for the
summer state. We should also do the
spring state. In spring, the sky should
turn deep sky blue. We should hide the
summer tree and show the spring tree
which is what we have here. Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to align.
So that things are
visible. The summer tree opacity is zero so
it is invisible, the spring tree opacity
is 1 so it is visible. The ground should
turn to this color, a 'lime'.
And the sun should turn light yellow.
Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to align.
And this is how the sun is going to look and
we want to start in this summer state.
Okay so we should come here and say
'state' "summer" and right now we have our
state defined. We set our default state.
We should run to see what our
application looks like. Okay you see that
we start in summer. The ground looks like
this. We have a summer tree and the sun
looks like this. Let's go back to our
application and change to spring. Run the
application. And you see that we turn the
colors to look like in spring. Now we
want to automate the changes from one
state to another. We are going to put in
a MouseArea that is going to fill the
container rectangle. Let's go to its
bottom right here, put in a MouseArea,
'anchors.fill' 'parent', onClicked and we
are going to say 'containerRectId.state'.
the state of the container rect is going to
be equal to the expression that we are
going to put in here. So if this state
equals 'spring', we are going to set this
state to 'summer', otherwise we are going
to set that to 'spring'. This is what this
expression says here. And if this doesn't
make sense, you should check your a
ternary operation knowledge by some
JavaScript tutorial. It is really easy we
are saying if the state equals 'spring',
set the state here to 'summer', if it is
not equal to 'spring', set this to 'spring'.
Let's run the application and we should
be able to toggle
between states and you see that the
changes are really great. We are
jumping from one state to another and it
should really help if we could make the
changes fluid when we go from one state
to another. And that's when transitions
come in. Transitions allow you to make
the changes in states fluid. Let me show
you what I mean. I'm going to go back to
our application and put in a transition.
The syntax really looks like the states
so we're going to say 'Transitions' here
and 'States' on top here. Let's go back to
transitions and say 'transitions'. You see
that we have a property of transitions
down here and put in an array like this.
Inside we want to put a set of
transitions. We want to go 'from' "summer" 'to'
"spring". The color changes are going to be
animated. Okay because we are changing
colors a lot. You're going to put in a
'duration' of 500 for example and we
should say NumberAnimation also. The
'property' that is going to change is
'opacity'. The 'duration' is also going to be
500. Okay, from summer to spring we are
going to animate like this. If we run the
application, okay, we are in spring. If we
go to summer, you see that the change is
crisp, it's very fast, there is no
animation. But if we go from summer to
spring, you see that it is animated. Okay
this is how you can animate from one
state to another. We also want to animate
from spring to summer. We should
basically say the same thing. Put in a
transition.
We're going to copy this transition, put
a comma here to separate them and put
another one. This one is going to be from
spring to summer and it basically is
going to be the same thing.
Okay, our changes are animated now from one
state to another. This is how you do it.
So if you don't want to separate this
things, if the animations are the same no
matter your direction, no matter if you
are going from summer to spring or
spring to summer, we can actually comment
this out. Let's comment this out and show
you another way you can do this. That is
easier and more readable if you want to
do the exact same thing like this. We can
say 'transitions' and pass in one
'Transition' and say 'from' any state 'to' any
state. We are going to do these
animations: ColorAnimation and NumberAnimation.
We should put in our colon here,
and put a semicolon in here to make
thing
pass the syntax check. And we are going
to put in our usual animation here.
ColorAnimation and NumberAnimation on
opacity. This is how you can pass
transitions to your animation. It is
going to work the same but now we have
one transition that is targeting
everything from any state to any state.
And this is really all that is to
working with states and transitions.
A state is a set of properties and you can
pass from one stage to another, just like
we did here, just by setting the stage.
The default state for our case here was
spring. And we are able to switch between
spring and summer. And this is how you
specify the properties for your state.
And these are the different
syntaxes that you can use to pass from
one state to another with an animation
specified within your transition
component here. This is all for this
lecture. In the next one, we're going to
show you how you can work with gradients
in your state and transitions.
I'll see you there.