In this lecture, we're going to do an
animated ball bounce. This is going to be
a slightly different demo that we're
going to be doing. Because I am going to
show you a reference that is very good
to learn about QML. We're going to find a
good example inside and we're going to
run it. I think this is a good way to let
you know of ways you can find things you
don't know yet. Okay, the reference, I was
talking about, is this book here. It is a
book that is available online. It is
called
'A book about Qt5'. It is contributed by
some people. It is open source. It has an
open license, you can read it or you can
even contribute to it if you happen to
have things to add to it. I'm going to
let you read on all these things if you
want. So what we want to do is to go in
chapter 5 on 'Fluid elements' and we want
to look at 'Animations'. And you see that
they also talk about easing curves. They
give you a good lecture about them. You
can really look at this. So let's scroll
down find our thing and we want to look at
'Grouped Animations'. You see that they
show how you can animate things. This is
basically what we did in the last
lecture. A SequentialAnimation, you move
on Y and on X and the ParallelAnimation
where it happens at the same time. But
this is not what we want. We want to do
this thing here, a bouncing ball. So we're
going to read this together and create a
Qt project to play with it.
So, grouped animation can also be nested
for example, a sequential animation can have
two parallel animations as child
animations and so on.
Okay so animations can be nested. We can
visualise this with the soccer ball
example. The idea is to throw a ball from
left to right and animate its behaviour.
Ok, this is what we want to do.
To understand the animation, we are going to
break this into three parts. We are going
to animate on X from left to right, we
are going to animate on Y1 the ball going
up, we are going to animate on Y2 the ball
going down,
and we are going to apply some bouncing
on this when the ball goes down, and we
are going to rotate the ball over the
entire animation. And they try to depict
what we are doing here. We are going to
animate on Y, we are going to start by
animating on Y , we are going to go
down and over all this period we are
going to be rotating and moving in X.
Let's go to Qt Creator, start a project
and follow up with us. Okay here we are
in Qt Creator, we are going to create our
project.
It's a Qt Quick Application. We call it
'AnimatedBallBounceDemo', save it in the
usual location, choose a Qt Version,
choose our kit and finish. We are going
to do everything in our 'main.qml' file.
We're going to skip this. This is kind of
a container for everything you are going to do.
The next step would be to add the
background, which is in our case two
rectangles with the green and blue
gradients. Okay we are basically going to
put in this. The first rectangle is this 'sky'.
It has a gradient. A gradient is
really a translation from different
colors. Okay you see this blue, start out
a little bit darker and it goes bright
as we go down and the same thing happens
to the green it starts out light and it
goes dark. So we're going to copy our
rectangle here and I think we should
actually copy all these, bring them back
in our example here. This is good
practice to copy and paste in your
projects and learn how to insert them.
Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to align. We have our background. The sky
is going to be this gradient. The ground
is going to be this gradient. And you see
that the ground is anchored to the bottom
of the sky and it is to touch the
bottom of the window. We can actually run
the application we have right now and
see how it looks.
Let's run you see that
our ground is not working. So, what is the
problem? We want to anchor the rectangle
for the ground to the bottom of the
parent so we should change this to
'parent.bottom'. This is better. Let's run
to see what we have now. Okay you see
that we have our sky and the ground
which is green. The upper rectangle is
going to take 200 pixel of the height
and the lower one is going to take the
remaining height.
Let's bring the soccer ball on the
canvas. The ball is an image stored under
"assets/soccer_ball.png'. For the beginning, we
would like to position it in the lower
left corner, near the edge. Okay it's going to
start out here. So what we're going to do is
basically bring in this image here, come
back to our project. We put it below the
second rectangle, the ground one. We want
to add a resource file that is going to
contain this image here. So I am going to
come here 'Resources', add new,
Qt resource file, we call it 'resource'.
This is done. We go back to where our project is stored.
That should be here. We want to
add the new directory called 'images' and
I want to open the directory and put in
my image of the ball. So if you don't
have this ball, you can come back to this
book here. I want to go to the start of
it and you're going to see that you can
find the chapter examples in the assets
folder. We are in chapter 5 so we should
look for chapter 5. Let's look at that.
You should download chapter 5 here and
you're going to extract this and find
the balls and the examples that you need.
So put that in your images folder like
this or you can even copy this image
from the project that I provided with
the course here. We're going to close
this because we don't need it anymore.
We're going to add a 'Prefix', take it out
because we don't want it, add file,
'images', we choose 'soccerball'. Notice the
name here, 'soccerball.png'. We save,
we come back here and we change this to
'images/soccerball.png'. You see that
it is recognised and you see that they
are saying 'root' here so we should define
this 'root' to be this window, because it
is parent. So it should say 'root' here.
So, it is going to be to the left bottom
because X is going to be 0 and the
height is going to be the height of the
parent which is this 'root' window here
minus the height of the ball. And when we
click, we are going to reset its X
position, its Y position, its rotation and
we are going to start the animation.
This is not defined yet so you can safely
ignore it now. We can actually comment
this out. We don't want it to influence
what we have. Let's run to see that we
have our ball in the correct location.
mm-hmm... We have our ball here. This is
good and right. Ok we have our image in
place. This is what we should have.
The image has a mouse area attached to it.
If the ball is clicked the position of the
ball will reset and the animation
restart. Let's start with a sequential
animation for the 2 Y transitions.
So, they put an a SequentialAnimation
to animate the ball to go up and go down.
Ok, it is going to animate 'to' 20 and its
going to animate back 'to' 240 and the
'duration' is going to be 0.4 and 0.6.
Let's copy this and put this in our
project. You should put that below the
image. This would work. So we have
SequentialAnimation. Ok the ball is
going to animate upwards and it's going
to animate downwards and you see that
40% of the time is going to be used upwards
and 60% of the time is going to be used
downwards. So we should define this
duration here. Let's go up. I don't think
we defined it.
Let's do 'property' 'int' call this 'duration'
and it is going to be one second (1000).
They said three seconds in the book but
I like to do one. You can do whatever you
want. And we took this chance to change
this thing. This should do. You should go
down now and uncomment this thing here.
Okay I hope you are seeing the process
you can go through to design something fun.
Let's run. The animation is going to
restart and we are going to see the ball
go up and down. Okay
that's what happens.
Now what we want is to put in the edge
and rotation animation. Let's go back to
the book. Next we need to add the X-translation.
The X-translation shall run
in parallel with the Y-translation
so we need to encapsulate the sequence
of Y-translations into a parallel
animation together with the X-translation.
So this is what we're going
to do. This is a SequentialAnimation
that we have. We are going to wrap that
into a ParallelAnimation and we're
going to add a NumberAnimation that is
going to animate the ball on the X
coordinate. Let's put in our parallel
animation. The 'id' is going to be 'anim'
and it is going to contain this
SequentialAnimation that we have here.
Let's take it out, put it in, take out this
'id' because we don't want it anymore.
But down here we want to put another
NumberAnimation and
the NumberAnimation is going to be what we have
here.
So we copied this and put that in here.
Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to align. So we are
animating the ball,
we are animating on X, it is going to
animate up 'to' 400 and the 'duration' is
going to be the duration that we have
here. Let's run the application and when
we start, we are starting the parallel
animation and things are going to happen
at the same time. You see that the ball
animates from left to right. We are
making some progress. Right? Okay this is
what we have. At the end we would like
the ball to be rotating. For this we need
to add another animation to the parallel
animation. We chose the RotationAnimation
because it is specialized for
rotation. Our RotatioAnnimation is going
to be like this. It is going to happen
all along from start to finish.
'target' is going to be 'ball' and it is
going to rotate up to this angle here.
Let's put that
in our project. It's going to be below
NumberAnimation because it needs to be
included in the ParallelAnimation here.
This is what we have.
Let's run. Okay, as we go, we are rotating.
We are having something more similar to
what we want. We should go back to the
book and see the next step. That's the
whole animation sequence. The one thing
left is to provide the correct easing
curves for the movements of the ball. For
Y1 animation I use 'Easing.OutCirc' curve as
this should look more like a circular
movement. Y2 is enhanced with Easing.OutBounce
as the ball should bounce at the end.
Okay the ball should bounce as we
end the animation. So what they did, they
put easing.type to when the ball is
going up and it is Easing.OutCirc.
When the ball is going up, we... ease OutCirc.
This is our animation here. Let's go back
to the book. When we go down, we.. ease OutBounce.
Let's go back to our code and use that.
Let's look at the book again and
see what we have. We don't have anything
else. This is really all. Let's come to
the project, run it and when you click,
you have a ball doing a bouncing
movement here. And ladies and gentlemen,
this is what we had to do in this
lecture. I hope you enjoyed it. The most
important thing is to see that you can
use this book here to learn a few things
that you might want to know, that I
didn't have a chance to cover. It is very
rich in content. They talk about more
things than I could cover in this course.
You see they talk about multimedia, the
talk about shader effects, they talk
about the canvas element. These are all
very interesting topics and you should
refer to this book when you are done
with this course. I think you are going
to have enough ground to read it and
understand it. Okay this is all I had for
this lecture. And the next one we're
going to look at states and transitions
I'll see you there