In this lecture we're going to do a demo
on working with translation, rotation and scaling.
And let's go to Qt Creator and do that.
Okay, here we are, in Qt Creator.
We're going to create a new project.
it's going to be a Qt Quick Application as usual.
we're going to call it 'TransformsDemo',
save it in a location on our drive,
choose our Qt Version, choose our kit and finish.
So, what we want to do is put
a set of rectangles in this window here,
and apply the transforms when you click
on the rectangle. We are going to do
translation, rotation and scaling.
Because we don't want to be repeating ourselves,
we want to create a component and use it all over again.
So we want to come here
to this QML resource file, add new, Qt,
we want to add the QML file and we want
to call it 'ClickableRect'
because that's what it is. We don't want to do
anything fancy here. We want to change
this 'import' to import the latest version
of Qt Quick and we want to turn this into
a rectangle. We don't want to do anything fancy.
We want to give it an ID.
Let's call this 'root' and we are going to
declare a 'signal' here to notify us when
the Mouse Area inside this rectangle is
clicked and we want to define
our MouseArea. Notice that we didn't put
any parentheses on the signal here. This
is possible in QML. We want the MouseArea
to fill the 'parent' and when it is
clicked, we want to emit this signal and
you already know how to emit a signal,
we call it like we call another JavaScript function.
So we're going to say a
'root.clicked()' like this.
Okay, our component here is done. We can
come back to main QML and start
working with that. We want to change the
title here to 'Transform Demo'.
We want to put in a rectangle
that is going to fill the window.
Inside this is going to be container. We wanted to
fill the parent and we wanted to have a
colour. Let's put in 'beige' and inside we
want to have a MouseArea that is going
to fill this rectangle. Let's say 'parent'
because it is the parent of this mouse
area and we want to know when it is clicked.
And this is where we are going to do a
few changes to the rectangles that we
are about to define. So we are going to
go down here and define our rectangles.
We are going to use 'ClickableRect',
the type that we just defined in here.
The ID is going to be 'rect1Id'. We want the
width to be 100 same as height. We wanted to
start at the x position of 50 and the
y position of 100. And when the
rectangle is clicked, notice that we can
say onclicked because we declared this
signal here, in the component here. We can
define a handler of this signal here.
Okay this is the convenience of using component.
So when you click on this
rectangle, the first one, we want to
translate on the x-axis. We are going to
increase the x-coordinate of this
rectangle here. So we're going to say x
+=, let's add 20 for example.
Okay, we should also give it a colour so that
we can differentiate them by just
looking at them. The colour is going to be
'red'. We want to copy this rectangle
because it's going to be mostly the same.
We are just changing the transforms that
we do when we click. Here we are doing a
translation
on x. This is going to be 'rect2Id'.
We want to put this at the x of 250
by default and when you click it we want
to add on its rotation property. Okay, we
want to add to the rotation angle, we're
going to add 15. We are going to see how
this works and the colour is going to be
'green'. Let's copy, put in our third
rectangle. By the way we should flag here
that we are working on rotation. Here we
are going to work on scaling. It should
be a 'rect3Id' here. And it's going to
start at the x location of 450.
Here we are going to add on this scale property
so we're going to say scale +=
let's add 0.05. We're going to see
how this looks.
These are the rectangles that are going
to be contained in the window here and
the widow is going to have a background
of this rectangle here. That is 'beige'.
We want to know when the user clicks
outside of these rectangles and we want
to put the rectangles back to the
starting position.
When you click here rect1 should go
back to x 50 so we're going to say
rect1Id.x equals 50. This is how
you bring them back. rect2Id.rotation
the rotation should go back to zero, so
we're going to say rotation equals zero.
rect3Id is going to go back to
the scale of 1 because this is the
default scale of our component. And these
properties, rotation and scale, I don't
think we talked about them before but
you can find them in the documentation.
Let's look at the 'rectangle' for example.
Click to find it, look at properties.
Okay, you see that it inherited item,
and if we look at properties that we
have here we are going to find, let's
scroll down a little bit, you can find
rotation, you can find scale here. And if
you click, they are going to tell you
exactly what they do. This property holds
the rotation of the item in degrees
clockwise around its transformOrigin.
We're going to look at transformOrigin
in a moment. But for now we just want to
run the application and see how it looks.
Okay, our app is here. The third rectangle,
we should change the colour. But if we
click on the red rectangle, you see that
it moves to the right. Okay if we click
on the green rectangle, you see that it
rotates around. And if we click on the
third rectangle, you see that it grows in size.
This is scaling in action. Okay if
you click outside, you see that they go
back to where they're belong. Okay, click
outside, they go back. We should go back
and change the colour of the third
rectangle to be 'blue', so that we can
differentiate these things. Okay now I
want you to see how you can work with
transformOrigin. This really makes sense
on rotation and scaling. If you look at
the second rectangle, if we click on it
you see that it is rotating and the
centre of the rotation is in the middle
of the rectangle. You click on the third rectangle,
you see also that it is
scaling but the centre of these scaling
behaviour is in the centre here. You can
actually modify this centre of the
transform by changing the transformOrigin property.
I think we can also look at this here.
This is the property that
holds the origin point around which
scale and rotation transform.
Okay, you can specify your transform to happen around
the top left, the top, top right
you can specify any of this enumerations here.
So we're going to go back to our code.
Look at the rotation transform that
we did here and say transformOrigin.
This is how you influence it.
Let's look at the documentation and see
what we can pass it here. We can say
'Item.BottomRight' for example. Why not copy
this and try it in our code. This is
great, right?
Okay our rectangle, the green one, is
going to rotate around the bottom right point.
Let's run the application.
Okay the bottom right point is here. If we click,
you see that our rotation happens around them.
Let's bring it back to the start by
clicking the beige rectangle. We can keep
playing with it. Come back to our code.
Let's say top right. Why's not
top right? If we run again, it's going to
rotate around the top right corner of
the rectangle. And this is what we have.
You can also do the same on the third rectangle,
where we apply is scaling transform.
So let's copy this for example.
Put it down here and say bottom left.
Why not? Let's run. And see our scaling
happening here. You see that the bottom
left is fixed and we are scaling in the
other directions. I hope this makes sense
and if you happen to need to do these
kind of changes, you can play with this
transformOrigin property of your item
in your QML code. Okay, and you can really
see that the transformOrigin is the
point around which your transform is
going to pivot. This brings us to the end
of this lecture. I hope it shed some
light on how you can work with these
kinds of transforms and really nothing
prevents you from mixing and matching
them. For example you can take the third
rectangle and also apply a rotation
property. Okay so that these things happen
together. Let's run and if you click, you
see that it is rotating and scaling at
the same time. Of course, if you click on
the beige rectangle, things go back to
normal, because we are resetting
everything here. In the next lecture, we
are going to introduce you to the
fascinating world of working with
animations in QML. I'll see you there.