A standalone animation is an animation
where you specify yourself the target
element that is going to be animate.
If you remember in the last lecture,
we didn't do that. We just stuff the
animation in a rectangle component and
we say what property we want to animate.
We're going to do things differently in this lecture.
Let's go to Qt Creator and do that.
Here we are in Qt Creator.
We're going to create our new project.
It's a Qt Quick Application.
We call it 'StandaloneAnimationDemo'.
Save it in the usual location, click next, do the usual
choose your kit here and finish.
We want to change the title here.
And we want to do exactly what we did in the last lecture.
But do things a little bit differently.
We're going to put in our
container rectangle. ID is going to be
'containerRectId'. It's going to fill the 'parent'
and it's going to be 'beige' background.
Inside we're going to have another rectangle.
ID is going to be 'containedRectId'.
Width's going to be 100, height is
going to be 100. The color is going to be
dodger blue and it is going to start at
the x-value of 50 and the y-value of 50.
Now we want to specify our animation.
We're going to say 'NumberAnimation'.
The element that we want to animate is this rectangle here
and we specify it using
the 'target' property. So we can say 'target'
'containedRectId'. This is our target, the
property that we want to animate.
You specify it using the 'property' property.
You specify x in quotes like this. We want
to animate the x-axis of this rectangle
and we specify the usual. The duration
is going to be two seconds and we want
to animate to the location of 530.
Okay we have our animation. Let's run the application
and see what we have.
The first thing you see is that unlike the
animations that we did in the last
lecture, this one doesn't start
automatically. You have to start it
yourself explicitly. Let's come back to the code
and we want to put in a MouseArea
that is going to allow us to start the animation.
We're going to go down the rectangle,
say MouseArea and 'anchors.fill: parent'.
We want it to fill the beige rectangle
and when it is pressed, we want
to do something and we want to do
something when it is released. We want to
give this animation an ID. We call it 'mXAnimationId',
and when we press we want
to start the animation. So you can copy
the ID here and say 'start' like this and
stop the animation when you release your
mouse, we're going to
stop the animation.
Let's run and see if our logic here
works.
I press, the animation goes. I release, the
animation stops. This is the behaviour we have.
And notice this syntax we are
using here to work with this animation.
This is what I want you to see.
Okay this animation is really independent
and for it to run, you have to start it yourself.
You also have to specify the target element
that you want to animate and the
rest is really what we had before.
And you can go to the documentation as usual
and look at the properties that are
available to you when you want to work with this thing.
You see that it is a child
animation of
PropertyAnimation and you can see all the
properties that you can play with this animation.
The thing we just did here,
you can do with the other animations,
that we have seen as well.
For example, you can do a RotationAnimation.
Let's select it here. ID 'mRotationAnimation'.
I want to target 'containedRectId'.
The 'property' that I want to animate
is 'rotation'. I want it to animate upto,
let's say, 2000 degrees. It's going to
spin a couple of times and the duration
is going to be 2000 as well, 2 seconds.
We can run the application. And you see that
if I press, the rotation is not applied
and that is because we did not start this animation.
I just wanted you to see
how easy it is to forget to start these animations.
So you start it like this and
stop it like this. Now, if we run, it's
going to run, if we press and it's going
to stop if we release as usual. And this
is really all I've to share with you in this lecture,
a different way if you will
to work with animations by explicitly
specifying the 'target' and the 'property'
that you want to animate on QML element.
In the next lecture we're going to work with Easings.
I'll see you there.