In this lecture we're going to see how
you can work with gradients within your
States changes. This is a subject that
confuses many students so I thought it
was a good idea to include it as a
lecture and make things clear a little
bit. We're going to go to QT creator and
look at that. We are going to start from
this state we left the last lecture and
but I am going to do this as a separate
project to have been separated nice and
neat. So I am going to create a new
project, file - new project,
it's a QT quick application we call it
StatesWithGradientsDemo, choose our QT
version, choose our kit, hit next and
finish. Let's state what we want to do. I
am going to go to the last project and
copy whatever we had in there and use it
here. The way I do that, I'm going to go
back there, you should go there in your
project and copy everything that is
inside the window element. We should do
it like this. I think this is correct.
Let's double check, yes, hit copy we come
back to the project here, the new one and
we paste in what we had. We also have to
bring in the resource files otherwise
we're not going to find the tree.
We're going to go where the last lecture
is defined click on the file here, the
main file of it - show in Explorer. We find
this folder of images. We're going to
copy it, close this, come back to our
current project - show in Explorer, the
same thing really. And we're going to
paste in this folder of images. Ok we
have our trees. Now we can add a resource
file resources - add new - qt - resource file,
call it resource.
You want to add your prefix tip, take
this out, hit enter, add files. And you're
going to find the two images here. You
want to load them, save your thing,
come back to main.qml. We can
close this actually let's see what thing
here, close everything because I don't
want things to confuse me, open my
project again. Okay this is what we have,
we run it we're going to have everything
we had in the last lecture. Okay this is
what we had. What I want to show you is
what would happen if you specified, for
example, the color of your sky or the
ground as a gradient.
Okay let's comment this out, for example,
and put in a gradient property like this.
Gradient is really nothing but a set of
color changes. You want to set the color
of your gradient for example us going
fluently from one color to another, for
example, from red to blue. You're going to
see what I mean if you run this
application now, let's see what happens.
Okay you see that the color of the sky
is like this, it's going from dark blue
to a lighter blue. This is what the
gradient is. So if you want to use this
in our application we are going to have
problems if we try to say this States
by passing gradient like this. I'm going
to show you what I mean. I'm going to put
another gradient for the ground. Let's
comment this out and put in a gradient
and go to our state's in summer. What
many new students do is specify a
gradient like this, okay, like they
specify a color so they say gradient and
set it to something like this, for
example, put in another gradient well
this is going to be disasters.
Let's run. Your application is not even
going to run because there are
components
that are going to fail to load. This is a
bad syntax and it can be confusing for
many students if they do this. So the way
you do this, you shouldn't pass a
full-blown gradient component like this.
You should look at the gradient, you see
that it has an ID okay and it has
properties so you can actually target
this thing and change its color. Okay so
what you should do is not do something
like this, we're going to comment this
out. Instead you would do a separate
property change that targets the
gradient ctrl+a crtl+i to align.
You see that we are targeting the start
color of the sky and we are changing
this to the color that we want. And we
could do the same thing for the sky end
color crtl+a crtl+i to align.
Then we animate the changing of the
start color and the end color in our
gradient. Okay this is how you should do
it when you want to pass in States
changes from your gradient. We're going
to do the same in the spring actually
the changes we did here are for spring.
So we're going to copy them here, I'm
sorry for that if this confuses you.
We're going to put this in spring and on
top here we are going to do for summer
and in summer it's going to be like this
crtl+a crtl+i. It's nothing new
really we are just changing the colors
here let's run and see what we get. This
guy should animate correctly now. You see
that we see our thing here. We are seeing
a gradient on the ground and on the sky
and if we click you see that the sky
color changes fluidly. This is what we
want and it is a gradient and it adds a
little bit of light to your scene here. I
don't know if you can see that. So we're
going to do the same for the ground. So
in summer,
the ground is going to change till, we
want to take out the color because
that's not what we are changing, we
comment this out
and we put an gradient that changes the
ground color crtl+a crtl+i. This is
what we want in summer, we should do the
same thing in spring. Let's go down find
ground, we should take this out because
we are not changing the colors we are
changing the gradients crtl+a crtl+i
to align. And we change the ground
gradient like this, we change the start
color and the end color.
Let's run you see that the ground also
is changing accordingly following the
gradients that we said. And this is
really all I wanted to show you in this
lecture. If you want to pass gradient
changes in your property changes you
shouldn't do it like this, this is not
going to work, your application is not
even going to run. Instead you should
specify your gradients like this give
gradientstop an ID and target these
IDs to change the colors this is how you
do it. This is all for this lecture. In
the next chapter we are actually going
to start working with networking in
qml and we are going to do fun
stuff like fetching REST API and using
them in our qt quick applications. I'll see
you there