In this lecture, we're going to gently
dive in the world of working with
animations. Let's go to Qt Creator
and do that. Here we are in Qt Creator.
We are going to create our project.
It's a Qt Quick Application.
We call it 'AnimationsIntroDemo'.
Save it in a location on our drive. Hit next,
choose the Qt version you have and choose your kit and finish.
We want to change the title here.
What we are going to do is
basically to put in a rectangle and
animate it as it moves from left to
right and top to bottom. Let's put in our rectangle.
Firstly, we are going to put in a parent rectangle.
The 'id' is going to be 'container'.
It's going to 'fill' the 'parent',
and it's going to have a beige colour.
This is what we want. We also want to
give an ID to the window here. Let's call
it 'rootId' and inside, we want to put our
contained rectangle. It's ID is
going to be 'ContainedRectId'. We want
to give it a width of 100, height of 100,
and we want it to start at the position
of x 50 and y 50. We also want to give it
a colour. Let's make it dodger blue.
Now let's say that I want to animate
this rectangle as it moves from left to right.
I want to move it up to an x value
of 300 for example and I want to animate
that process of moving from left to right.
I can use a PropertyAnimation and
the way you use that you say 'PropertyAnimation'.
Let's select this and say 'on x'.
We go inside. I want to animate up to 530.
You can put in whatever you want.
And I want the animation to take two seconds
which is 2000 Milliseconds as we specify here.
Okay and if you want
to know more properties that are
available on this thing, you already know
what to do. You can select that, hit F1,
and you go in the full help mode to see
all the properties. We just used 'duration'
and the 'to' property. Let's come back.
And we can run the application and see how
it behaves. Let's run it. mm-hmm.. You see
that as we run it, it moves from left to
right, the rectangle inside. This is the
behaviour you have. The animation runs by
default even if you didn't specify for
it to run. To be able to control when it
runs and when it doesn't run, which is
what you most likely go into one, you can
put a MouseArea inside this parent
rectangle here. Let's do that. We wanted
to fill the 'parent' and when it is
clicked, we want to do something. We are
going to come to the top here. Say
'property', it's a 'boolean' and it is
'running' and it is 'false' by default
because we want the animation to be not
running. We actually want to run the
animation when you press down the mouse
and stop the animation when you release it.
This is what we're going to do.
So, we're not going to use 'onClicked', we are
going to use 'onPressed', which is this one
and 'onReleased'. And again you can
find these signals by looking at the
documentation of 'MouseArea' here. So, when
we press, we are going to set the running
property of this window here, because
that's where we defined it. We are going
to set it to 'true' when we press down. You
should actually put 'rootId'. I'll have
to do this so that things are very clear
where the properties are coming from.
When we release, we want to set this to
'false' and we want to set the running
property of the animation. We can set
that 'running', you see that we have it.
We want to say 'rootId.running'.
Okay, and this is a property bindings that runs
this property to the property that we
have at the root level. Don't be confused
by the name. The names are the same but
they are two different properties: one is
a custom property that we defined here
and another is a build-in property for the
'PropertyAnimation' that we are working with.
Now if we run the application,
the animation is not going to run by default.
We press down, it runs. We release, it stops.
This is how you can control
your animation. We can also make our
rectangle move from top to bottom.
That's what we want to do and we are going to
use a 'NumberAnimation' which is a
special kind of animation you use when
you just want to animate numbers.
So we are going to say 'NumberAnimation on y'.
We want to animate up to 300. It's going to
take two seconds as well, and it's going
to be running when we make it run. The
same as this 'PropertyAnimation' here.
So we're going to say 'rootId.running'.
Run the application. When you press down, you
see that our rectangle moves down and it
stops when it gets upto the ending
location which is a y-coordinate of 300.
You can also do a rotation animation.
Let's do that 'RotationAnimation' on
rotation.
That's the property that we want to play with.
It's going to animate up to an angle
of let's say 600. It's going to spin a
few times. It's going to take two seconds
as well. We want it to run when we press
down the mouse and stop when we
release it. And we're going to say 'rootId.running' here.
Let's run the application.
mm-hmm... and you see that as we press down
it moves to the right, moves to the bottom,
and it rotates. And just like this,
we have covered a few basics of how you
work with animations in your QML code.
You basically specify your properties
like we specified this rectangle here.
And then you specify the animations that
are going to animate the changes in
properties. In our case, we animated the
changes in X, the changes in Y and the
changes in rotation for our rectangle here.
If you want to know more on these animations,
you can select them, hit F1,
come back in full help mode and look at.
'PropertyAnimation' provides a way to
animate changes to a property's value.
Come back to the code. Look at 'NumberAnimation'.
We do the same thing. It is a
specialized PropertyAnimation that
defines an animation to be applied when
a numerical value changes. And they do
what we basically did. RotationAnimation
is the same for rotation. It gives
control over the direction of rotation
during an animation. Now you have all
that you need to start playing with it
in your QML applications.
In the next lecture, we're going to look at how you
work with standalone animations.
I'll see you there.