In this lecture, we're going to see
how you can group your animations using
ParallelAnimations or SequentialAnimation.
We're going to go to Qt Creator and play with this.
Here we are in Qt Creator.
We're going to create our project.
It's a Qt Quick Application.
We call it 'GroupedAnimationsDemo'.
We save it in the usual location,
choose our Qt Version, choose our kit and finish.
We want to change the title here to say 'Grouped Animations Demo'.
We want to give it an ID and
define a 'property' for 'animationDuration'.
It's going to start at 500. Inside we
want to have a 'Rectangle'. Let's put some space here.
We wanted to 'fill' the 'parent'
and we want its 'color' to be 'gray'.
Inside we have another 'Rectangle'. Its ID
is going to be 'circleId', because we want
this to be a circle, 'width' is going to be
100, 'height' is going to be 100. And its
'radius', we're going to make it big enough
to make it a circle, so I'm going to put
in 70 here. And its 'color' is going to be
'yellowgreen'. Why not? Now we want to
animate it. What we want to animate is
its X position and its Y position and we
want to wrap those animations in either
a parallel animation or a sequential
animation. These animations are exactly
what they sound like.
Parallel animations make your
animations happen at the same time in
parallel and sequential animations make
them run one after another. We're going
to start by SequentialAnimation. We're
going to give it an ID. This will do. And
it's going to contain two
NumberAnimation.
You want to do it like this. We want to
make them standalone for the first one.
The 'target' is going to be 'circleId', the
'property' is going to be "X". It is going to
animate 'to' 'rootId.width - width'. It's
going to start 'from' 0 and the
'duration' is going to be 'animationDuration',
that we specified at the start
of this lecture here. The properties are
really going to be the same for the
other animations. So we're going to copy
this and put that here and we should
flag here that we want to animate X.
This is better for readability if we
come back to look at this piece of code
later. We want to animate 'circleId', the
'property' is going to be "Y". We're going to
animate 'to' 'rootId.height - height' and it should
start at 0. This is what we want and when
we click in this parent rectangle here,
we want to start the animation. So we
should put our MouseArea inside, it's
going to 'fill' the 'parent'
and when it is clicked, we want to reset
the values and animation. So we say 'circleId'.
Because X and Y might have been changed
by the animation, we want to reset that
to zero. So we say 'circleId.x' equals zero,
'circleId.y' equals zero. This is how we
reset and we want to start this
SequentialAnimation here. I actually
think this ID is not adequate, so I'm
going to change this to 'groupedAnimId'
and the way you start the animation is
the usual thing really. You say
'groupedAnimId.start()' and we should have our
animation running. Notice that it is a
SequentialAnimation that we had here,
and inside we are animating X and we are
animating Y. So what is going to happen?
Our circle here is going to move from
left to right and then it's going to
move from top to bottom and all that is
going to happen in this time 'duration' here.
Now we can run the application.
Ok you see we have our 'yellowgreen'
rectangle, we click, nothing happens.
Why is that? Why is that? Let's go back to our
MouseArea and if you look, we made a
small mistake. The 'to' location should be
in relation to the 'circleId' so we
shouldn't say - 'width' here we should say
'circleId.width'. Let's correct that.
Ok, 'circleId.width' and 'circleId.height' here.
It is easy to make mistakes like this.
Let's run.
If we click in the gray area, you see
that it goes from left to right and then
from top to bottom. This is what we want
and if you notice, I put a debug
statement in here to just know that I
clicked in the MouseArea. I love to have
my develop formation. You can check it
out if you want. It is this line here.
Okay this is a SequentialAnimation.
If we want it, we will do that in parallel.
So we can actually comment this out
This is going to be messy but it's going to
remind you that you can do sequential
and parallel animation. So we're going to
say 'ParallelAnimation' and put a
brackets like this. So we change the
SequentialAnimation to a ParallelAnimation
and if you want to switch, you
can just uncomment and comment the other.
We're going to run the application and I
will try to guess what's going to happen.
Our animation is going to happen at the
same time. It is moving from left to
right and from top to bottom at the same time.
That's why you see it move like this,
along this diagonal line.
This is what we have. This is really all
to working with sequential and parallel
animation. But before we wrap up this lecture,
I would like to show you a
little bit about easing and overshoots.
I'm going to go to this Y animation here,
and I'm going to set an 'easing.type', it's
going to be 'Easing.OutBounce' and the
amplitude, we can set the amplitude for this thing.
Let's make that 3.
Run the application and see what it looks like.
If you run you see that
it looks like a bouncing ball and this is
one of the effects you can achieve using easing.
This is cool. Right? Okay this is
all we have for this lecture and the
next one we're going to do a demo and
animate a ball falling from the top.
I'll see you there.