In this lecture, we're going to look at
Easings for your animations. Easing is a
grouped property that controls how your
animation changes over time. What do I mean?
If we look at the app we have here
which is what we'd like to build in this
lecture, we start by a Linear animation
here and you see that everything is
linear. The animation starts and finishes
at a constant speed. If you look at InQuad here,
you see that it starts out slow
and it ends fast. And we have all
kinds of animations in here, they are all
different in their own ways. But notice
that it is one animation, it starts and
finishes in one location. We are just
changing the easing type, okay, the way
the animation changes over time within
this distance from the start to finish.
And if we go on its online documentation,
you see that there is a bunch of
properties that we can set for this. You
can set the type of the curve and
depending on the curve that you have, you
can set all these other properties. They
say to specify this in curve, you need to
specify a type. For some curves you can
also specify amplitude, period and
overshoot. If you go down here, they show
you how you can apply these settings.
Okay, you have a PropertyAnimation and you
put an 'easing.type' here and they show
you the available types. Okay, and easing type
can be Linear. You see that the
curve here is linear. InQuad starts out slow and fast.
Okay you see that as we
progress in time, the slope is becoming
more steep. OutQuad starts out fast and
ends slow. And you can look at all these
curves and see different properties that
they have. Now we are going to go to Qt Creator,
and play with these things.
Okay, here we are in Qt Creator.
We're going to create our project. it's a Qt Quick Application.
We call it is 'EasingDemo'.
Save it in the usual location.
Choose our Qt Version.
Choose our kit and finish.
We want to change the title here to say is 'Easings Demo'.
Okay, we want to remind ourselves of
what we want to work, we are going to
build this moving rectangle as an
external component and then we are going
to tap that into a column layout to
have this behaviour here. And the column
layout is probably going to be wrapped
in a flickable component to have this
flicking. And that's really all for this
application and we are going to be able
to apply Easing externally to the
component from the 'main.qml' file.
Let's get to work.
We're going to add a new QML file.
Right click on 'qml.qrc' here, add new,
choose Qt, choose Qt Quick.
We are going to call it the 'MovingRectangle'
because that's what it is. We want to change the Qt Quick import here.
We want to start by
putting in a few properties
that the user is going to be able to set externally.
We are going to set these properties
when we define our item in the 'main.qml' file.
Okay we want to be able to
set this background colour, the grey here.
We want to set the starting colour which
is 'beige' in general. We want to set the
ending color is in text. You see in the
middle here, the duration for the
animation, the Easing type and the width
of the container.
Okay, these are things we want.
So put them here. Inside, we want to put a rectangle.
It's ID is going to be 'smallContainerRectId1'. We're
going to give it this ID. Width is going
to be 'containerwidth', height is going to
be 50 and the color is going to be 'backgroundColor'.
Okay you see the
properties that we set here, we are
starting to use them. We have used this
'containerwidth' and we have used this
'backgroundColor'. Inside we're going to
put a 'Text' component that is going to be
Easing text.
We don't want this ID.
The text is going to be is 'easingText', what we
passed in here and we want it 'centreIn'
the 'parent'. Its parent happens to be
this rectangle here. We also want to put
another rectangle which is this small
moving rectangle in the middle here.
ID is going to be 'containedRectId1' because it is a
contained rectangle. It's color is going
to be 'startColor'. Width is going to be 50.
Height is going to be 50. We wanted to
have a border like this and a radius of 10,
because we wanted to have round edges.
We also want to put in a MouseArea
because this thing is going to be clickable.
It is going to fill the parent,
and we want to know when it is clicked.
Ok we are going to do something but
before we do anything fancy here, I want
to provide our animations. Okay because
we want this thing to animate from left
to right, it is going to start at 0, it is
going to end at the width of the window
here minus the width of the rectangle.
The first thing I want to do I want to
provide the final destination which is
'finalX'. So right here
I can come and say 'property', it is an 'int',
it is going to be called 'finalX',
the value is 'parent.width' minus 'width'
of this rectangle here. This is all we
need now. Down here we're going to put our animations,
we want to have a NumberAnimation,
it's Id is going to be 'mNumberAnimationId',
the 'target' is going
to be this rectangle here, the contained
rectangle. So we can copy the ID put that here.
That's going to work.
The 'property' that we want to animate is "X".
The 'easing.type' is going to be 'easingType',
what we paste, when we create the
component here. You see that we paste
that right here. It's a 'var' type and we
use it right here. It is going to animate
up to 'finalX' which is what we just
specified here and the duration for the
animation is going to be this property
that we paste in here. It's going to be
an 'animDuration'. We're going to be able
to set this externally. That's what we
are designing for here. We have one
'NumberAnimation' finished now. We also
want to animate the changes in color.
So , we're going to say 'ColorAnimation'.
It's going to go from 'startColor' and go to 'endColor'.
The 'duration' is going to be
the same as for the NumberAnimation, 'animDuration'
The 'target' is going to be
the same as for the NumberAnimation as well.
So we put it here. The ID is going
to be 'mColorAnimationId'.
The 'property' that we are going to animate
is going to be "color".
And for debugging purposes, we want to put in
the width of the component in a debug output
to see that our sizes are working correctly.
We're going to say 'console.log'.
This should do. Now we want to come in
our MouseArea. When we click, we want to
animate two things: one is the X position.
The rectangle is going to move from left
to right, the final destination is going
to be the width of the parent rectangle,
which is this one, minus the width of
this rectangle here. And we should
specify the width and height of this
item here, because we are going to use it in layout.
The width is going to be the
width of this rectangle, the height is
going to be the height of this rectangle here.
width: smallContainerRectId1.width
height: smallContainerRectId1.height
We want to come back to our MouseArea.
Okay when we click, we want to animate X
from 0 to this location and
animate the color changes from the startColor
to the endColor and the start and
end colors are going to be specified
externally when you define this item.
We want to start by keeping track of
whether the small rectangle is on the
left or on the right, and we do that by
defining a 'property' here. We call it 'toRight'
and it's going to start out 'false',
because our rectangles are going to
start on the left.
Inside here, we are going to say if 'toRight' equals 'false',
we're going to move to right, otherwise
we are going to move to left. But before
we do that we have to set this setting
here. So we're going to tangle the value
of 'toRight' here. If it is 'false', we want
to make it 'true'.
So, you're going to say 'toRight', it was
'true' and here we want to make it 'false',
because if we false here, it is true obviously.
Now we want to animate X, animate color.
The only thing we need to
do to animate number is called 'mNumberAnimation'
and set its 'to' value of 'finalX'.
We want to start the animation after we
do that. For the colors, we want to set
the starting color and the ending color.
So, we're going to start by the starting
color, 'mColorAnimationId.from' is  going to 'startColor'
and 'mColorAnimationI.to'
equals 'endColor' and we want to
start the animation. Just like this.
Otherwise, we're just going to do the reverse.
Let's copy this because we don't
want to type all this again. We are going
to animate back to zero and we are going
to switch 'endColor', we are going to
animate from the 'endColor' and the
destination is going to be the 'startColor'.
This is what we want.
Okay, when we click, if we are on the left, we are going
to animate to the right and if we are on
the right, we are going to animate to the left.
And this should be all for our component here.
I know it might confuse you
because I think this is the biggest
component we have whilst ever in this course.
So take a deep breath and look at
it a couple of times. You're going to
understand how it works. Now we want to
go back to the 'main.qml' file and
actually use this. We want to import
QtQuick LayOuts,
we want to use 1.4. We want to give a
window here an ID, so we're going to say
'rootID'. We also want to set the
'property' for the animation duration.
'property' and it's going to be
'animDuration',
let's start by half a second, 500 milliseconds.
Inside we want to put the
'Flickable' component. It is going to 'fill'
the 'parent' and inside that we want to
have a 'ColumnLayout'. The ID is going to be
'mColumnId' and we want to pass the
height of this column as the 'contentHeight'
of this flickable component
because that's the height of what it has
to display. So we can say 'contentHeight' here.
This is an important property for
a 'Flickable' component. We are going to say
'mColumnId.implicitHeight'. The width is
going to be that of the parent, so we're
going to say 'parent.width'. And we want the
'spacing' of 2. Now we
want to put in our 'MovingRectangle'.
Okay, we define it like this, like we
would for any other components. Okay let's
look at the properties that we can
specify. We can specify a background
color, so we should say 'backgroundColor'.
the 'backgroundColor' is going to be
"gray". We can specify the starting color
so we say 'startColor' and it's going to
be "beige". The 'endColor' is going to be
'blue' and 'animDuration' is going to be
duration from this one, but we don't want
to confuse the properties so we should
say 'animationDuration' here.
That's better.
This property is from this 'main.qml' file here.
Okay, the other one is from the 'Item' here
which is called 'animDuration'.
That's what we are setting. I hope this
makes sense. The 'easingText' is going to
be "Linear". This is what we want to see in
the middle. 'easingType' is going to be
'Easing.Linear'. The remaining property is
'containerwidth'. We should specify that.
'containerwidth', it's going to be 'rootId.width'.
Okay, by now we should be able to
run the application and see how it looks.
We are only going to have one component
but if this works correctly, it's going
to be very easy to add others. Let's run
the application. mm-hmm.... Our app is here.
If you click, nothing happens and they
say 'finalX is not defined'. Why is that?
Let's go back to our MovingRectangle and
look at 'finalX'. Why is it not recognised?
Can I not define a property here?
Let's debug and see what is happening.
Here what if I put in a static value
like 200. Let's come to the 'main.qml' file,
change a few things, put in spaces, run again.
hmmmm... I know it's not defined. Let's put
this property outside and see if this
works. I'm going to put that here and I'm
going to say this finalX is going to be
a 'smallContainerRectId1.width - containedRectId1.width'
Now let's see if this works correctly.
Let's come to main.qml, put in a
few spaces, run again.
Now it's going to work. Okay, why is it
not working here when you define a
property inside? This is a mystery to me.
Okay, keep that in mind. If you find an
answer to this mystery, you can ping me
in the QA section to tell me. I'm going
to research on this after this video. But
the important thing is that we found a
way around and it is working. And that's
a good skill as a software developer to
find ways around even if you haven't
understood yet how it works,
because sometimes you need something
that works due to time constraints.
Okay, we have our thing working here. We are
animating from left to right and that Easing type
is the Linear. If you look to the
curve we had here, linear as
is easing curse for a linear function: velocity is constant.
We want to try all these
Easings.
So we are going to come back to 'main.qml' file,
and simply copy what we have here
put in a second
MovingRectangle, the easing type we want
to test is InQuad and we want to color
to end 'green'. Let's run. Okay you see
that it is different. It starts out slow
and ends fast. And this goes only linear.
I hope you can see this. So I am going to
pause the video, put in all the other
easings and I'm going to come back to
test what we have.
I should also correct this text. It
shouldn't say 'Linear', it should say 'InQuad'.
Ok, let's change the text. Okay we
have our moving rectangles. Then you see
that there is quite a lot and that's
because there are quite a lot of easing
types that you can use in here. Okay I'm
going to let you take some time and read
on all these if you happen to need them.
But what I wanted you
to see is how they work and how you can
set those if you happen to need them.
You see that the width is in here, being
displayed linear, it's going to animate
InQuad, OutQuad. If we keep scrolling, we
can see all the others. The InBounce.
This is interesting. Let's look at this
curve. InBounce is easing curve for a bounce.
This is the curve. Okay it
follows this structure here. Okay this is
really all I've to say in this lecture.
I hope you saw how easing can effect
your animation. You see we have a
same animation from a given location to
another location, but just changing the
easing, can dramatically change how your
animation happens. And you can play with
thiese things to see what you like more.
And I want you to notice that the color
changes are also animated. Look at this
color it starts out 'beige' and it fluidly
changes to another color. Okay, this is
another thing you should know too.
Okay, this is all for now.
In the next lecture, we're going to look
at grouped animations. I'll see you there