In this lecture we want to look at the
focus scope qml component. This component
is very helpful when you are using
external components in your main.qml
file. Let's go to QT Creator, create a
new project and show you what I mean.
Okay so here we are in QT Creator. We
are going to create a new project. We
call it focus scope demo. Hit Next.
Choose your QT version here and your
desktop kit as usual. Let's change the
title to say focus. We want to create a
rectangle component inside. Give it a
width of 300, a height of 50, a color of
beige. I love page.And we make it focused.
Inside we are going to put a text
component. The text is going to say
default by default. And it's going to be
centered in the parent. Its parent
happens to be this rectangle here. Let's
call this container red. Because we want
this rectangle to tell us when it has
focus ,we are going to use the keys
attached property. And we are going to
check if it is the key number one that is
correct. So you already know how to do
this if event key equals Qt key one. Be
careful on the spelling that you use
here. Here it is lowercase K. Here it is
capital K. We are going to set the text
of this text component to let us know
that we have pressed on the key one here. So
let's give it an ID
and we are going to say text ID text
equals. We want to test for at least
another key. If the key is two, we are
going to say we pressed on key two. Else
we are going to say pressed on another
key. And we are going to say whatever key
it is by adding it's key to this
string here. So we're going to say event
key. Let's run the application.
Okay we have our base rectangle, I click
on one, press on one. I press
two. I press some other key and it gives
me the key that I pressed. This is what
we want. So let's say we want to
instantiate our rectangle component
multiple times. And we don't want to go
copy paste since we already know how to
create custom components. We are going to
create an external component of this
rectangle and instantiate it whenever we
need it in the main.qml file. Let's
create another qml file. So we're going
to add new  qml file QT quick two - and
we call it MButton. It is going to be in
this project. So we go into main.qml file
and copy our rectangle here. We are going
to get rid of this and paste it in here
and change the import here to 2.11,
because that the version of QT Quick we
are using. And because we are arguing qml
citizens, we are going to wrap this into
an item element. So let's do that
and expose the width of this thing. So
that we can put it in positioners like
row and columns. Its width is going to be
container rect ID width. And its height
is going to be container high. And we
also want to expose this color so that
we can specify it whenever we
instantiate it in the main.qml file. So
we are going to use the property
alias. And it is going to refer to the
container
rect ID color. And an alias is really a
way to give your properties a nickname.
So that you can use them under that
different name. But this time we are
defining this alias in the root scope of
this item. So it will be available for
other components from the main qml file.
So what we want to do is to instantiate
our MButton component. We are going to
say BMutton and you see that it is
recognized. So this is the first one. And
we are going to instantiate the second
one. But for the second one, we want to
change the color to green so that we can
differentiate them. Remember that we
exposed the color property through this
property alias. Okay to position this
things nicely, we're going to wrap them
into a column and component. Copy this
and paste it it down here. Run the
application and see what we get. Which
one has focus. Let's click on one and you
see that number one has focus. So let's
give the first button focus.
Run the application. I click on one, no
effect. I click on two, no effect. I click
on other buttons, no effect. You see that
it seems like neither button has focus.
Let's comment this out. Give the second
rectangle focus. Run the application. And
if we click on one, you see that it looks
like the first button has focused even
if we explicitly told the second button
to have the focus. This is the problem
that comes with using external
components in your qml files when
transferring focus. Research can be
unpredictable when you set focused your
components. To solve this problem, you
just have to wrap your components into a
focused scope component. So let's do that.
Just like this. Let's go to the main file
and change it a little bit. Because
sometimes when you don't change the main
qml file, QT Creator doesn't pick the
changes you made in external components.
So I'm going to add a space here. Run
again. Click on one and you see that the
second button has focus. This is what we
set here.
Let's move the focus to the first button
like this. Run our application. Click on
one, you see one has focus. And you can
see that by wrapping your external
component into a FocusScope, the
results of setting you focus property on
your component is much more predictable.
This is what I wanted you to see in this
lecture. If you want to learn more about
the focus scope component, you can select
it and hit F1. And you're going to have a
piece of documentation that you can read.
But it just says that focus scopes assist
in keyboard focus handling when building
reusable
components. And this is what we just did.
Discoverers always setup during this
lecture. In the next chapter, we're going
to start and look at javascript and see
how you can use it to add some
interactivity to your qml. And if you
noticed, we have been using JavaScript
all along. But we are going to explain
these things and shed some light on them.
I see you in the next lecture.