This chapter is all about user input. We
are going to look at the elements that
allow the user to type in some text like
TextInput and TextEdit. We are going to
look more on the MouseArea that we've
been using and look at some more of its
signals. We are also going to look at how
you can know which key on your keyboard
was clicked. The other thing we'll see is
how you transfer focus between you or UI
components using KeyNavigation and how
you make sure that focus is transferred
correctly in your custom components. In
the next lectures we are going to tackle
these subjects, starting with TextInput
in the next one. I'll see you in the
next lecture.