In this lecture we are going to look at
the text input element of QT quick. To
show of its powers, we are going to build
the contact panel like this, where the
user is going to be allowed to type in
the first name and last name. Let's go to
QT creator and do this. Here we are in QT
creator. We are going to create our
project. It is a "QT Quick Application". We
are going to name it "TextInputDemo",
save it in the usual location. We want to
use this as the default location because
this is a new chapter. Let's choose our
Kit, choose "Desktop". And we have our
project here. The title is going to say
"TextInput...". We are going to specify our
Row. Give it the next Y location, specify
the spacing of 10.
You probably remember the "Row" component
from previous lectures. It is used to
layout things from left to right. Inside
we are going to put a Rectangle. This is
for the first name. Inside we are going
to put in a Text element for the text.
This is going to work like a label. And
it should be centered in the parent.
Now we want to specify the width and
height of this rectangle in relation to
the size of the text. That is in here. The
way we do that you probably know all
this from the previous lectures. The width
equals firstNameLabelId.implicitWidth.
We add a margin of 20. Let's type
width well. Height is going to be the same.
Let's run this to see what it looks like.
Mm-hmm we have a label saying FirstName.
This looks good.
We want to add a TextInput element
that is inside the rectangle as well. So
that things look a little bit consistent.
So we are going to add the rectangle
again. Inside we are going to put a
TextInput element. The ID is going to be
firstName... Text is going to be: "Type in
your first name". Why not? And it is going
to be centered in the parent as well. So
we're going to say anchors.centerIn,
parent. And it should have the focus so
we should set "focus: true". If you
look at TextInput, let's look at it in
the documentation. We select it, hit F1. It
is going to open. In help to the right
here, click on this button on top. Open in
help mode to have it shown in
full-screen. Let's look at all the
members including inherited members. And
if you look down we're going to find a
property called "focus" and this property
holds whether the item has focused
within the enclosing focused scope, okay?
It basically says if
sytem has focus. We are not going to go
into focus scope by now. We are going to
look at that later in the chapter. But we
have our TextInput now. And we can run
to see it in action.
Mm-hmm you see that...