In this lecture we're going to look at
the MouseArea and how you capture mouse
events using it. We're also going to look
at how you can build the drag and drop
features in your QML elements.
Let's go to Qt Creator and play with it.
Here we are in QT creator. We're going to
start a new project.
It's a Qt Quick application. We are going
to call it MouseAreaDemo, store it in
the usual location. Hit "Next", choose our
"Build System" and make it "qmake", choose
your QT version and choose your Kit. We
are going to change the title to "MouseArea
Demo". And inside we are going to put
a Rectangle. It's going to have the same
width as the parent and its parent is
this window here so it's going to be 640
in width.
Let's give it height of 200, a color of
"beige". Inside this rectangle we're going
to put a MouseArea like we've been
doing all along. It's going to fill its
parent which is this rectangle here. And
we should give it an id, this rectangle.
Let's call it containerRectId. And in
the onClicked
handler, we're going to use something. We
want to move this rectangle to the
location where the user clicked the
mouse on the x coordinate. So to do that
you need to capture the parameter of
this MouseEvent. Okay that's what I want
you to see. Let's visit this MouseArea
component. We haven't really talked about
it so much. Let's go to the documentation,
type in "MouseArea", look at the
documentation. And it is "an invisible
item that is typically used in
conjunction with a visible item". We have
been using it inside rectangles in order
to provide mouse
handling for that item. Okay that's what
we've been doing. But what I want you to
see is the signals that this MouseArea
can emit and among those signals there
is one that we have been using a lot
which is called "clicked". Let's click on
it. You see that it has a parameter that
is called MouseEvent. Let's click on
this MouseEvent. And you can see that it
has a few properties: two of them are the
x-coordinate where the user clicked on
the mouse and the y-coordinate where the
user click on the mouse. Okay this is
what we want. There are other things you
can work with, all these properties are
there for you to use. But we are going to
focus on x and y here. This MouseEvent is
available to you under an object called
"Mouse". So we can actually say the
location where they use a click by doing
console.log(mouse.x), for example. Let's
run the application. You can see that it
shows the location where we click and
this rectangle here. So let's try and go
to the top. And it's 1. And it still. I'm
trying to get... Oh, I got a 0.
I was trying to get a 0. You now know
that we can capture the x and
y coordinates
in the MouseEvent. So what we want to do
is put another rectangle inside this
rectangle here and move it in a location
where we clicked the mouse, on the x
coordinates. Let me show you what I mean.
We are going to put a rectangle inside.
"id" is going to be movingRectangleId.
The width is going to be 50 and the
height is going to be the same as the
width. So it's also going to be 50.
We're going to give it a color of blue.
So what we want to do when we click on
this MouseArea is to move the moving
rect to a location where we click the
mouse. And that location is stored and
the Mouse object that comes with this onClicked
event. And the x property of it. So
if we run this application the blue
rectangle is going to be in the top left
of this rectangle, which is the top left
of the window object here. Let's run. Okay
we see our blue rectangle here. If we
click on the outside here, in the white
space, we are not going to see anything.
Why is that? The MouseArea is attached
to this rectangle. And it has a height of
200 and this space is out of this
Clickable area. The Clickable area is
this beige area here, which is this
rectangle that we defined. And we set
this MouseArea to fill this rectangle.
So the area outside this rectangle is
not going to be Clickable. At least it's
not going to be handled by this MouseArea
that we defined here. But if we
click inside. See what happens? The blue
rectangle moves to our new location. Okay
so this is how you can capture Mouse
events, capture the location where they
use a click and use that in your
application. Okay so this is working fine
and correct. One thing I want to point
out is that the location of this MouseArea
is very critical. I have seen many
students doing something like this. I'm
going to copy this MouseArea, put it
inside this rectangle, it will do
something like this. If you do this, this
MouseArea is not going to handle this
parent rectangle. It's going to handle
this blue rectangle. So let's run the
application. If you click on the outside
in the beige rectangle you're not going
to get any MouseEvent because the MouseArea
is attached to this blue rectangle
here. And one thing I want you to see is
that the mouse coordinates. Now
I'm working
inside this blue rectangle because
that's where the MouseArea is attached.
So if you click to the top here you're
going to see 0, ok? The coordinates are
inside this blue rectangle. They are not
in this beige rectangle. So you really
need to be careful where you put your
MouseAreas and know the coordinates
that you are working in. I hope this
makes sense. So I am going to take this
MouseArea back and put it where it
should be.
This is going to be fine. Run the
application. And this is what we want. The
other signal we're going to look at is
WheelEvent which is "emitted in
response to mouse wheel and trackpad
scroll gestures". We are going to use it
for the mouse wheel for now. So let's
look at the properties that this event
has. You can see the x and y position. We
also have a property called angleDelta
which indicates if you are rotating the
wheel in the positive direction or in the
negative direction. We're going to try
this out. Let's go back to our code and
capture another event. Say onWheel,
console.log some properties about this
wheel event. The x-coordinate is going to
be wheel.x, the y-coordinate is going to
be wheel.y. And the angle is going to be
angleDelta. Let's run the application.
I roll it upwards, and you see that the
second parameter of the point is
+100. I roll it
downwards, you see that it is negative. If
it is positive you are rotating upwards.
If it's negative you are rotating
downwards. And you can do some processing
based on this in
QML application. The other thing I want
you to see is how to work with hover
events in this MouseArea. You first have
to enable hover by setting this property
to "true", hoverEnabled and then handle
the hover event. So how do we do that? We
are going to set a property hoverEnabled,
set this to "true" and do onHoverChanged
inside. We are going to test for
something. There is another property we
can use. There is this property that is
"true" when the MouseArea contains the
mouse and it is false when the MouseArea
doesn't contain the mouse. So we can
use this we are going to say if containsMouse
equals to "true". We want to change
the color of the movingRect to red,
movingRectId.color. And if it doesn't
contain the mouse we are going to set
its color to green. Let's run the
application. So when it starts it's going
to be blue. When we hover on it, it's
going to turn red because it's going to
contain the mouse. When we take the mouse
out it's going to turn green. Okay so
blue.
And hover on it, it turns red. When I go
out it doesn't turn green. Why is that?
The MouseArea is in the beige space
here. Now you see how not getting clear
where your MouseArea is operating can
become a problem. Okay so if I want this
behavior to only affect this rectangle I
have no choice but to move the MouseArea
back inside this rectangle. But now
you get the idea of what we are trying
to do. But to make things less confusing
I'm going to affect this beige rectangle
and not this blue rectangle. Let's go
back to our code.
This is going to be a fast change. So
it's going to be containerRectId that
we affect. Change this to the correct
rectangle, change this to the correct
rectangle. Run again. We go into this, it
turns red. We go back it turns green. And
you can see that our onClick event is
still working as it should. Now that we
have worked with this I want to show you
how you can drag and drop. We have done
quite a lot in this rectangle here. So I
think it's a good idea to actually
create another one. Let's do that. I'm
going to copy this. I'm going to go down
here and paste in this thing and create
a new rectangle. Inside we are going to
put another rectangle. So I'm going to
copy this we give it an id of draggableRect
because we want to drag it. But we want
this to be on a y-coordinate of 250 so
that they don't overlap. So we're going
to say y equals 250. Let's run the
application. We have our new rectangle. So
what we want to do is to enable the
dragging of this contained Rectangle.
To do that we are going to put
in a MouseArea. You probably guessed
this. It's going to fill its parent. So
the way you enable dragging, we want to
only drag on the x-axis. But you can drag
in whatever direction you want, x or y. We
are going to specify our drag target. And
it is going to be this draggableRect
here. We specify its id. We are going to
specify the access that we want to drag
on.
So we specify it like this.
This axis, you can specify x, y, or x and
y. We are going to use x right now. The
last thing we need to do is to specify
the drag maximum and minimum. So drag.
minimumX is going to be 0.
drag.maximumX is going to be the
width of this container rectangle minus
the width of this contained rectangle.
We're going to say dragContainerId.width
- draggableRect.width. To really show the
effects of this dragging we want to handle
the event that is fired when the x
position of this rectangle is changed. We
want to do something like onExchanged.
And we are going to output the
x-coordinate. We are going to output it
here. If you run this application
dragging is going to be enabled for this
drag container rectangle. And we are
going to be able to drag the contained
rectangle. Whenever it's moving it is
going to tell us where it moves that. And
these are the properties that enable our
dragging behavior. Let's run the
application. Mm-hmm you see that we can
drag from left to right. The minimum is 0.
The maximum is the width of this
rectangle minus the width of this one.
This covers all the set up to do in this
lecture. I hope you now have a better
idea of what you can do with the MouseArea
and how you can drag and drop your
contain rectangles. In the next lecture
we're going to look at how you can
handle key events in your QML
applications using the keys attached
property. I'll see you in the next
lecture.