In this lecture we are looking at keys
attached properties and how you use them
to give superpowers to your qml
components. So what are attached
properties anyway? They are properties
you attach to your qml components and
give them powers that they otherwise
wouldn't have had to make things clear.
Let's go to QT creator and play with us.
Okay so here we are in QT creator. We are
creating a new project as we always do.
We call it keys attached property demo,
store it in the usual location, choose
our QT version. Choose your Q and
finish. Let's change the title to say
keys attached and put a rectangle inside.
We are going to say rectangle, give it a
width of 300, why not? A height of 50. Give
it a color of dodgerblue. We Center it in
the parenting and set focused to
true. We want to give it the focus so
that it receives key events. What we want
to do is type keys on digit 1. Press for example.
And console.log.
Pressed on key one. Let's run this
application and see what it does. You
probably guess that we are going to
press the one button on our keyboard and
we are going to have a message in the
application output pane here if it works
as we expect. So I click on one and you
see that it says pressed on one. This is
how you capture events in your QML
objects. You give them the focus if they
don't have it, and then you handle events
for different keys like we need here.
Keys on digit 1 pressed. To see the full
list of these events, let's go to the
documentation and search for keys. And
if you go down in the signals here you
can see all these signals here that you
can handle. But this list of signals is
not exhaustive, not every signal is
documented in here and that's why they
give you this pressed event where you
can check the clicked event yourself. So
what we're going to do here is to do
keys Onpressed.
Handle that event. And from the
documentation, you see that this pressed
event passes in a key event, and this
event has the key that was pressed as a
property so we can check for it. So right
now we are going to do this check. We are
going to say if event key equals QT
key one we are going to output something.
We are going to say something here.
console.log. Pressed on key 1 and we are
going to comment this out to make sure
that it is this one that is working. Run
the application. Press on 1. And you see
that we receive the event. You have two
ways you can capture your key events in
your QML
applications. You can capture events for
the particular events that are provided
here ,or you can use the pressed event
and check for the key that was pressed
yourself, and do appropriate action in
your qml application. So what if you have
these two signals handled? Let's see what
happens.
Run the application. You click on one. You
see that one signal is being fired. The
other one is not being fired. Which one
is being fired here? To differentiate
that let's flag in the console here. Say
that it is the specific signal. We're
going to say specific and say general
signal. Run the application. If we click
one, you see that the specific signal
takes priority over this general signal.
If you want both of these handlers to be
called you need a way to let on digit
one pressed here. Give a chance to the
second handler here to run. And the way
you do that you say event accepted and
set this to false. And what this is doing?
It is flagging this event as not handled
and other signal handlers that might be
interested in handling this event are
going to be fired. And in this case key is
onpressed is going to be fired and we
are going to capture it here and output
our console message here. Let's run the
application. Press 1 and you see that now
both signal handlers are being called. To
prove our case let's set this event
accepted property to true and you're
going to see that only these specific
signal is going to be fired and handled.
One signal the specific one.
Another thing I want you to see is how
to work with modifiers. How do you know
if the user pressed your key while
pressing for example the control key, the
shift key, and things like that. Let's add
another Key Handler. And we want to
capture the handler for the key file.
Okay. We want to detect if the user
pressed the key number five while
pressing down the control modifier. So we
want to say if event.modifiers equals
control modifier, which is this one we
want to say pressed control five. And if
it's not, okay. And you might wonder how
do I know this. Let's go back to the
documentation. This is the only source of
truth
when in doubt. Let's go back a little bit.
On digit five pressed, you see that
there's an event parameter that is
passed in here. Let's look at it and it
has a modifiers property, which says the
modifiers that you can pass in here. We
are interested in the control modifier
that says a control key on the keyboard
is pressed. This is how you check these
things. And they give you a nice example
you can look at. But we are going to test
this in our code anyway. Let's run the
application.
I press number five it's going to say
pressed regular five. I hold the control
key down, press five and you can see that
it is saying pressed ctrl 5. This is cool.
So if you want to do the same thing to
check for the modifiers, while using the
unpressed signal how do you do that? One
way I can think of is to actually cheat
from the documentation. You just saw this.
You can copy this and modify it to suit
our needs. I am going to comment this out
because I want to have the same effect
as this one . I am going to paste in my
code here. We want to check for the key
number five, so we are going to change
this to key_5. Go down to key_5 we want to
change this to a triple equal sign
because that's more safer. And we want to
check for the control modifier. Let's
copy this and put that inside here. We
are checking to see if the pressed key
is key number five. And we are doing an
end operation with this expression which
checks to see if the control key is
pressed. If all this is true we are going
to know that control five is pressed. Run
the application hit control 5. And you
see that we have our thing working.
I hope this opens your eyes on ways you
can use the keys attached property to
handle any key in your QML application.
In the next lecture we are going to look
at how you can transfer focus between
your QML components in your user
interface. i'll see you in the next lecture.