In this lecture we are looking at the
key navigation attached property. This is
a property that adds focus navigation
properties to focusable UI components.
Let's go to QT creator and play with it.
Here we are in QT creator. Let's
create a new project. We call it key
navigation demo. Store it in the usual
location. Hit next. Choose the Q... choose
the QT version that you have installed.
And choose Ok. We want to change the
title here to key navigation demo. We are
going to add a row component inside. It's
going to be in the center of the
rectangle. So we're going to Center it in
the parent. And we are going to put two
rectangles inside. There it is. Going to
be firstrectID. The Width is going
to be 200 and the height is going to be
equal to the width. We want to have a
border color of black. We want the
rectangle to have a color of green and
we want it to start with the focus set
to true. It's going to start focused it's
going to be able to receive key events,
because we want to know when it has
focus. We are going to add the keys
attached property and listen for the key
number 5 being pressed. You already know
how to do this from the last lecture, and
we are going to say console.log I am
rect1 to know that it is the first
rectangle here that has focus. We
actually want to copy this rectangle and
paste it down here and modify it a
little bit. We are going to change the ID
and it is going to be blue, why not.
It's not going to have the focus by
default because we want the first one to
start with the focus. And when you hold
down the key number five it is going to
say I am red 2. Okay now we get to use
key navigation. Key navigation is a
property that allows you to navigate
through your UI components, when some key
is pressed. Let's go to each
documentation. Okay you can see that we
can detect when the backtab is collect
down, left, right, up and the tab key. So we
want to move the focus to the right for
this first rectangle, when you click on
the right button. So we are going to say
keys: key navigation, right. And it's going
to move to second rect ID. You specify
your target element by its ID. We want to
do something similar to the second
rectangle here. When you click on the
Left button, while this rectangle has
focus, we are going to transfer focus to
the first rectangle, which is identified
by this ID, first rect ID and we do that
like this. Okay and how do you know which
rectangle has focus? We are going to
press on the key number five and it's
going to tell us which rectangle has
focus, like we do in the console out here.
Let's run the application. Okay we have
two rectangles. The rectangles are laid
out in a row component and the green
rectangle because it is the first one is
going to be to the left. The blue
rectangle is second in the row component
and it's going to be to the right. Okay
so what we want to do is to hold down
the
key number five and you see that
rectangle one has focus. I'm going to
touch the right arrow key on my keyboard
and click on number five again. You see
that rect two has focus. Click on the
left arrow key. Click on five. You see
that rect one has focus. And you can see
that we are successfully transferring
focus from one rectangle to another
using this key navigation attached
property. And again it is an attached
property because the rectangle doesn't
have these properties by default. We are
attaching these properties using this
key navigation component here. This is
what is meant when somebody says that a
property is an attached property. Another
thing we can do to make these Apple
powers even better is to handle the
unfocused changed signa. Okay so if the
focus changes we are going to check and
see if focus equals to true for this
component for this rectangle here. If
it's true we are going to set its color
to gray, and if it isn't we are going to
turn it back to green. We are going to do
something similar to the second
rectangle. But when it is not focused, we
are going to turn the color back to
being blue, because that's what it was.
And we need to surround this with quotes
like this. Let's run the application. We
click on the right. You see that the
second rectangle has focused so it turns
gray. If we hold down the key number five,
it's going to tell us the same thing,
that it has focused. We turn it to the
left the first rectangle turns gray, but
the second rectangle lost focus so it
turns back to blue. Okay this should
give you an introduction on how to work
with key navigation to transfer focus
between you you icon.
But if we go back to the documentation
for key navigation and look at the
description you see that they have an
example here that we can try out. Okay so
it basically is four rectangles that are
wrapped in a grid component, and the grid
component is basically laying your
rectangles or whatever is inside into a
grid structure. We have the first
rectangle, the second rectangle, the third
one and the fourth one. And if you look
at the properties they have the width
and height, they have a color that
depends on whether or not the rectangle
is focused, and they transfer focus when
you hold down the right key while this
rectangle has focus focus is going to go
to the top right and you can see the
sentence. Okay so I am going to copy all
this code up to here. Comment out what we
have in our application so far so you
don't want to delete it. You want to keep
it for reference if you need it in the
future. But we are going to paste in the
code from the documentation. Okay so we
have our width component here. Let's run
the application and see what it looks
like. M-hmm what is wrong.
We didn't close the last bracket here so
we should close it.
This looks good. And down here you see
that it is smashed. Let's run again. You
see that this thing is showing but it is
really small. Let's click on right
you see that focus goes to the right.
Down goes down. Left it goes left. But
this is very small and it is not
centered, so we can use our qml powers to
turn it into what we want. I am going to
get rid of this width and height, because
I don't need it.
I am going to Center it in the parent,
and its parent is this window here and I
am going to turn its width and height to
100 because 50 is too small to see. Let's
do 100. Copy this. Paste it here, Paste it
here. We basically paste it everywhere,
where we need it. Let's run the
application. It should be in the center
now and our rectangles should be bigger.
Right, bottom, left, top. This is really
good. This is nothing different from what
we did before here. But they are using
ternary operators here to change the
color of the rectangle based on whether
or not the rectangle has focus. This is
the only different thing really. The
other fans are just transferring focus
to the ID of interest. This covers all
we set up to do in this lecture. And the
next one we're going to look at the
concept called focus school. I'll see you
in the next lecture.