In this lecture we are looking at the
TextEdit element. From the documentation
they say that "TextEdit item displays a
block of editable, formatted text". And
this is a small example of how you use
it. So let's copy this and create a new
project.
It's a QT quick application. We're going
to call it TextEditDemo. Save it in the
usual location. Choose our kit. And we are
going to paste in the text that we
copied. Ctrl+A, Ctrl+I to line up things
nicely. And change the title here to "TextEdit Demo".
Let's run the application. Okay,
you see that we see our text here. But we
are seeing these tags here. Why is
that? That is because we didn't set the
text format to rich text. Okay this is
used to show simple texts like this. Run
again.
Okay you see that it says "Hello World".
But if you want these tags to be
processed you can do something like "textFormat"
"RichText". I think yes. And we can
now use the text that we had here from
the Qt documentation. These are HTML tags,
if you are familiar with HTML. Let's do
this. And if we run "Hello" is going to be
bold, "World" is going to be in italic, just
like this. You can also position this
thing in the middle as we've been doing
all along anchors.centerIn:parent.
Run again.
Okay you can also delete and edit the
text. This is a TextEdit element by the
way. Okay but this thing can handle
multiple lines of text. So what I'm going
to do is bringing some text that I have
prepared that has some features that I
want to show off. I want to separate this
in different lines. So that things are
very visible because this is a long
piece of text. And I want you to notice
that inside we have "strong" tags that
we're going to make the text bold.
We have carriage return characters and
newline characters inside. We also have
set the font color to be red for this
piece of text here. If we run this we're
going to see that our text is clipped
off. It is trying to show this in one
line but the width is just not enough to
do that. So what is happening here the
text is being chopped off to our width. If
you want the text to be shown we
should use the "wrap" property. Okay, so we
can use TextEdit.Wrap. Run to see the
effect of this. You can see that our text
is wrapping in the "div" and width of our
TextEdit here, which is 240. But it is
also not showing in the available height
that we have here. So we should do
something. It would really help if we
could scroll through the text to see
what is being shown in here. And the way
to do that, you wrap your TextEdit into
a Flickable element. If we look for
Flickable
in the documentation we see that it is
an item that wraps its children on a
surface that "can be dragged and flicked
causing the view onto the child items to
scroll". And this is what we want. We want
to be able to flick through the text
that we have in our TextEdit element. So
we are going to create a Flickable
element. We're going to take this TextEdit.
Wrap it all.
And put it inside our Flickable element.
We give it an id and the width of this
Flickable is going to be the width of
this textInputId. You need to
tell this Flickable element the height
of the contents that it is expected to
show. And you specify that using the
contentHeight property. And it's going
to be textInputId.implicitHeight
because this is the height of the text
that we want to show. But we should also
give it a height. So we are going to give
it a height of 300. Let's run and see
what we have. Notice that we can scroll
now but the text is not centered and we
can't really scroll. It is still trying
to show the entire height of the text. So
what we can do we can clip this text. Set
the "clip" property of this then to true.
And take this centerIn statement here
back to the parent item, which is the
Flickable element. Run the application
again. And this is much better. Now you
can see that we can scroll through the
entire text that we have. It's bold
because we set it to strong in the text
here. You can see that "localhost" is in
red text because we wrapped that into
the font tags and give it a color
attribute. You can also see that the
TextEdit element supports many properties
that we have seen to the Text element. We
have the color of the text. We have the
font. The last thing I want to show you
in this lecture is how you can capture
the text that is inside this thing here.
You can attach in onEditingFinished
signal and say console.log("The current text
is: ",
0:06:27.060,0:06:36.240
say the text. Okay just like this. But
to do this you need a way to take focus
from this TextEdit here. So to do that
we are going to give it an id. And down
below we are going to put a Rectangle
inside we have a MouseArea.
The width is going to be 200. Why not? I
just going to be 100 and color is going
to be red. Let's make it red. And we
wanted to be shown to the bottom of the
Flickable element. We want the top line
of this rectangle to be to the bottom of
the Flickable. So we're going to say
anchors.top: mFlickable.bottom.
Let's run to see if the position is what
we want. Okay,
this works fine. And when we click in the
MouseArea we want to give the focus to
the rectangle. So we say mRectId.focus,
it was true. Let's try this.
Run the application. When we click on
this thing we are wrapping the text
inside this TextEdit. Let's delete the
entire text and say "This is my new text".
Click this thing. And you see that it
says... Let's search actually. Ctrl, find
"This is my...", "my new text". And you see that
this is what we just typed in here. Okay
you can wrap the text by listening on
the onEditingFinished. But you can
also directly wrap the text inside here
if you happen to need that. And it's very
easy to do. You can say console.log("The
new text"). And you pass in the id for the
TextInput. So we're going to say
TextInput.text. Just like this you have to
append the text to this string here. And
when you click this thing we have the
text that we want. This covers our usage
of TextInput. You can use it to show
some text. You can use some HTML tags to
make your text beautiful. For that work
you have to set the textFormat to
TextEdit.RichText here. You also can set
different "wrap" modes to have different
effects for your text. And you can look in
the documentation for the options that
are available for the wrap mode that you
can use in here. This cover all you have
to do in this lecture. In the next
one we're going to look at the MouseArea
in a little bit more detail and see
how you can use it to drag and drop
elements. I'll see you in the next
lecture.